<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org</title><link>https://paregorios.org/</link><description>Tom Elliott's blog and personal site</description><atom:link href="https://paregorios.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:ipse@paregorios.org"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;&lt;img
alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
property="dct:title"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;paregorios.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by
&lt;a xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" href="https://paregorios.org/me"
property="cc:attributionName" rel="cc:attributionURL"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; is
licensed under a &lt;a rel="license"
href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 16:09:33 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Some background on Social.coop</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/social-coop/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those following &lt;a href="https://paregorios.org/categories/fediverse"&gt;my posts about the fediverse&lt;/a&gt; might be interested in the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Irving, Alanna. “&lt;a href="https://medium.com/open-collective/social-coop-a-cooperative-decentralized-social-network-c10980c9ed91"&gt;Social.coop: A Cooperative Decentralized Social Network&lt;/a&gt;.” &lt;a href="https://medium.com/open-collective"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Open Collective&lt;/em&gt; (blog)&lt;/a&gt;, August 28, 2017. Available: &lt;a href="https://medium.com/open-collective/social-coop-a-cooperative-decentralized-social-network-c10980c9ed91"&gt;https://medium.com/open-collective/social-coop-a-cooperative-decentralized-social-network-c10980c9ed91&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="https://www.zotero.org/users/465/items/GCC6KXWW"&gt;Zotero record&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>fediverse</category><category>mastodon</category><category>microblogging</category><category>social networks</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/social-coop/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 16:02:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The thing about heterarchy is: more heterarchy</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/fediverse-macgirven/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So over the weekend I published &lt;a href="https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/fediverse/"&gt;a post intended to introduce the notion of the "fediverse"&lt;/a&gt; to friends and colleagues who are interested in exploring options other than the big, commercial, centralized social media outfits. &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/"&gt;The W3C spec for &lt;em&gt;ActivityPub&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; took a starring role in my presentation, because its fundamental to the operation of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mastodon_(software)"&gt;Mastodon, the social communication server software&lt;/a&gt; on which I focused. But this morning (thanks to &lt;a href="https://social.coop/@wu_lee/99908922653051699"&gt;a Mastodon post from @Wu-Lee&lt;/a&gt;, a fellow &lt;a href="https://social.coop/about"&gt;social.coop&lt;/a&gt; user) I learned that not everyone is so boosterish about the protocol.&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;a href="https://macgirvin.com"&gt;Mike Macgirvin&lt;/a&gt; voices some significant criticism of &lt;em&gt;ActivityPub&lt;/em&gt; in an October 2017 interview for &lt;a href="https://deadsuperhero.com"&gt;Sean Tilley&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/we-distribute"&gt;We Distribute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; blog. Macgirvin is the author of &lt;a href="https://hubzilla.org"&gt;Hubzilla, a &lt;abbr title="Free and Open Source Software"&gt;FOSS&lt;/abbr&gt; "platform for creating interconnected websites."&lt;/a&gt; Among other criticisms, he opines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as protocols go, ActivityPub is a poor quality specification. This is unfortunate for a protocol with such high expectations, coming from an organization whose only function is to produce working specifications for the web. The places where we needed guidance to produce interoperable products (such as privacy and encryption and signatures and even allowed message content) were left undefined or poorly defined. Many of the things that were specified with any precision turned out to be things that are critical to interoperation and cross-federation of existing web services and the specification restricts the ability for them to interact in some fundamental ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire interview is well worth a read, as is all of Tilley's blog. It focuses on the fediverse, the free web, and the people involved in building its components. Among the things you'll find there is &lt;a href="https://medium.com/we-distribute/the-do-everything-system-an-in-depth-review-of-hubzilla-3-0-692204177d4e"&gt;a recent, deep-dive article entitled "The Do-Everything System: An in-depth review of Hubzilla 3.0."&lt;/a&gt; if you want to learn more about that platform.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>fediverse</category><category>hubzilla</category><category>mastodon</category><category>microblogging</category><category>social networks</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/fediverse-macgirven/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 23 Apr 2018 13:25:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Heterarchy: Decentralization and Federation in Social Networking</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/fediverse/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite its hifalutin title, this is not a theoretical or (primarily) political essay. It's rather meant as an idiosyncratic primer on the "fediverse" for friends and colleagues (particularly in academia) who have heard about or are looking for "something different/better than Twitter/Facebook/etc." Caveat: &lt;abbr title="I am not an expert"&gt;IANAE&lt;/abbr&gt;, but after a few weeks dipping my toes into the fediverse I find that I can answer some basic questions at least provisionally. Everything I offer here was gleaned from web searches (I use &lt;a href="https://duckduckgo.com/"&gt;DuckDuckGo&lt;/a&gt;, at present), from trying things out, from watching other people do things, from talking to friends, and from reading especially these posts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://glammr.us/@platypus"&gt;Ruth Kitchin Tillman&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="http://ruthtillman.com/mastodon-overview/"&gt;“Overview of Mastodon &amp;amp; Why I Like It.” &lt;em&gt;Ruth Kitchin Tillman&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (blog), November 14, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seth Kenlon. &lt;a href="https://opensource.com/article/17/4/guide-to-mastodon"&gt;“A Beginner’s Guide to Microblogging on Mastodon.” &lt;em&gt;Opensource.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (blog), April 6, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may find reading them first to be more rewarding that continuing below the fold here immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not hard to find legitimate complaints and concerns about the dominant services in social media today (see, for example, &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/column/zeynep-tufekci"&gt;Zeynep Tufekci's column in the &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). Some people are reacting by seeking alternative social communication mechanisms that differ from Twitter, Facebook, and the like by being less centralized, providing more privacy options, and protecting personal information from exploitation. The ascendant alternatives are, for the moment, coalescing around an open standard for exchanging social networking information over the web called ActivityPub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ActivityPub&lt;/strong&gt; has recently been formalized as &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/"&gt;a W3C Recommendation&lt;/a&gt;. It specifies "a client/server &lt;abbr title="application programming interface"&gt;API&lt;/abbr&gt; for creating, updating and deleting content" (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ActivityPub"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;). Here, "content" means data commonly used in social media or micro-blogging environments like status updates, image posts, direct messages, and hashtags. By "client" we mean a program running on your computer, phone, or table.  ActivityPub also provides for server-to-server exchange of notifications and content. Using this protocol, multiple copies of software installed on different servers under separate administrative control could potentially &lt;strong&gt;federate&lt;/strong&gt; to create a decentralized, distributed network that differs from the centralized, top-down-managed systems most social media users know today. ActivityPub would permit individuals to connect and communicate each other, via client connections through one of these servers and, thanks to the server-to-server federation, across other servers to their connected clients' users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, a social network &lt;strong&gt;fediverse&lt;/strong&gt; based on ActivityPub has emerged. The best-known software tool used to set up a federated server is called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/tootsuite/mastodon"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Its creators, led by &lt;a href="https://mastodon.social/@Gargron"&gt;Eugen Rochko&lt;/a&gt;, describe it as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mastodon is a free, open-source social network server based on open web protocols like ActivityPub and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OStatus"&gt;OStatus&lt;/a&gt;. The social focus of the project is a viable decentralized alternative to commercial social media silos that returns the control of the content distribution channels to the people. The technical focus of the project is a good user interface, a clean &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_state_transfer"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Representational state transfer"&gt;REST&lt;/abbr&gt; API&lt;/a&gt; for 3rd party apps and robust anti-abuse tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that you will often see, &lt;a href="https://hackernoon.com/welcome-to-mastodon-111d9227e56a"&gt;even in Rochko's own writing&lt;/a&gt;, some slippage in terminology. "Mastodon" is often used to connote the entire federated network, rather than just the server software. But in fact, there are other software packages that make use of ActivityPub and can (or potentially can) federate with Mastodon servers (e.g., &lt;a href="https://project.hubzilla.org/page/hubzilla/hubzilla-project"&gt;Hubzilla&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://git.pleroma.social/pleroma/pleroma"&gt;Pleroma&lt;/a&gt;). More are likely to emerge. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yes, I'm leaving aside &lt;a href="https://gnu.io/social/"&gt;GNU Social&lt;/a&gt; for now, since &lt;a href="https://git.gnu.io/gnu/gnu-social/issues/256"&gt;it hasn't yet added full ActivityPub support alongside OStatus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic steps to get started microblogging in the fediverse are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find and join an "instance"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect to your new account on your host instance &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find and follow friends, colleagues, and other accounts of interest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do that thing you do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Finding and joining an instance&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;strong&gt;instance&lt;/strong&gt; is often used as a generic term for a copy of Mastodon running on a particular server. Each instance is separately established and administered, and they each have their own themes (or not), rules, moderation practices (or not), and so on. Rochko and the other core developers of Mastodon run one of the biggest instances, &lt;a href="https://mastodon.social/about"&gt;mastodon.social&lt;/a&gt;, but there are over 2,500 instances in the fediverse at the time of this writing. To find one you like and think you can trust, you can try the flagship &lt;a href="https://joinmastodon.org/"&gt;join.mastodon.org&lt;/a&gt; site. There's also &lt;a href="https://instances.social/"&gt;instances.social&lt;/a&gt;, which is operated by the maintainer of another big, general-purpose instance,  &lt;a href="https://mastodon.xyz/about"&gt;mastodon.xyz&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I initially explored options with both of these tools, in the end I took a different approach to finding an instance to join. I sought out friends and colleagues who were already using Mastodon and looked into the instances they were using. In addition to the two listed above, I found out about three more that I'll mention here since they might be of interest to my intended audience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://scholar.social/about"&gt;Scholar.social&lt;/a&gt;: a Mastodon instance for academics&lt;/strong&gt; is a small instance (less than 1,000 people), run by &lt;a href="https://www.bgcarlisle.com/blog/"&gt;Benjamin Carlisle at McGill University&lt;/a&gt;. He describes its focus as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;scholar.social is meant for: researchers, grad students, librarians, archivists, undergrads, academically inclined high schoolers, educators of all levels, journal editors, research assistants, professors, administrators—anyone involved in academia who is willing to engage with others respectfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://glammr.us/about"&gt;glammr.us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is (at present) a very small instance, run by &lt;a href="https://glammr.us/@joshuatj"&gt;@joshuatj@glammr.us&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;glammr.us is a space for folks interested in productive conversation about, well, galleries, libraries, archives, museums, memory work and records. It is pronounced “glamorous” as our work is often charmingly or fascinatingly attractive, especially in a mysterious or magical way. Sometimes it is also full of excitement, adventure, and unusual activity (oh, yes). It is also inspired by Toys’R’us to showcase the fun playful side of glammr.us tooters. But you don't necessarily have to only post about GLAMMR-related topics, bring your whole self. Talk about fun things you saw, your exciting day or even your struggles. Many of us are Twitter refugees looking for an inclusive and community-supported approach to social media. If any of these things sound good to you, consider joining us by contributing as little as a $1 a month on patreon to help keep our server online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://glammr.us/about/more"&gt;Glammr.us has an online code of conduct&lt;/a&gt; (scroll down the page). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://social.coop/about"&gt;Social.coop:  a co-op corner of the fediverse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is owned, operated, and co-financed by a formal co-operative, with &lt;a href="https://social.coop/bylaws"&gt;established bylaws&lt;/a&gt; that dictate open, democratic policy-making. I applied to join the coop because of that openness and because I hoped the bylaws and participatory governance model would serve as a bulwark against arbitrary administrative actions. Plus, they clearly had healthy administrative and technical &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus_factor"&gt;bus numbers&lt;/a&gt;. Happily, I was accepted as a co-owner and member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you've picked an instance and worked through whatever application/joinup/payment process that instance has in place, you'll want to establish some sort of profile and start following others and producing content. Mastodon instances provide a default web experience, subject to customization by the instance admins. There are also a growing number of mobile apps for connecting to your instance. On my OSX laptop, I connect to the social.coop instance's native web interface using &lt;a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/blog/2017/11/14/introducing-firefox-quantum/"&gt;Firefox Quantum&lt;/a&gt;. On my iphone, I use &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/amaroq-for-mastodon/id1214116200?mt=8"&gt;John Gabelmann's &lt;em&gt;Amaroq for Mastodon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Finding and following other people&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the people I know from my &lt;a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/words-at-play/what-is-meatspace"&gt;meatspace&lt;/a&gt; and/or &lt;span title="that is, Twitter"&gt;birdsite&lt;/span&gt; social networks who were also already in the fediverse were either on mastodon.social or scholar.social, rather than my home instance social.coop. No matter their instance, following them (once logged into my social.coop account) was as easy as visiting the web page corresponding to their Mastodon profile. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for example, I typed the following into my search engine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;eric kansa mastodon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I clicked through the results to &lt;a href="https://octodon.social/@ekansa"&gt;https://octodon.social/@ekansa&lt;/a&gt;. Once there, I clicked "remote follow":&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://paregorios.org/images/fediverse/remote_follow.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also be able to find people you know by typing their names into your Mastodon instance's search box, but your results may depend on whether anyone else on your instance is already following someone from the other instance (or other techno-administrative factors that at present I only vaguely intuit). Search is also your friend for finding people with similar interests. Imagine a hashtag and search for it; see who uses it. Watch your "Local Timeline" (i.e., every post on your instance) for users and topics of interest. Dip into the firehose of the "Federated Timeline" to sample the fediverse &lt;em&gt;Zeitgeist&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="For What It's Worth"&gt;FWIW&lt;/abbr&gt;, the core developers of Mastodon also run https://bridge.joinmastodon.org/, which is supposed to help you "find your friends on Mastodon." I haven't used it either, because it requires authenticated access to your Twitter account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Microblogging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most instances I've seen suggest you offer a self-introduction (using the #introductions hashtag) in the interest of explaining yourself to other folks on your local timeline. Consider your privacy before you do this: Mastodon gives you the ability to limit the scope of your posts ("toots" are the domain-specific term) to "public" timelines, only non-public timelines (i.e., instance-internal), "followers only", or "direct" (i.e., only to individuals whose accounts you mention in the post itself).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's &lt;a href="https://social.coop/@paregorios/99644416200468402"&gt;my initial introduction&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://social.coop/@paregorios/99836014294446671"&gt;a follow-up introduction&lt;/a&gt; I made after watching what other people were doing in that regard. I'm not sure whether either of them is all that great, so you might lurk for a few days and watch how others on your instance behave. You can look for more by searching for the hashtag #introductions. Don't be surprised if someone on your instance (admin or otherwise) initiates contact to welcome you and encourage an #introductions post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Crossposting (&lt;span style="color: red"&gt;updated 23 April 2018&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've seen some people set up cross-posting from birdsite to their Mastodon instance (or vice versa), but &lt;a href="https://octodon.social/@steko/99905269629290006"&gt;Stefano Costa pointed out to me&lt;/a&gt; that witter-to-Mastodon autoposting is not necessarily well accepted in the fediverse. &lt;a href="https://scholar.social/@bgcarlisle/99905312826543963"&gt;Benjamin Carlisle reinforced that point, saying&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might need to check your instance's policies re: autoposting. For example, on Scholar Social, repeaters of RSS feeds or Twitter accounts are allowed, but they must be set to post as Unlisted, not Public&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As to technology, I've seen people recommend the following tools:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/YoloSwagTeam/t2m"&gt;t2m&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://crossposter.masto.donte.com.br/"&gt;Mastodon Twitter Crossposter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Now What&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I'd suggest that if you haven't yet read the blog posts cited above &lt;a href="http://ruthtillman.com/mastodon-overview/"&gt;from Ruth Tillman&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://opensource.com/article/17/4/guide-to-mastodon"&gt;from Seth Kenlon&lt;/a&gt;, now would be good time. Reading both of them will give you a broader introduction than I've tried to lay out here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="color:red"&gt;Updated 23 April 2018&lt;/span&gt;: it looks like there will be follow-on posts to this one. I just published one on criticisms of &lt;em&gt;ActivityPub&lt;/em&gt; that also has some links to some more interesting writing on the fediverse, writ large. The best way to keep up with any subsequent posts to this one is probably through &lt;a href="https://paregorios.org/categories/fediverse/"&gt;the fediverse tag&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>fediverse</category><category>mastodon</category><category>microblogging</category><category>social networks</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/fediverse/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2018 15:50:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Call for Papers: Climate Science and Ancient History in Basel, 27-29 November 2018</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/ancient-climate-cfp/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposal deadline: 31 May, 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I noticed &lt;a href="https://altegeschichte.philhist.unibas.ch/de/personen/sabine-huebner/"&gt;Sabine Huebner's&lt;/a&gt; post to several lists with a call for papers for the following conference. Since only a PDF version of same is available via the website of &lt;a href="https://altegeschichte.philhist.unibas.ch/de/forschung/forschungsprojekte/climate-science/"&gt;The Basel Climate Science and Ancient History Lab&lt;/a&gt;, I thought I'd reproduce it in a more web-friendly format here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please direct any comments or questions to Professor Huebner at sabine.huebner@unibas.ch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Call for Papers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Climate Science and Ancient History:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decoding “Human” and “Natural” Archives&lt;br&gt;
Basel, Switzerland. Nov. 27-28, 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ancient historians rely on “human archives” (historical narratives, inscriptions, coin hoards, papyrus archives, etc.) to reconstruct historic events, and social, economic, political and cultural systems among the Greeks, Romans and their neighbors. These historians are trained to read human archives with all their subjectivity and errors in recording and transmission. Palaeoclimatologists read and interpret “ natural archives” to assess changes in climatic and environmental conditions in the past. Palaeoclimate archives include organic (tree rings, corals) and inorganic materials (speleothems, lake and marine sediments, ice cores) and represent a treasure trove for accessing a whole new set of statistical and quantitative, usually highly resolved data of precisely dated information about past climate and environmental conditions. Natural archives also come with their inherent difficulties including qualitative and quantitative variations by region and period, temporal resolution, dating uncertainties, and climate information they resolve (temperature, precipitation, sunshine duration, drought, sea level changes, pH, sea water temperature, streamflow changes, etc.). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only are ancient historians and palaeoclimatologists often working on the same period and region, palaeoclimatologists also have to rely on historical documents as climate proxies for reconstructing climate in the past and need the help of historians for properly interpreting them. A closer collaboration between the two fields and a convergence of evidence from both disciplines will thus not only help to clarify the picture of past climates, but also widen our knowledge about the interaction between climate change, environmental stress, and socio-political systems. In recent years, a new discipline, coined “historical climatology”, has been established crossing the traditional division between historians and the natural sciences and combining their two approaches. Historical climatologists are studying the connectures between human and climate history, especially the impact of environmental change on past societies, and human resilience and mitigations strategies when faced with climate variability and climate change (cf. Izdebski et al. 2016; Haldon et al. 2018).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Switzerland has been at the forefront of climate research for the past few decades. “The Basel Climate Science and Ancient History Lab” is directing the focus on the impact of climate variability and climate change on societies in the ancient Mediterranean and in particular on the society of Graeco-Roman Egypt. Egypt in particular provides a unique historical laboratory in which to study social vulnerability and responses to climate and environmental change thanks to its extraordinarily rich evidence unparalleled for any other region of the ancient world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this colloquium we want to discuss the challenges connected to a joint interpretation of human and natural archives in the ancient Mediterranean, the problems inherent in a collaboration between ancient historians and the natural sciences (terminology, project design, publication culture), methods to solve discrepancies between information gained from the textual and archaeological evidence on the one hand and tree rings, ice cores and speleothems on the other one, the methodological difficulties in distinguishing between correlation and causality, and methods of assessing the impact of climatic variability or change on ancient societies without oversimplifying their causal connections. The impact of climate on past societies need to be assessed in a holistic venture, integrating and synthesizing traditional classical scholarship with the most advanced scientific methods in a manner which does not privilege data from one field over another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keynote lecture will be delivered by &lt;a href="https://www.uni-giessen.de/faculties/f07/geography/sections/climate/staff/luterbacher"&gt;Jürg Luterbacher&lt;/a&gt; (Giessen) on “Reconstructing Climate back to Greek and Roman Times: Challenges, Opportunities, and Uncertainties”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ancient historians and paleoclimatologists interested in starting a dialogue should send expressions of interest, along with short abstracts (not exceeding 300 words) to sabine.huebner@unibas.ch. Please include the full title of your talk and a brief biographical note on your academic affiliation and previous research. PhD candidates are encouraged to apply as well. The deadline for sending abstracts is May 31, 2018. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Selected Literature:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brázdil, R., et al. 2005 “Historical climatology in Europe – The State of the Art,” Climatic Change 70, 363-430.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Haldon, J., et al. 2018 “History meets palaeoscience: Consilience and collaboration in studying past societal responses to environmental change,” Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 115 (13), 3210-3218.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Holmgren, K., et al. 2016 “Mediterranean Holocene climate and human societies,” Quaternary Science Reviews 136, 1-4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Izdebski, A., et al., 2016 “Realising consilience: how better communication between archaeologists, historians and geoscientists can transform the study of past climate change in the Mediterranean,” Quaternary Science Reviews 136, 5-22.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luterbacher, J., et al. 2012 “A Review of 2000 Years of Paleoclimatic Evidence in the Mediterranean,” in P. Leonello ed., The Climate of the Mediterranean Region: From the Past to the Future . Salento, 87-185.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manning, J. G., et al. 2017 “Volcanic suppression of Nile summer flooding triggers revolt and constraints interstate conflict in ancient Egypt,” Nature Communications 8 (900).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manning, S. W. 2013 “The Roman world and climate. Context, relevance of climate change, and some issues,” in: W. V. Harris ed. The ancient Mediterranean environment between science and history. Leiden, 103–170.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;McCormick, M. 2011 “History’s changing climate: climate science, genomics, and the emerging consilient approach to interdisciplinary history,” Journal of Interdisciplinary History 42, 251–273.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;McCormick, M., et al. 2012 “Climate Change During and After the Roman Empire: Reconstructing the Past from Scientific and Historic Evidence,” Journal of Interdisciplinary History 43, 169-220.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ancient history</category><category>cfp</category><category>climate</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/ancient-climate-cfp/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 19:10:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Strip Geospatial Data from Image Headers</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/strip-geo-images/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reblogged from &lt;a href="https://social.coop/@paregorios/99796064822455556"&gt;a Mastodon post&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that most phone cameras and many other digital cameras automatically embed spatial data in image headers&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;, I'd like to point out that the following command-line invocation of &lt;a href="https://www.sno.phy.queensu.ca/~phil/exiftool/"&gt;Phil Harvey's ExifTool&lt;/a&gt; removes it when that's what you'd prefer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;exiftool -gps:all= -xmp:geotag= your_image.jpg
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>exif</category><category>exiftool</category><category>geodata</category><category>images</category><category>privacy</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/strip-geo-images/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 13:16:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Questing Beasts</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/questing_beasts/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;For those at home following my &lt;a href="https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/hosting_quest"&gt;Hosting Quest&lt;/a&gt;, here are the suggested providers given me (so far) by friends and social media contacts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/lightsail/"&gt;AWS Lightsail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://cloudvault.me/"&gt;Cloudvault.me&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/"&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://esosoft.com/webhosting/"&gt;EsoSoft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linode.com/"&gt;Linode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.mythic-beasts.com/"&gt;Mythic Beasts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://reclaimhosting.com"&gt;Reclaim Hosting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tigertech.net/"&gt;Tiger Technologies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.vidahost.com/web-hosting/pricing"&gt;Vidahost&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.webarchitects.co.uk/shared-hosting"&gt;Webarchitects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a lot to like about all these recommendations; however, I'm going with Tiger Technologies for now. I like their combination of green power, &lt;a href="https://httpd.apache.org/"&gt;Apache&lt;/a&gt;, free &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTPS"&gt;HTTPS over TLS&lt;/a&gt; using a certificate from &lt;a href="https://letsencrypt.org/"&gt;Let's Encrypt&lt;/a&gt;, free domain name management and renewal, free WHOIS privacy, email, ssh/shell, and unmetered bandwidth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll let you know how it goes. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>hosting</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/questing_beasts/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2018 20:46:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hosting Quest</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/hosting_quest/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm currently hosting &lt;em&gt;paregorios.org&lt;/em&gt; via GitHub pages, but I'm looking for an alternative because there are features I need that GitHub doesn't provide. Here, I think, is a description of my ideal solution:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apache web server with ability to use &lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; files (because I want to be able to issue HTTP redirects)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SSL with Let's Encrypt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deploy via ssh+rsync using ssh keys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cost: less than $10/month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder where I will be able to find such a combination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>apache</category><category>hosting</category><category>htaccess</category><category>rsync</category><category>ssh</category><category>ssl</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/hosting_quest/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2018 19:49:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hello, World ... Again</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/hello-world-again/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the new &lt;em&gt;paregorios.org&lt;/em&gt;, powered by &lt;a href="https://getnikola.com/"&gt;the &lt;em&gt;Nikola&lt;/em&gt; static site generator&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt;. For now, it plays host to the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://paregorios.org/about"&gt;Metadata about me (Tom Elliott)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://paregorios.org/categories/horothesia"&gt;All the content from my old blog, &lt;em&gt;Horothesia&lt;/em&gt; (2007-2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any &lt;a href="https://paregorios.org/"&gt;new blog posts&lt;/a&gt; (like this one) that I choose to write&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>meta</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/04/hello-world-again/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 23:27:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Preserving Accented and Non-Roman Characters in CSV Workflows</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/02/preserving-accented-and-non-roman/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Digital work in and around the Humanities often involves moving data from one system or format to another. That data often involves complex textual materials in multiple languages and writing systems. One commonly used format is the "&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comma-separated_values"&gt;Comma-Separated Values&lt;/a&gt;" text file. It's not uncommon to find that characters not used in English get garbled when exported from a spreadsheet program like Microsoft Excel to CSV (or imported from CSV into such a program). What's going on and how do you make it stop?&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Why&lt;/h3&gt;CSV began life in an era before &lt;a href="http://unicode.org/standard/WhatIsUnicode.html"&gt;Unicode&lt;/a&gt; and, because of that background, some software assumes that CSV should be encoding using &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ASCII"&gt;the ASCII text encoding scheme&lt;/a&gt; (some older versions of Excel). Some software defaults to using ASCII, but you can override it manually (more recent versions of Excel). Some software tries to guess what encoding to use when reading or writing a given CSV file, but how it guesses may not be foolproof. Some software writes a special code called a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byte_order_mark"&gt;Byte-Order Mark (BOM)&lt;/a&gt; into the beginning of any CSV file that uses a Unicode-aware encoding (Excel for Mac 2016). Some software doesn't expect a BOM and will fail to read the data correctly even if the encoding (e.g., &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTF-8"&gt;UTF-8&lt;/a&gt;) is otherwise supported.&lt;br&gt;&lt;h3&gt;How to make it stop&lt;/h3&gt;The best way to make it stop is to:&lt;br&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Make sure that any CSV file you import or export is encoded in UTF-8 without a Byte-Order Mark.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Make sure that any software you're using is capable of reading and writing CSV files in UTF-8 without BOM and has been told to do so.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;Failing that (i.e., you got the CSV file from someone else), you need to find out what encoding it uses and configure your software to read it properly. But note that if the creator of the CSV file allowed it to be written in ASCII, it can't be repaired. You'll have to get them to re-export properly, or to send you the original file so you can open it in appropriate software and save it more deliberately.</description><category>csv</category><category>data</category><category>dh</category><category>horothesia</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2018/02/preserving-accented-and-non-roman/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2018 05:33:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Using OpenRefine with Pleiades</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2017/10/using-openrefine-with-pleiades/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This past summer, &lt;a href="https://blogs.library.duke.edu/dcthree/"&gt;DC3&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a href="https://ryanfb.github.io/"&gt;Ryan Baumann&lt;/a&gt; developed a reconciliation service for &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. He's named it &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="http://geocollider-sinatra.herokuapp.com/"&gt;Geocollider&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. It has two manifestations:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Upload &lt;a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/fdd/fdd000323.shtml"&gt;a CSV file&lt;/a&gt; containing placenames and/or longitude/latitude coordinates, set matching parameters, and get back a CSV file of possible matches.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;An online Application Programming Interface (API) compatible with the &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="http://openrefine.org/"&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; data-cleaning tool.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;The first version is relatively self-documenting. This blog post is about using the second version with &lt;i&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Reconciliation&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I.e., matching (collating, aligning) your placenames against places in &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Running &lt;i&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/i&gt; against &lt;i&gt;Geocollider&lt;/i&gt; for reconciliation purposes is as easy as:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://openrefine.org/download.html"&gt;Download and install &lt;i&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Follow &lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/Reconciliation"&gt;the standard OpenRefine instructions for "Reconciliation,"&lt;/a&gt; but instead of picking the pre-installed "Wikidata Reconciliation Service," select the "Add standard service..." button and enter "http://geocollider-sinatra.herokuapp.com/reconcile" in the service URL dialog, then select the "Add Service" button.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;When you've worked through the results of your reconciliation process and selected matches, &lt;i&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/i&gt; will have added the corresponding &lt;a href="https://pleiades.stoa.org/help/what-are-pleiades-uris"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; place URIs&lt;/a&gt; to your dataset. That may be all you want or need (for example, if you're preparing to bring your own dataset into &lt;a href="http://commons.pelagios.org/"&gt;the &lt;i&gt;Pelagios&lt;/i&gt; network&lt;/a&gt;) ... just export the results and go on with your work. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But if you'd like to actually get information &lt;b&gt;about&lt;/b&gt; the &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; places, proceed to the next section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Augmentation&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I.e., pulling data from &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; into &lt;i&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/i&gt; and selectively parsing it for information to add to your dataset.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; provides an API for retrieving information about each place resource it contains. One of the data formats this API provides is &lt;a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/fdd/fdd000381.shtml"&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;, which is a format with which &lt;i&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/i&gt; is designed to work. The following recipe demonstrates how to use the &lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/General-Refine-Expression-Language"&gt;General Refine Expression Language&lt;/a&gt; to extract the "Representative Location" associated with each &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; place. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style="color: red;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Caveat:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt; this recipe will not, at present, work with the current Mac OSX release of &lt;i&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/i&gt; (2.7), even though it should and hopefully eventually will.  It has not been tested with the current releases for Windows and Linux, but they probably suffer from the same limitations as the OSX release. More information, including a non-trivial technical workaround, may be had from &lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/1265"&gt;OpenRefine Issue 1265&lt;/a&gt;. I will update this blog post if and when a resolution is forthcoming.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;b&gt;1. Create a new column containing &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; JSON. &lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Assuming your dataset is open in an &lt;i&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/i&gt; project and that it contains a column that has been reconciled using &lt;i&gt;Geocollider&lt;/i&gt;, select the drop-down menu on that column and choose "Edit column" -&amp;gt; "Add column by fetching URLs ..."&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-p7Op-SfHjOk/WeEyP9BNS_I/AAAAAAAAAvY/B7ndDjX2fuEEgS6H6c32Eu6tIRYfCUbDQCLcBGAs/s1600/foo1.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screen capture of OpenRefine column drop-down menu: add column by fetching URLs" border="0" data-original-height="378" data-original-width="409" height="369" src="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-p7Op-SfHjOk/WeEyP9BNS_I/AAAAAAAAAvY/B7ndDjX2fuEEgS6H6c32Eu6tIRYfCUbDQCLcBGAs/s400/foo1.png" title="" width="400"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;In the dialog box, provide a name for the new column you are about to create. In the "expression" box, enter a GREL expression that retrieves the &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; URL from the reconciliation match on each cell and appends the string "/json" to it:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;cell.recon.match.id + "/json"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-vi2Jk_4TNqM/WeEyaD1MlTI/AAAAAAAAAvc/s1Zqp-crhog1b9yY2nN5h39DXgMM--zSgCLcBGAs/s1600/Screen%2BShot%2B2017-10-13%2Bat%2B4.18.59%2BPM.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screen capture of OpenRefine dialog box: add column by fetching URLs" border="0" data-original-height="548" data-original-width="720" height="304" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-vi2Jk_4TNqM/WeEyaD1MlTI/AAAAAAAAAvc/s1Zqp-crhog1b9yY2nN5h39DXgMM--zSgCLcBGAs/s400/Screen%2BShot%2B2017-10-13%2Bat%2B4.18.59%2BPM.png" title="" width="400"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;i&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/i&gt; retrieves the JSON for each matched place from &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; and inserts it into the appropriate cell in the new column. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;2. Create another new column by parsing the representative longitude out of the JSON.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;From the drop-down menu on the column containing JSON, select "Edit column" -&amp;gt; "Add column based on this column..."&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-6Pp_ZLZop7E/WeEygxbwkSI/AAAAAAAAAvg/BhRqIf9VzLIuem68F86jLgQP7yfV40miwCLcBGAs/s1600/foo2.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screen capture of OpenRefine column drop-down menu: add column based on this column" border="0" data-original-height="387" data-original-width="655" src="https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-6Pp_ZLZop7E/WeEygxbwkSI/AAAAAAAAAvg/BhRqIf9VzLIuem68F86jLgQP7yfV40miwCLcBGAs/s1600/foo2.png" title=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;In the dialog box, provide a name for the new column. In the expression box, enter a GREL expression that extracts the longitude from the &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;reprPoint&lt;/span&gt; object in the JSON:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;value.parseJson()['reprPoint'][0]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-eRYBqNDMXxg/WeEyrMvN9XI/AAAAAAAAAvk/nCkcYKP6zI0oMoeGI0Ek6_eoip4AbyHKwCLcBGAs/s1600/Screen%2BShot%2B2017-10-13%2Bat%2B4.30.13%2BPM.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screen capture of OpenRefine column dialog box: add column based on this column" border="0" data-original-height="519" data-original-width="718" height="289" src="https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-eRYBqNDMXxg/WeEyrMvN9XI/AAAAAAAAAvk/nCkcYKP6zI0oMoeGI0Ek6_eoip4AbyHKwCLcBGAs/s400/Screen%2BShot%2B2017-10-13%2Bat%2B4.30.13%2BPM.png" title="" width="400"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Note that the &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;reprPoint&lt;/span&gt; object contains a two-element list, like:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;[ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;37.328382, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;38.240638 ]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; follows &lt;a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7946"&gt;the GeoJSON specification&lt;/a&gt; in using the longitude, latitude ordering of elements in coordinate pairs so, to get the longitude, you use the index (0) for the first element in the list.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;3. Create a column for the latitude&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;Use the method explained in step 2, but select the second list item from &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;reprPoint&lt;/span&gt; (index=1). &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;4. Carry on ...&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;Your data set in &lt;i&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/i&gt; will now look something like this:  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-O9NL6Rj0tT8/WeEywg8gBlI/AAAAAAAAAvs/vQ-aYkgXapg3lyzFWqayLL9Ka5OgW00CgCLcBGAs/s1600/Screen%2BShot%2B2017-10-13%2Bat%2B4.30.58%2BPM.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="screen capture showing portion of an OpenRefine table that includes an ancient toponym, JSON retrieved from Pleiades, and latitude and longitude values extracted from that JSON" border="0" data-original-height="237" data-original-width="1082" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-O9NL6Rj0tT8/WeEywg8gBlI/AAAAAAAAAvs/vQ-aYkgXapg3lyzFWqayLL9Ka5OgW00CgCLcBGAs/s1600/Screen%2BShot%2B2017-10-13%2Bat%2B4.30.58%2BPM.png" title=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style="white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>csv</category><category>horothesia</category><category>interop</category><category>json</category><category>patterns</category><category>pelagoios</category><category>pleiades</category><category>refine</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2017/10/using-openrefine-with-pleiades/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2017 03:49:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>