<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about awib)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://paregorios.org/categories/awib.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:paregorios@hotmail.com"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 16:22:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Pleiades, Flickr, and the Ancient World Image Bank</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2011/12/pleiades-flickr-and-ancient-world-image/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Many of you are already aware that &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://flickr.com/"&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/awib/"&gt;Ancient World Image Bank&lt;/a&gt; have joined forces to link together online, open-access imagery and ancient geographical information. This blog post is intended to answer some lingering questions that users and potential contributors have been asking about the process.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Other Blog Posts&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/about/news/geography-and-imagery"&gt;A general notice of the development on the ISAW News Blog&lt;/a&gt; (by me)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/Members/sgillies/news-items/eye-on-the-sidebar-related-photos-from-flickr"&gt;An extended discussion of the effects, from the Pleiades perspective&lt;/a&gt; (by Sean Gillies)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://code.flickr.com/blog/2011/12/16/pleiades-a-guest-post/"&gt;An extended discussion with developers' how-to on the Flickr Code Blog&lt;/a&gt; (by Sean Gillies), &lt;a href="http://sgillies.net/blog/1103/flickr-support-for-ancient-world-places"&gt;mirrored on Sean's blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2011/09/feeds-of-flickr-photos-depicting.html"&gt;The blog post here at Horothesia that started it all&lt;/a&gt; (by me)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;How to Construct a Pleiades Machine Tag&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;In Flickr, you add the machine tag the same way you add regular tags when editing an individual image or a set or group in the organizer.   The machine tag should use the following syntax:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;pleiades:TERM=#####&lt;/blockquote&gt;where "TERM" is one of the recognized terms (&lt;a href="http://gawd.atlantides.org/terms/"&gt;originally from the Concordia Thesaurus, aka the Graph of Ancient World Data, or GAWD, terms&lt;/a&gt;) listed below and "#####" is the numeric identifier of the Pleiades place you wish to associate with the photo.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You can get the identifier by visiting pleiades.stoa.org then searching for and finding the place. Copy the numeric portion of the URL of the place page and paste it into your tag.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, for example, if I wanted to tag a photo that "depicts" ancient Athens (or a portion thereof), I'd visit Pleiades and search for Athens. I'd find this place page: &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/579885/"&gt;http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/579885/&lt;/a&gt;. So, I'd grab 579885 and construct the following machine tag for use in Flickr:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;pleiades:depicts=579885&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;Recognized Terms in Pleiades Machine Tags&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;TERMS for use in Pleiades machine tags should begin with a lowercase letter. The following TERMS are recognized in Pleiades machine tags:&lt;br&gt;&lt;dl&gt;&lt;dt&gt;depicts&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;the photo so tagged can be said to "depict" the referenced ancient place or a significant or exemplary portion thereof&lt;br&gt;(this term is equivalent to CIDOC CRM p62 "depicts")&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;findspot&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;the photo so tagged shows an object that was first found in modern times at the referenced ancient place&lt;br&gt;(this term is particularly useful for items now in museums or elsewhere, especially those no longer at the initial place of finding)&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;origin&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;the photo so tagged shows an object that is believed, with reasonably high certainty, to have been originally located or produced at the referenced ancient place&lt;br&gt;(this can differ from the findspot, as when an inscription or other object was moved in antiquity)&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;observedAt&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;the photo so tagged shows an object that was observed in modern times at the referenced ancient place&lt;br&gt;(the implication being that the place observed is neither the modern findspot nor the presumed original location; I suspect this term will rarely need to be used to link photos with Pleiades place resources)&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;where&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;the photo so tagged is related in some way to the referenced ancient place, but for some unspecified reason no more specific relationship can be asserted&lt;br&gt;(this term should not be used unless none of above terms are deemed to be appropriate)&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;place&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;this term is DEPRECATED; it was originally used in exploring the Pleiades machine tag idea (and is highlighted in my previous blog post). Its semantics are assumed to be equivalent to "where". If at all possible, photos carrying this tag should be updated to use one of the more specific terms above.&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;br&gt;Please note that pleiades:place&lt;span style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;=##### (i.e., with a plural) is not a recognized machine tag. Its behavior in Flickr or Pleiades is undefined. So is the behavior of any Pleiades machine tag with a misspelling or a term not included in the list above. ("finspot" seems to be a popular typo at present).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Any photo tagged with the proper Pleiades machine tag syntax and one of the terms above will be noticed by Pleiades and picked up in the summary counts and links on individual place resource pages. In order for a photo to be considered for the &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/groups/pleiades-places/"&gt;Pleiades Places group on Flickr&lt;/a&gt; (and therefore as a "portrait image" for a Pleiades place), the photo must be tagged with a pleiades:depicts tag.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;How do I Add Pleiades Machine Tags Quickly?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It would be unreasonable of us to ask a prolific photographer with an extensive, well-tagged collection already on Flickr to go through an individually add appropriate machine tags by hand. Fortunately, Flickr provides a mechanism for easy batch editing of tags.&lt;br&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Suppose that you have tagged a large number of your photos with the name of the ancient site (e.g., Halicarnassus)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Visit the following link: &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/me/alltags/"&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/me/alltags/&lt;/a&gt;; it will give you an alphabetical list of all your tags.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Find the name of the site and click on the corresponding link. You'll see all the photos thus tagged in your photostream.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Find and click on the "Change this tag" link (Really. Skip "Edit these in a batch" link for now).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Insert the cursor after your existing tag string, type a space, then type or paste in the desired Pleiades machine tag (read the fine print on that page for an extended explanation of what's going on).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Click the "save" button. Flickr will go off and add the new tag to all those images at once.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;If you'd rather be more selective about which photos you want to add a tag to, you can choose the "Edit these in a batch" link I told you to skip above, then paste the Pleiades machine tag into the tag lists associated with only those images you wish to update.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Why Can't We Just Use Geotagging That's Already in the Photos?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Some photographers have geotagged their photos, either using a GPS-enabled digital camera or some method of post-processing. I was recently asked on twitter why we're putting people to all the trouble above when we could just use the geotagging? There are several reasons:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Not everybody's photos are machine-tagged.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Many ancient sites are coincident with urban areas (or areas of natural beauty or places where someone took a picture of their dog) and so mere proximity to an ancient site can't be interpreted as indicating a given photo is relevant to a nearby Pleiades place.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Horizontal precision and accuracy can vary widely in geotagged photos as a function of the geotagging method used and the interests and skill of the person doing the geotagging. As a result, a photo might be geotagged at a location closer to another, unrelated pleiades place.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The horizontal precision and accuracy of Pleiades coordinates also varies widely given the varying sources from which it derives and the subsequent coordinate extraction methods. This makes the process of proximity correlation even more fraught.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;This is not to say that we're not interested in exploring uses for geotagged photos in Flickr (or supporting a geotag-your-photo-using-Pleiades-coordinates tool), but I hope this discussion helps explain why we like the machine-tag approach for indicating relevance.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Please let me know, via comments here, if you have additional questions or suggestions. &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>awib</category><category>flickr</category><category>gawd</category><category>horothesia</category><category>images</category><category>machine tags</category><category>pleiades</category><category>pleiades:depicts=579885</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2011/12/pleiades-flickr-and-ancient-world-image/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2011 21:42:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Meetup: The Future of the Ancient World Image Bank</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2011/10/meetup-future-of-ancient-world-image/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;So, my brain has mashed up its happiness at the success of &lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/116427745746305527780/posts/fTXi1HbFrhC"&gt;last week's Pleiades community meetup&lt;/a&gt; with the hanging conversations that started in response to my blog post on &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2011/09/feeds-of-flickr-photos-depicting.html"&gt;Pleiades machine tags in Flickr&lt;/a&gt;. Nate Nagy (&lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/awib/"&gt;AWIB&lt;/a&gt; Managing Editor) and I had a good conversation a couple of weeks ago about the future of AWIB, one that would be more open and collaborative than the current model.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'd like to light a fire under (and refine) those ideas. I'm starting a Doodle poll to find a time for a "future of AWIB" meetup, to be held via Google+. I'll send invites to all of our contacts on Flickr and others who have expressed interest. &lt;b&gt;Please post a comment here if you'd like to be part of the event.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>awib</category><category>collaboration</category><category>horothesia</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2011/10/meetup-future-of-ancient-world-image/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2011 01:15:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Feeds of Flickr Photos Depicting Pleiades Places</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2011/09/feeds-of-flickr-photos-depicting/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Some months ago, ISAW started adding &lt;b&gt;Pleiades machine tags&lt;/b&gt; to the &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/awib"&gt;Ancient World Image Bank (AWIB)&lt;/a&gt; photos we've been uploading to &lt;a href="http://flickr.com/"&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;. This post will explain what that means, how it might be useful to you and how you can add Pleiades machine tags to your own photos so we can find out about them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Updated: &lt;/b&gt;8:45pm EDT, 10 September 2011 (&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;changes highlighted in orange&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Updated:&lt;/b&gt; 10:43am EST, 20 December 2011 (some of what's here is now superseded by recent developments; see further this new post: &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2011/12/pleiades-flickr-and-ancient-world-image.html"&gt;Pleiades, Flickr, and the Ancient World Image Bank&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pleiades Machine Tags&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt; is a collaborative, open-access digital gazetteer for the ancient world. AWIB is an open-access publication that uses the Flickr photo-sharing site to publish free, reusable photos of ancient sites and artifacts. &lt;a href="http://tagaholic.me/2009/03/26/what-are-machine-tags.html"&gt;Machine tags&lt;/a&gt; are an extension to &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/help/tags/"&gt;Flickr's basic tag-this-photo functionality&lt;/a&gt; that "use a special syntax to define extra information about a tag" (&lt;a href="http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/yws-flickr/message/2736"&gt;Aaron Straup Cope, "Ladies and Gentlemen: Machine Tags," 24 January 2007&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A Pleiades machine tag looks like this:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;pleiades:place=&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;795868&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;where 795868 is the stable identifier portion of a Pleiades &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_Resource_Identifier"&gt;Uniform Resource Identifier&lt;/a&gt; (URI).  In this example, the URI corresponding to the machine tag above is:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/795868"&gt;http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;795868&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;Note what's in common between the machine tag and the URI (highlighted in yellow).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;What Pleiades Machine Tags Are Good For&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/services/api/"&gt;Flickr API&lt;/a&gt; makes it possible to request lists of machine-tagged photos in the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS"&gt;RSS webfeed format&lt;/a&gt;. So, to get a list of all photos in Flickr that are tagged with the example machine tag above, pop this into your &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/News_aggregator"&gt;feed reader&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://api.flickr.com/services/feeds/photos_public.gne?tags=pleiades%3Aplace=795868&amp;amp;lang=en-us&amp;amp;format=rss_200"&gt;http://api.flickr.com/services/feeds/photos_public.gne?tags=pleiades%3Aplace&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;795868&amp;amp;lang=en-us&amp;amp;format=rss_200&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;The same results can be viewed in HTML in a browser by resolving the following:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/tags/pleiades:place=795868" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/tags/pleiades:place=795868&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;To get a list of all photos in Flickr that are tagged with &lt;b&gt;any&lt;/b&gt; Pleiades machine tag, try this (the API syntax supports wildcards!):&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://api.flickr.com/services/feeds/photos_public.gne?tags=pleiades%3Aplace%3D&amp;amp;lang=en-us&amp;amp;format=rss_200"&gt;http://api.flickr.com/services/feeds/photos_public.gne?tags=pleiades%3Aplace%3D&amp;amp;lang=en-us&amp;amp;format=rss_200&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;The same results, viewed in HTML on the Flickr site:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/tags/pleiades:place" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/tags/pleiades:place&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;Feeds like these aren't just for feed readers anymore. You can add user-interface widgets to your blog or website to summarize the latest content for your readers (check out the right-hand column in this blog). You can hook up services like &lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/networkedblogs"&gt;Networked Blogs&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://twitterfeed.com/"&gt;Twitterfeed&lt;/a&gt; to pass on the latest changes to your Facebook friends or Twitter followers. If you've got a &lt;a href="http://nomisma.org/"&gt;web-facing numismatic database that you've already linked up with Pleiades&lt;/a&gt; for the mint locations, you could write custom code to pull a corresponding picture of the ancient site into your web interface (say, alongside the map you've already got).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Add Pleiades Machine Tags to Your Own Photos on Flickr&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Many of you have been taking amazing photos of ancient sites and artifacts for years. Many of you have posted some of them to Flickr and shared them with great groups like &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/groups/chiron/"&gt;Chiron&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/groups/562831@N24/"&gt;Visibile Parlare - Greek Inscriptions&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/groups/visible_words/"&gt;Visibile Parlare - Latin Inscriptions&lt;/a&gt;. If you'd like these photos to appear in queries and feeds (like those described above), right alongside the photos that we're publishing via AWIB, all you have to do is add the appropriate Pleiades machine tags in Flickr. Just look up your site on Pleiades, copy the numeric ID from the URI in your browser's location bar, append it to the string "pleiades:place=" and tag your Flickr photos with it. In this way, you can help us improve findability of good photos of ancient sites and the artifacts found there for everyone on the web. Who knows ... maybe enough people will join us in this effort that we can someday get the Flickr development team to give Pleiades machine tags some &lt;a href="http://code.flickr.com/blog/2009/07/06/extraextraextra/"&gt;extra love&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Kudos to:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Aaron Straup Cope for his blog post &lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;"&lt;a href="http://code.flickr.com/blog/2008/07/18/wildcard-machine-tag-urls/"&gt;Wildcard Machine Tag URLs&lt;/a&gt;" (18 July 2008)&lt;/span&gt; that showed me how to construct the API queries necessary to get the RSS feeds described above. &lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;That, and &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/services/feeds/docs/photos_public/"&gt;the Flickr API documentation on feeds&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Nate Nagy, Managing Editor of AWIB, who applies the tags and keeps AWIB rolling.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dan Pet, from the &lt;a href="http://finds.org.uk/"&gt;Portable Antiquities Scheme&lt;/a&gt;, and Ryan Baumann, from the &lt;a href="http://www.vis.uky.edu/"&gt;Center for Visualization and Virtual Environments&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Kentucky, who put me onto machine tags in the first place and helped me get up to speed.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>awib</category><category>collaboration</category><category>feeds</category><category>flickr</category><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>pleiades</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2011/09/feeds-of-flickr-photos-depicting/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2011 23:51:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>