<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about boundaries)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://paregorios.org/categories/boundaries.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:ipse@paregorios.org"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;&lt;img
alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
property="dct:title"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;paregorios.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by
&lt;a xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" href="https://paregorios.org/me"
property="cc:attributionName" rel="cc:attributionURL"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; is
licensed under a &lt;a rel="license"
href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 May 2018 12:25:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>People from my dissertation in RDF</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2012/06/people-from-my-dissertation-in-rdf/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;On the road to &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/search/label/demarc"&gt;turning my dissertation into linked data&lt;/a&gt; I've minted URIs for, and produced &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/demarc/blob/master/ttl/people.ttl"&gt;basic RDF for, all of the historical individuals&lt;/a&gt; I dealt with examining boundary disputes internal to the early Roman empire.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I used &lt;a href="http://xmlns.com/foaf/spec/#term_Person"&gt;foaf:Person&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://xmlns.com/foaf/spec/#term_name"&gt;foaf:name&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://vocab.org/bio/0.1/olb.html"&gt;bio:olb&lt;/a&gt; (the latter from the &lt;a href="http://vocab.org/bio/0.1/.html"&gt;BIO Vocabulary for Biographical Information&lt;/a&gt;, developed by Ian Davis and David Galbraith). The Roman emperors who appear in my list have been aligned to &lt;a href="http://dbpedia.org/About"&gt;dbpedia&lt;/a&gt; resources using &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/owl-ref/#sameAs-def"&gt;owl:sameAs&lt;/a&gt;. I intend to do more alignments in future to resources like dbpedia and &lt;a href="http://viaf.org/"&gt;viaf.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here's &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/demarc/blob/master/xml/people.xml"&gt;the XML I started from&lt;/a&gt; (part of an Open Document Text format file I converted from Word), and &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/demarc/blob/master/xsl/people2ttl.xsl"&gt;the XSLT I used to produce the Turtle RDF&lt;/a&gt;, which was then cleaned up by hand.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;More to come.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>boundaries</category><category>demarc</category><category>horothesia</category><category>lawdi</category><category>LOD</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2012/06/people-from-my-dissertation-in-rdf/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2012 11:28:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ancient Studies Needs Open Bibliographic Data and Associated URIs</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2012/06/ancient-studies-needs-open/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;Update 1:  links throughout, minor formatting changes, proper Creative Commons Public Domain tools, parenthetical about import path from Endnote and such, fixing a few typos.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.neh.gov/"&gt;NEH&lt;/a&gt;-funded &lt;a href="http://wiki.digitalclassicist.org/Linked_Ancient_World_Data_Institute"&gt;Linked Ancient World Data Institute&lt;/a&gt;, still in progress at &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt;, has got me thinking about a number of things. One of them is bibliography and linked data. Here's a brain dump, intended to spark conversation and collaboration.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;What We Need&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;As much bibliographic data as possible, for both primary and secondary sources (print and digital), publicly released to third parties under either a public domain declaration or an unrestrictive open license.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Stable HTTP &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_resource_identifier"&gt;URIs&lt;/a&gt; for every work and author included in those datasets.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Why&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Bibliographic and citation collection and management are integral to every research and publication in project in ancient studies. We could save each other a lot of time, and get more substantive work done in the field, if it was simpler and easier to do. We could more easily and effectively tie together disparate work published on the web (and appearing on the web through retrospective digitization) if we had a common infrastructure and shared point of reference. There's already a lot of digital data in various hands that could support such an effort, but a good chunk of it is not out where anybody with good will and talent can get at it to improve it, build tools around it, etc.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;What I Want You (and Me) To Do If You Have Bibliographic Data&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Release it to the world through a third party. No matter what format it's in, give a copy to someone else whose function is hosting free data on the web. Dump it into a public repository at &lt;a href="http://github.com/"&gt;github.com&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://sourceforge.net/"&gt;sourceforge.net&lt;/a&gt;. Put it into a shared library at &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/"&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.bibsonomy.org/"&gt;Bibsonomy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.mendeley.com/"&gt;Mendeley&lt;/a&gt;, or another bibliographic content website (most have easy upload/import paths from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EndNote"&gt;Endnote&lt;/a&gt;, and other citation management applications). Hosting a copy yourself is fine, but giving it to a third party demonstrates your bona fides, gets it out of your nifty but restrictive search engine or database, and increments your bus number.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Release it under a Creative Commons &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/about/pdm"&gt;Public Domain Mark&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/about/cc0"&gt;Public Domain Dedication (CC0)&lt;/a&gt;.  Or if you can't do that, find as open a &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/"&gt;Creative Commons&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_content#Licenses"&gt;similar license&lt;/a&gt; as you can. Don't try to control it. If there's some aspect of the data that you can't (because of rights encumberance) or don't want to (why?) give away to make the world a better place, find a quick way to extract, filter, or excerpt that aspect and get the rest out.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Alert the world to your philanthropy. Blog or tweet about it. Post a link to the data on your institutional website. Above all, alert &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/people/staff/chuck-jones"&gt;Chuck Jones&lt;/a&gt; and Phoebe Acheson so it gets announced via &lt;a href="http://ancientworldonline.blogspot.com/"&gt;Ancient World Online&lt;/a&gt; and/or &lt;a href="http://ancientbiblio.wordpress.com/"&gt;Ancient World Open Bibliographies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do the same if you have other useful data, like identifiers for modern or ancient works or authors.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get in touch with me and/or anyone else to talk about the next step: setting up stable HTTP URIs corresponding to this stuff.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;b&gt;Who I'm Talking To&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;First of all, I'm talking to myself, my collaborators, and my team-mates at ISAW. I intend to eat my own dogfood.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here are other institutions and entities I know about who have potentially useful data.&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="http://openlibrary.org/"&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt; : data about books is already out there and available, and there are ways to add more&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/"&gt;Perseus Project&lt;/a&gt; : a huge, FRBR-ized collection of MODS records for Greek and Latin authors, works, and modern editions thereof.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://chs.harvard.edu/chs"&gt;Center for Hellenic Studies&lt;/a&gt;: identifiers for Greek and Latin authors and works&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.annee-philologique.com/"&gt;L'Année Philologique&lt;/a&gt; and its institutional partners like the &lt;a href="http://www.apaclassics.org/"&gt;American Philological Association&lt;/a&gt;: the big collection of analytic secondary bibliography for classics (journal articles)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://projects.chass.utoronto.ca/amphoras/tocs.html"&gt;TOCS-IN&lt;/a&gt;: a collaboratively collected batch of analytic secondary bibliography for classics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://papyri.info/"&gt;Papyri.info&lt;/a&gt; and its contributing project partners: TEI bibliographic records for  much of the bibliography produced for or cited by Greek and Latin papyrologists (plus other ancient language/script traditions in papyrology)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gnomon-online.de/"&gt;Gnomon Bibliographische Datenbank&lt;/a&gt;: masses of bibliographic data for books and articles for classics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Any and every university library system that has a dedicated or easily extracted set of associated catalog records. Especially any with unique collections (e.g., Cincinnati) or those with databases of analytical bibliography down to the level of articles in journals and collections.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ditto any and every ancient studies digital project that has bibliographic data in a database.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Comments, Reactions, Suggestions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Welcome, encouraged, and essential. By comment here or otherwise (but not private email please!).&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>backstop</category><category>bibliography</category><category>books</category><category>boundaries</category><category>collaboration</category><category>concordia</category><category>digclass</category><category>horothesia</category><category>interop</category><category>isaw</category><category>lawdi</category><category>linkeddata</category><category>openness</category><category>rights</category><category>walled gardens</category><category>zotero</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2012/06/ancient-studies-needs-open/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2012 19:03:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Open-Access Epigraphic Evidence for Boundary Disputes in the Roman Empire</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2012/05/open-access-epigraphic-evidence-for/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I've been sitting on the dissertation way too long. So &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/demarc"&gt;here it is, unleashed upon the world&lt;/a&gt; under the terms of a Creative Commons Attribution Share-alike license.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I have visions of hacking it up into a super-cool, linked data, ever-updated information resource, but there's no reason -- even though it's pretty niche in a lot of ways -- why anyone who might benefit from having, using, or critiquing it meantime should have to wait for that to happen.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Comments, questions, and post-release reviews are welcome via comment here, or via email to tom.elliott@nyu.edu, or on your own blog. And feel free to fork the repos and play around if you're mob-epigraphically inclined.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>boundaries</category><category>epigraphy</category><category>horothesia</category><category>inscriptions</category><category>linkeddata</category><category>LOD</category><category>mob-epigraphy</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2012/05/open-access-epigraphic-evidence-for/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2012 02:07:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>La formation et la définition des frontières locales</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/la-formation-et-la-definition-des/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="http://www.compitum.fr/index.php?option=com_eventlist&amp;amp;Itemid=32&amp;amp;func=details&amp;amp;did=1274"&gt;By way of compitum.fr&lt;/a&gt; I learn about an interesting conference going on today in Poitiers:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;h4 align="justify"&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;h4 align="justify"&gt;Information signalée par Renaud Alexandre&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1 align="center"&gt;La formation et la définition des frontières locales&lt;br&gt;(paroisses, communautés d'habitants)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;h2 align="center"&gt;Cycle de journées d'étude « Frontières et limites ». Session 3&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p align="justify"&gt;Programme&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;9 h 30&lt;br&gt;Ouverture de la journée par Cécile Treffort, directrice adjointe du CESCM et par Stéphane Boissellier, professeur (Université de Poitiers, CESCM)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 align="justify"&gt;Paroisses, présidence Cécile Treffort, professeure (Université de Poitiers, CESCM)&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;div align="justify"&gt;&lt;br&gt;9 h 50&lt;br&gt;Les actes de délimitations paroissiales dans les diocèses de Rennes, Dol et Saint-Malo, entre les XIe et XIIIe siècles&lt;br&gt;Anne Lunven, doctorante (Université de Rennes II)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;10 h 20&lt;br&gt;Limites de paroisses et de villae dans le nord du Portugal&lt;br&gt;Christophe Tropeau, doctorant (Université de Poitiers)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;10 h 50&lt;br&gt;La délimitation des paroisses de l'ancien diocèse de Liège ( XIIe -XVe siècles)&lt;br&gt;Julie Dury, doctorante (Université de Liège)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;11 h 20        Discussion&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;12 h 00        Repas (buffet sur place)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2 align="justify"&gt;Autres circonscriptions, présidence Luc Bourgeois, maître de conférences (Université de Poitiers, CESCM)&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;div align="justify"&gt;13 h 30&lt;br&gt;Les frontières des territoires locaux dans l'espace gaulois de Sidoine Apollinaire à Grégoire de Tours&lt;br&gt;Pierre-Eric Poble, post-doctorant (Université de Paris IV)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;14 h 00&lt;br&gt;Villa, ban, court et mairie Formation et définition des frontières locales dans les seigneuries de l'abbaye de Stavelot-Malmedy (XIe - XVe s.)&lt;br&gt;Nicolas Schroeder, doctorant (Université libre Bruxelles)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;14 h 30&lt;br&gt;Réflexions autour des limites des agglomérations à la fin du Moyen-Âge en Basse-Bretagne,&lt;br&gt;Régis Le Gall, doctorant (Université de Poitiers)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;15 h 00&lt;br&gt;Délimiter l'espace maritime dans la Bretagne de la fin du XVe siècle, d'après les archives ducales&lt;br&gt;Frédérique Laget, doctorante (Université de Nantes)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;15 h 30&lt;br&gt;Discussion&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;16 h 20&lt;br&gt;Conclusions&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Source : &lt;a href="http://www.mshs.univ-poitiers.fr/cescm/spip.php?article251"&gt;Centre d'Études Supérieures de Civilisation Médiévale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>boundaries</category><category>conferences</category><category>horothesia</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/la-formation-et-la-definition-des/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2009 19:43:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Determinationes, past and present</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/05/determinationes-past-and-present/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Determinatio&lt;/span&gt; is a Latin term (Greek: ἀφορισμός or ὁροθέσια) for the written, serial description of boundaries, produced as necessary by Roman surveyors and routinely included in the verdicts of Roman (pro-)magistrates and &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;iudices&lt;/span&gt; when settling boundary disputes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here's an example, dating to the early second century CE:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Serving as proconsul of either Achaia or Macedonia, &lt;a href="http://www.forumromanum.org/literature/sentius_augurinusx.html"&gt;Q. Gellius Augurinus&lt;/a&gt; delivered the following verdict in a boundary dispute between the Thessalian communities of &lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?hl=en&amp;amp;client=firefox-a&amp;amp;q=Lamia+Greece&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;split=0&amp;amp;gl=us&amp;amp;ei=lIYeSub-C6Gstgel2cjsAw&amp;amp;ll=38.898515,22.434082&amp;amp;spn=0.718216,1.455688&amp;amp;z=10"&gt;Lamia&lt;/a&gt; and Hypata (mod. &lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=s_q&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=&amp;amp;q=Ypati+Greece&amp;amp;sll=38.825801,22.240448&amp;amp;sspn=0.359476,0.727844&amp;amp;gl=us&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;ll=38.855751,22.241135&amp;amp;spn=0.359325,0.727844&amp;amp;z=11&amp;amp;iwloc=A"&gt;Ypati&lt;/a&gt;). His ruling was subsequently inscribed, and was first recorded by modern scholars in 1855 in the Greek village of &lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=s_q&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=&amp;amp;q=Mexiates&amp;amp;sll=38.881412,22.309799&amp;amp;sspn=0.179598,0.363922&amp;amp;gl=us&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;ll=38.883198,22.313258&amp;amp;spn=0.179593,0.363922&amp;amp;z=12"&gt;Myxiates&lt;/a&gt;, where the stone had been reused in building a house.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;CIL 3.12306; ILS 5947a; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style="font-weight: bold;" href="http://books.google.com/books?id=LLRBfq0mbHcC&amp;amp;pg=PA19&amp;amp;lpg=PA19&amp;amp;dq=Myxiates&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=HDbcXKqYP-&amp;amp;sig=GhY2shnfLqmYzZL_WWe1fFDDKhI&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=-4IeSv6dMpTDtweiltnsAw&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=2#PPA19,M1"&gt;IG IX/2 p. 19 (before no. 60)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;; CIL 3.586; Henzen 1856; Smallwood 1966 447. See also: Stählin 1924, 220-222; RE s.v. Hypata.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Q(uinto) Gellio Sentio Augurino proco(n)s(ule) decreta / ex tabellis recitata kalendis Martis. Cum optimus maximusque princeps / Traianus Hadrianus Aug(ustus) scripserit mihi uti adhibitis menso/ribus de controversiis finium inter Lamienses et Hypataeos cognita causa / terminarem egoque in rem praesentem saepius et continuis diebus /&lt;/span&gt;5&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt; fuerim cognoverimque praesentibus utriusque civitatis defensoribus, / adhibito a me Iulio Victore evocato Augusti mensore, placet initium / finium esse ab eo loco in quo Siden fuisse comperi, quae est infra con/saeptum consecratum Neptuno, indeque descendentibus rigorem ser/vari usque ad fontem Dercynnam, qui est trans flumen Sperchion, it[a ut per] /&lt;/span&gt;10 &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;amphispora Lamiensium et Hypataeorum rigor at fontem Dercynn[am supra] / scriptum ducat et inde ad tumulum Pelion per decursum Sir [---] /  at monimentum Euryti quod est intra finem Lam[iensium --- ] / [---] Erycaniorum et Proherniorum [---] / [---] thraxum et Sido [---] /15 [---] const [ ------&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Translation (mine):&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Verdicts recited from the tablets when Quintus Gellius Sentius Augurinus was proconsul, on the kalends of March. Since the best and greatest princeps, Trajan Hadrian Augustus, wrote to me that, once surveyors had been consulted concerning the boundary disputes between the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Lamienses&lt;/span&gt; and the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Hypataeoi&lt;/span&gt;, and the case had been investigated, I should make a boundary demarcation; and, since, in the case at hand, I was present often and for successive days, and I investigated with the defenders of both cities being present and with Iulius Victor, evocatus of the emperor, a surveyor, being consulted by me, let it be that the start of the boundary be from that place in which I have learned Side was, which is below the enclosed area consecrated to Neptune; and thence in descending to preserve a straight line all the way to the spring (called) Dercynna, which is across the river Sperchion, so that a straight line leads through the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;amphispora&lt;/span&gt; of the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Lamienses&lt;/span&gt; and the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Hypataeoi&lt;/span&gt; to the above-mentioned spring Dercynna; and thence to the tumulus (called) Pelion along the slope (called) Sir... to the monument of Eurytos which is within the boundaries of the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Lamienses&lt;/span&gt; ...&lt;/blockquote&gt;This same genre is still in use in legal property descriptions in the United States today. I stumbled across another example this morning in the revised Huntsville downtown planning and zoning document, now awaiting approval by the city council (&lt;span class="main_text"&gt;&lt;span class="main_text"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.hsvcity.com/Planning/Art23-GenBusC3BufferZones2.pdf"&gt;ARTICLE 23 GENERAL BUSINESS C-3 DISTRICT REGULATIONS&lt;/a&gt;, pp. 9ff):&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Within Historic District Buffer Zone B, the maximum number of stories shall be four (4) stories with a maximum height of sixty (60) feet.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Historic District Buffer Zone B is defined as the property that lies within the following boundaries: Begin at the the intersection of the centerlines of Clinton Avenue and Monroe Street/Lincoln Street; then in a southerly direction along the centerline of Monroe Street/Lincoln Street to the intersection of the centerlines of Lincoln Street and Randolph Avenue; then West along the centerline of Randolph Avenue to the intersection of the centerlines of Randolph Avenue and Green Street; then South along the centerline of Green Street to the intersection of the centerlines of Green Street and Eustis Avenue; then West along the centerline of Eustis Avenue to the intersection of the centerlines of Eustis Avenue and Franklin Street; then South along Franklin Street to the intersection of the centerlines of Franklin ... [ it goes on and on, of course! ]&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;Truly, a morning of geekish glee for me ...&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Thanks to James at the &lt;a href="http://huntsvilledevelopment.blogspot.com/2009/05/planning-commission-approves-buffer.html"&gt;Huntsville Development Blog&lt;/a&gt; for posting the link.</description><category>boundaries</category><category>epigraphy</category><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><category>inscriptions</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/05/determinationes-past-and-present/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2009 18:11:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>John Hessler on Physical and Epigraphical Remains of Roman Centuriation and Surveying in Tunisia (25 February 2009)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/02/john-hessler-on-physical-and/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;By way of Lawrence Summers' post to the MapHist list, I just learned of the following &lt;a href="http://www.loc.gov/today/pr/2009/09-030.html"&gt;public lecture, to be given by John Hessler at the Library of Congress&lt;/a&gt; on the 25th of February, 2009:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;John W. Hessler, a senior reference librarian in the Geography and Map Division of the Library of Congress and fellow of the Royal Geographical Society, will present "In the Footsteps of Caesar: Searching for the Physical and Epigraphical Remains of Roman Centuriation and Surveying in Tunisia" at noon on Wednesday, Feb. 25. The lecture will be held in the Geography and Map Reading Room, in the basement level of the James Madison Building, 101 Independence Ave. S.E., Washington, D.C.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Sponsored by the &lt;a href="http://www.loc.gov/rr/geogmap/"&gt;Geography and Map Division&lt;/a&gt;, the event is free and open to the public; tickets and reservations are not required. The lecture is part of the division's "Map Talk" series.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In his lecture, Hessler will provide a brief description of the cartography and surveying techniques employed by the Romans in North Africa; a description of a sixth-century manuscript known as "Corpus Agrimensorum," which spells out how the Romans surveyed their territories; and a travel log describing his search for the physical remains of Roman surveying practices in Tunisia and Southern France.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>ancgeo</category><category>boundaries</category><category>epigraphy</category><category>horothesia</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/02/john-hessler-on-physical-and/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2009 21:46:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Thraces and Moesi update</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/02/thraces-and-moesi-update/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="http://masters-classics.dir.bg/Publ_NSh.htm"&gt;Nikolay Sharankov&lt;/a&gt; has just posted &lt;a href="http://www.currentepigraphy.org/2008/02/22/query-a-hadrianic-boundary-marker-from-bulgaria/#comment-3488"&gt;a thorough and helpful response&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2008/02/demarcation-between-thraces-and-moesi.html"&gt;my recent query about a Roman boundary inscription from Bulgaria&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;He includes revised readings -- not only of the inscription for which I have the photo -- but for all four originally published by Hristov in &lt;span style="font-style:italic;"&gt;Minalo&lt;/span&gt;.</description><category>bibliography</category><category>boundaries</category><category>demarc</category><category>horothesia</category><category>inscriptions</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/02/thraces-and-moesi-update/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2008 05:45:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Demarcation Between the T(h)races and Moesi</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/02/demarcation-between-thraces-and-moesi/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;In working up our &lt;a href="http://zcologia.com/news/691/digitizing-ancient-inscriptions-with-openlayers/"&gt;OpenLayers + SVG image tracing demo&lt;/a&gt; today, &lt;a href="http://zcologia.com/sgillies/"&gt;Sean&lt;/a&gt; and I selected &lt;a href="http://homepages.nyu.edu/%7Ete20/demarc/examples/b.jpg"&gt;a picture of a Roman boundary marker&lt;/a&gt; as our example image. &lt;a href="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/schools/humanities/bmgs/staff/roueche.html"&gt;Charlotte Roueché&lt;/a&gt; had taken this picture in the garden of the Bulgarian National Museum in 2006. She sent it to me because of the work I'd done on &lt;a href="http://homepages.nyu.edu/%7Ete20/dissertation.html"&gt;my Chapel Hill dissertation about Roman boundary markers&lt;/a&gt;. This particular inscription proved to belong to an instance of demarcation that I'd treated in the dissertation, but this text was not specifically in my catalog. I assumed it was either unpublished, or had been so at the  time I was finishing the dissertation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It appears now that this inscription is either unpublished, or I've failed to spot the publication. I provide the account and background below in the hopes that readers can provide a citation for this particular text, or information about other evidence related to this particular event that I have so far missed. Corrections to what follows are also welcome.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;In 2003 or so I wrote (for the dissertation) about this group of inscriptions as follows:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Six boundary markers from various sites in Bulgaria attest to a demarcation between the provinces of &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Thracia&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Moesia Inferior&lt;/span&gt; [in AD 135]. These are the only markers in the published epigraphic record that explicitly marked a provincial boundary without making reference to any of the cities or communities in either province. The word &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;provincia&lt;/span&gt; is not used. The ethnics corresponding to the provincial names are: &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Moesi&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Thraces&lt;/span&gt;. The markers were placed, on &lt;a href="http://www.roman-emperors.org/hadrian.htm"&gt;Hadrian’s&lt;/a&gt; authority, by an otherwise unknown individual named [M(arcus)] Antius Rufus, who is thought to have been acting as a special legate of the emperor. It is most unlikely that he was a governor of either of the provinces in question, since neither governor can have possessed a sufficient span of jurisdiction to affect both provinces. The context and motivation for this demarcation are completely obscure.&lt;/blockquote&gt;Here's a transcription and translation of this particular text, made from the image:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;div style="font-family: GentiumAlt, Gentium, 'Palatino Linotype', 'Palatino', 'Lucida Grande', 'Times New Roman'; margin-left: 1.5em;"&gt;&lt;span id="l-1"&gt;    ex auctoritate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id="l-2"&gt;    Imp(eratoris) Cae(saris) divi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id="l-3"&gt;    Tra(iani) Parth(ici) f(i)l(i) di-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id="l-4"&gt;    vi Nerv(ae) nep(otis) Tra(iani)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id="l-5"&gt;   Had(riani) Aug(usti) p(atris) p(atriae) poṇ[t?]-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;font-size:85%;"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id="l-6"&gt;    if(icis) maxi(mi) trib(unicia) poṭ(estate)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id="l-7"&gt;    XX co(n)s(ulis) III M(arcus) An[ti?]-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id="l-8"&gt;    us Rufinus inter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id="l-9"&gt;    T(h)racas (!) et Moe-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id="l-10"&gt;  sos fines posụ[it?]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;font-size:85%;"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style="font-style: italic;font-size:85%;"&gt;vacat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;By the authority of the emperor Caesar, son of the god Trajan Parthicus, grandson of the god Nerva, Trajan &lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Hadrian&lt;/span&gt; Augustus, father of the country, pontifex maximus, (holding the) tribunician power 20 (times), consul 3 (times), M(arcus) Antius Rufinus placed boundaries between the Thraces and the Moesi.&lt;br&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Notes&lt;/h4&gt;The rectangular stone was prepared with a deep rectangular campus that left a heavy external border (I do not have measurements).  This frame (and an uninscribed portion of the campus) is broken away at the top right corner. Beginning at the level of line 7, the border has been snapped away at a depth just below that of the campus. The bottom of the stone is missing, but it is clear that the main text terminates above a large empty space before the break.&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;5, end: Part of an N on the upward-sloping portion of the border (i.e., just outside the prepared campus). This may have included a ligature with T that has been worn away(?).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;6, end: What appears to be a small, irregular T cut across the transition from prepared campus to border.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;7, end: if TI were inscribed on the border, this has been lost; there is no room for the characters in the prepared campus.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;7-8: Rufinus: &lt;a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/22316528"&gt;PIR2&lt;/a&gt; A784 + &lt;a href="http://www.bbaw.de/forschung/pir/addenda/A/0784.html"&gt;addenda&lt;/a&gt;; Thomasson 1984 20:78 + 22:16; Aichinger 1982, 198-199.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Comments&lt;/h4&gt;Now, in looking at this image more closely (and starting to hunt for a corresponding publication), I see that I missed at least one of these inscriptions, and yet another has subsequently appeared. But I still haven't been able to identify a published text of this particular inscription. It clearly shares a source text with [EDH HD045725] = [AE 2004.1306] = I. Christov, &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Minalo&lt;/span&gt; 11, 2004, 6-7, no. 4 (citations from EDH), but the text is laid out differently on the stone. It would be interesting to have access to an image of this doppelgänger, but I can't immediately put my hands on a copy of &lt;a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/31254228"&gt;the journal Минало&lt;/a&gt;. These are the only two of the inscriptions I know of that put the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Thraces&lt;/span&gt; before the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Moesi&lt;/span&gt;; the majority of the texts have the inverse order.&lt;br&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Concordance of Editions&lt;/h4&gt;Here's my list of texts and corresponding publications as it stands now:&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Elliott 2004.95.1; EDH &lt;a href="http://edh12.iaw.uni-heidelberg.de:8080/EDH/servlet/EgrForm?aktion=eingabe&amp;amp;benutzer=gast&amp;amp;kennwort=g2dhst&amp;amp;f_id_nr=%27HD042659%27"&gt;HD042659&lt;/a&gt;; IGLNovae 73; ILBulg 357; ILS 5956; CIL 3.749&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Elliott 2004.95.2; EDH &lt;a href="http://edh12.iaw.uni-heidelberg.de:8080/EDH/servlet/EgrForm?aktion=eingabe&amp;amp;benutzer=gast&amp;amp;kennwort=g2dhst&amp;amp;f_id_nr=%27HD042812%27"&gt;HD042812&lt;/a&gt;; ILBulg 429; CIL 3.12407&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Elliott 2004.95.3; EDH &lt;a href="http://edh12.iaw.uni-heidelberg.de:8080/EDH/servlet/EgrForm?aktion=eingabe&amp;amp;benutzer=gast&amp;amp;kennwort=g2dhst&amp;amp;f_id_nr=%27HD006328%27"&gt;HD006328&lt;/a&gt;; ILBulg 390; AE 1985.729; Banev 1981, no. 1&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Elliott 2004.95.4; EDH &lt;a href="http://edh12.iaw.uni-heidelberg.de:8080/EDH/servlet/EgrForm?aktion=eingabe&amp;amp;benutzer=gast&amp;amp;kennwort=g2dhst&amp;amp;f_id_nr=%27HD006340%27"&gt;HD006340&lt;/a&gt;; ILBulg 386; AE 1985.730; Banev 1981; CIL 3 p. 992 n. 749&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Elliott 2004.95.5; EDH &lt;a href="http://edh12.iaw.uni-heidelberg.de:8080/EDH/servlet/EgrForm?aktion=eingabe&amp;amp;benutzer=gast&amp;amp;kennwort=g2dhst&amp;amp;f_id_nr=%27HD006322%27"&gt;HD006322&lt;/a&gt;; AE 1985.733; Božilova 1985; ILNovae 51; IGLNovae 72&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Elliott 2004.95.6; EDH &lt;a href="http://edh12.iaw.uni-heidelberg.de:8080/EDH/servlet/EgrForm?aktion=eingabe&amp;amp;benutzer=gast&amp;amp;kennwort=g2dhst&amp;amp;f_id_nr=%27HD031971%27"&gt;HD031971&lt;/a&gt;; ILBulg 358; CIL 3.14422/1; AE 1902.106&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;EDH &lt;a href="http://edh12.iaw.uni-heidelberg.de:8080/EDH/servlet/EgrForm?aktion=eingabe&amp;amp;benutzer=gast&amp;amp;kennwort=g2dhst&amp;amp;f_id_nr=%27HD042658%27"&gt;HD042658&lt;/a&gt;; ILBulg 184; AE 1912, 16 n. 56; Filow &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;BullSocArchBulg&lt;/span&gt; 2 (1911), 271 (not checked, bibliography per EDH)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;EDH &lt;a href="http://edh12.iaw.uni-heidelberg.de:8080/EDH/servlet/EgrForm?aktion=eingabe&amp;amp;benutzer=gast&amp;amp;kennwort=g2dhst&amp;amp;f_id_nr=%27HD045725%27"&gt;HD045725&lt;/a&gt;; AE 2004.1306; . Christov, &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Minalo&lt;/span&gt; 11 (2004), 6-7, no. 4 (not checked, bibliography per EDH)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;[ &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Horothesia&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2008/02/demarcation-between-thraces-and-moesi.html"&gt;"Demarcation Between the T(h)races and Moesi" (22 February 2007)&lt;/a&gt; ]&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h4&gt;Short titles used here are glossed in the PDF versions of my &lt;a href="http://homepages.nyu.edu/%7Ete20/diss/abbreviations.pdf"&gt;abbreviations list&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://homepages.nyu.edu/%7Ete20/diss/worksCited.pdf"&gt;works cited list&lt;/a&gt;. Eventually, all these works will be folded into the Pleiades bibliography.</description><category>boundaries</category><category>demarc</category><category>epigraphy</category><category>horothesia</category><category>inscriptions</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/02/demarcation-between-thraces-and-moesi/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2008 05:51:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>EpiDoc meets dissertation: epigraphic bibliography</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/02/epidoc-meets-dissertation-epigraphic/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first in &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/search/label/demarc"&gt;a highly irregular series&lt;/a&gt; exploring aspects of my attempt to turn my &lt;a href="http://homepages.nyu.edu/~te20/dissertation.html"&gt;dissertation&lt;/a&gt; (or parts thereof) into a digital publication using the &lt;a href="http://epidoc.sf.net/"&gt;EpiDoc&lt;/a&gt; customization of the &lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/"&gt;Text Encoding Initiative&lt;/a&gt; tagset (in XML). I'm starting using a batch of boundary inscriptions from Roman Cyrenaica, partly because I'm working with a team in London and Cambridge that is working on &lt;a href="http://ircyr.kcl.ac.uk/"&gt;the definitive publication of the Roman Inscriptions of Cyrenaica (IRCyr) as collected and analyzed by Joyce Reynolds&lt;/a&gt;. This collection will include a number of previously unpublished boundary inscriptions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Today's topic: epigraphic bibliography&lt;/h4&gt;There are various examples of code below, but you can also &lt;a href="http://homepages.nyu.edu/%7Ete20/demarc/examples/demarc-biblio-2007-02-20.xml"&gt;download a fully encoded example&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A proper epigraphic edition includes a complete history of previous published editions, published derivative texts, corrections and, often, commentary on same.  There are various common mechanisms for presenting these citations in print, usually in a compact form that makes liberal use of abbreviations and short titles. Thus, text 62.2 in my dissertation (of Claudian date), presented the following bibliography:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.uni-heidelberg.de/institute/sonst/adw/edh/"&gt;EDH&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://edh12.iaw.uni-heidelberg.de:8080/EDH/servlet/EgrForm?aktion=eingabe&amp;amp;benutzer=gast&amp;amp;kennwort=g2dhst&amp;amp;f_id_nr=%27HD011697%27"&gt;HD011697&lt;/a&gt; (Latin); &lt;a href="http://www.unc.edu/awmc/pleiades/bibliography/seg.html"&gt;SEG&lt;/a&gt; 26.1819; &lt;a href="http://www.unc.edu/awmc/pleiades/bibliography/ae.html"&gt;AE&lt;/a&gt; 1974.682; *Reynolds 1971, 47-49.1.&lt;/blockquote&gt;Here, order signifies date and the asterisk indicates the edition I follow in my own catalog. So, we can read this as:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Originally published in Reynolds 1971, 47-49.1, whence derivative editions in AE 1974.682, SEG 26.1819 and EDH HD011697 (the latter only providing the Latin portion of this bilingual Greek/Latin text).&lt;/blockquote&gt;Often, such bibliographies include other notation to indicate the "genetic lemma" (derivative relationships) between publications. So, one could have produced something like:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;[EDH HD011697 (Latin)] = [SEG 26.1819] = [AE 1974.682] = Reynolds 1971, 47-49.1&lt;/blockquote&gt;where the square brackets indicate derivative editions, i.e., those that derive from another published edition rather than autopsy of the stone and/or reference to a squeeze, rubbing or photograph. This particular lemma is a little misleading, since the provisional EDH edition actually derives from the edition in AE, which is itself derivative of the Reynolds edition.&lt;br&gt;&lt;h4&gt;How to do this in EpiDoc?&lt;/h4&gt;Let's start with something like the more prose-ish of the above examples, since this is the approach IRCyr is using (demonstrated in &lt;a href="http://www.insaph.kcl.ac.uk/ala2004/"&gt;ALA2004&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/iaph2007/index.html"&gt;IAph2007&lt;/a&gt;). First, EpiDoc calls for the bibliography to be wrapped in an appropriately typed &amp;lt;&lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-div.html"&gt;div&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; element, as follows:&lt;br&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;div type="bibliography"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt; &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Original publication was Reynolds 1971, 47-49.1,&lt;br&gt;    whence derivative editions in AE 1974.682, SEG 26.1819&lt;br&gt;    and Elliott 2004, 167.62.2. The Latin portion of the&lt;br&gt;    text is reproduced in EDH HD011697 (1997, provisional)&lt;br&gt;    on the basis of AE.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;Part of the reason to do our bibliography in XML is to be able to encode relationships, assertions and semantic distinctions in a way that is machine actionable. On the bibliographic front, we might want to be able to search, sort and index by these other editions, or link to them if digitally available. That means we need to mark each citation as a discrete bibliographic citation, and TEI provides the &amp;lt;&lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-bibl.html"&gt;bibl&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; element for this purpose:&lt;br&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;div type="bibliography"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt; &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Original publication was&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl&amp;gt;Reynolds 1971, 47-49.1&amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;,&lt;br&gt;   whence derivative editions in&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl&amp;gt;AE 1974.682&amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;,&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl&amp;gt;SEG 26.1819&amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;   and&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl&amp;gt;Elliott 2004, 167.62.2&amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;.&lt;br&gt;   The Latin portion of the text is reproduced in&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl&amp;gt;EDH HD011697 (1997, provisional)&amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;   on the basis of AE.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;We may want to have a search function distinguish between original editions and those that are derivative, so we need to encode that distinction too. We don't want to have to parse text strings and try to infer the meaning of phrases like "original publication" or "derviative". Rather, we'll use the standard TEI "type" and "subtype" attributes on the &amp;lt;bibl&amp;gt; element to make this distinction clear for our little silicon friends. The values we're using for this attribute are specific to the EpiDoc customization of TEI.&lt;br&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;div type="bibliography"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt; &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Original publication was&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl type="edition" subtype="primary"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;     Reynolds 1971, 47-49.1&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;,&lt;br&gt;   whence derivative editions in&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl type="edition" subtype="derivative"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;     AE 1974.682&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;,&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl type="edition" subtype="derivative"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;     SEG 26.1819&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;   and&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl type="edition" subtype="derivative"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;     Elliott 2004, 167.62.2&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;.&lt;br&gt;   The Latin portion of the text is reproduced in&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl type="edition" subtype="derivative"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;     EDH HD011697 (1997, provisional)&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;   on the basis of AE.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's additional tagging internal to each &amp;lt;bibl&amp;gt; element that we can/should do to facilitate sorting, searching and linking to digital/digitized works, but we'll skip over that here (check out the &lt;a href="http://homepages.nyu.edu/%7Ete20/demarc/examples/demarc-biblio-2007-02-20.xml"&gt;example file&lt;/a&gt; for the full encoding).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The only thing our example doesn't do that we might like is encode the derivative relationships between the various editions. We know that one is "primary" and the others "derivative", but it's not clear what the path of derivation is for each one. EpiDoc doesn't currently have guidance for this, and I'm not sure what the broader TEI community thinks (I'm posting a link to this entry on TEI-L to find out), but it occurs to me that this would be pretty easy to do with the TEI &amp;lt;&lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-link.html"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; element. We'll need unique identifiers on each &amp;lt;bibl&amp;gt; element to make use of this approach.&lt;br&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;div type="bibliography"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt; &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Original publication was&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl xml:id="reynolds-1971-1" type="edition" subtype="primary"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;     Reynolds 1971, 47-49.1&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;,&lt;br&gt;   whence derivative editions in&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl xml:id="ae-1974-682" type="edition" subtype="derivative"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;     AE 1974.682&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;,&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl xml:id="seg-26-1819" type="edition" subtype="derivative"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;     SEG 26.1819&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;   and&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl xml:id="elliott-2004-62-1" type="edition" subtype="derivative"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;     Elliott 2004, 167.62.2&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;.&lt;br&gt;   The Latin portion of the text is reproduced in&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;bibl xml:id="edh-hd011697" type="edition" subtype="derivative"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;     EDH HD011697 (1997, provisional)&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;/bibl&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;   on the basis of AE.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;link targets="#reynolds-1971-1 #ae-1974-682 #seg-26-1819 #elliott-2004-62-1"/&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;   &amp;lt;link targets="#ae-1974-682 #edh-hd011697"/&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;Stay tuned for further adventures, in which we exploit some of this bibliographic tagging, and then move on to encoding the epigraphic text itself.</description><category>boundaries</category><category>demarc</category><category>epidoc</category><category>epigraphy</category><category>horothesia</category><category>inscriptions</category><category>tei</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/02/epidoc-meets-dissertation-epigraphic/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2008 22:40:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Graduate Conference in Ancient Borderlands</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2007/10/graduate-conference-in-ancient/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;By way of David Meadow's &lt;a href="http://www.atrium-media.com/rogueclassicism/"&gt;rogueclassicism&lt;/a&gt;, I spotted &lt;a href="http://www.ihc.ucsb.edu/research/borderlands/flyer2.html"&gt;this call for papers for a Graduate Conference in Ancient Borderlands&lt;/a&gt;, to be held 22-23 March 2008 at the University of California Santa Barbara. Abstracts due 1 December 2007.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;A forum in which participants from a variety of fields and areas of expertise can explore both physical and intellectual borderlands in the ancient world. The specific disciplines the Graduate Student Conference aims to involve include Anthropology, Archaeology, Art History, Asian Studies, Classics, History, Medieval Studies, Mesoamerican Studies, Near Eastern Studies, Philosophy, and Religious Studies.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>boundaries</category><category>conferences</category><category>horothesia</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2007/10/graduate-conference-in-ancient/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2007 17:07:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>