<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about concordia)</title><link>http://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://paregorios.org/categories/concordia.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:paregorios@hotmail.com"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 22:06:17 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Citing Sources in Digital Annotations</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2013/04/citing-sources-in-digital-annotations/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm collaborating with other folks both in and outside &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt; on a variety of digital scholarly projects in which &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/LinkedData.html"&gt;Linked Open Data&lt;/a&gt; is playing a big role. We're using the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resource_Description_Framework"&gt;Resource Description Framework (RDF)&lt;/a&gt; to provide descriptive information for, and make cross-project assertions about, a variety of entities of interest and the data associated with them (places, people, themes/subjects, creative works, bibliographic items, and manuscripts and other text-bearing objects). So, for example, I can produce the following assertions in RDF (using the &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TeamSubmission/turtle/"&gt;Terse RDF Triple Language, or TuRTLe&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre style="font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; color: #000000; background-color: #eee;font-size: 12px;border: 1px dashed #999999;line-height: 14px;padding: 5px; overflow: auto; width: 100%"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45&amp;gt; a &amp;lt;http://geovocab.org/spatial#Feature&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  rdfs:label "Serugh" ;&lt;br&gt;  rdfs:comment "An ancient city where Jacob of Serugh was bishop."@en ;&lt;br&gt;  foaf:primaryTopicOf &amp;lt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suruç&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  owl:sameAs &amp;lt;http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/658405#this&amp;gt; .&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;This means: 'There's a resource identified with the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_resource_identifier"&gt;Uniform Resource Identifier (URI)&lt;/a&gt; "http://syriaca.org/place/45" about which the following is asserted: &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;it is a "Feature" as defined in the &lt;a href="http://geovocab.org/spatial.html"&gt;NeoGeo Spatial Ontology&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-schema/#ch_label"&gt;human-readable version of its name&lt;/a&gt; is "Serugh";&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-schema/#ch_comment"&gt;a human-readable description&lt;/a&gt; (in the English language) of it is "An ancient city where Jacob of Serugh was bishop.";&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;it is &lt;a href="http://xmlns.com/foaf/spec/#term_isPrimaryTopicOf"&gt;the primary topic of a document&lt;/a&gt; that is identified by the URI "http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suruç"; and&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;it is &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/owl-ref/#sameAs-def"&gt;the same resource as&lt;/a&gt; that identified by another URI: "http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/658405#this".'&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br&gt;(Folks familiar with what &lt;a href="http://sgillies.net/"&gt;Sean Gillies&lt;/a&gt; has done for the &lt;a href="https://github.com/isawnyu/pleiades-rdf"&gt;Pleiades RDF&lt;/a&gt; will recognize my debt to him in the what proceeds.) &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But there are plenty of cases in which just issuing a couple of &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-rdf-concepts-20040210/#dfn-rdf-triple"&gt;triples&lt;/a&gt; to encode an assertion about something isn't sufficient; we need to be able to assign responsibility/origin for those assertions and to link them to supporting argument and evidence (i.e., standard scholarly citation practice). For this purpose, we're very pleased by the &lt;a href="http://www.openannotation.org/"&gt;Open Annotation Collaboration&lt;/a&gt;, whose &lt;i&gt;Open Annotation Data Model&lt;/i&gt; was recently updated and expanded in the form of a &lt;a href="http://www.openannotation.org/spec/core/"&gt;W3C Community Draft (8 February 2013)&lt;/a&gt; (the participants in &lt;a href="http://pelagios-project.blogspot.com/"&gt;Pelagios&lt;/a&gt; use basic OAC annotations to assert geographic relationships between their data and Pleiades places).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A basic OADM annotation uses a series of RDF triples to link together a "target" (the thing you want to make an assertion about) and a "body" (the content of your assertion). You can think of them as footnotes. The "target" is the range of text after which you put your footnote number (only in OADM you can add a footnote to any real, conceptual, or digital thing you can identify) and the "body" is the content of the footnote itself. &lt;a href="http://www.openannotation.org/spec/core/core.html#BodyTarget"&gt;The OADM draft formally explains this structure in section 2.1&lt;/a&gt;. This lets me add an annotation to the resource from our example above (the ancient city of Serugh) by using the URI "http://syriaca.org/place/45" as the target of an annotation) thus: &lt;br&gt;&lt;pre style="font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; color: #000000; background-color: #eee;font-size: 12px;border: 1px dashed #999999;line-height: 14px;padding: 5px; overflow: auto; width: 100%"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45/anno/desc6&amp;gt; a oa:Annotation ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:hasBody &amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45/anno/desc6/body&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:hasTarget &amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:motivatedBy oa:describing ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:annotatedBy &amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/editors.xml#tcarlson&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:annotatedAt "2013-04-03T00:00:01Z" ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:serializedBy &amp;lt;https://github.com/paregorios/srpdemo1/blob/master/xsl/place2ttl.xsl&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:serializedAt "2013-04-17T13:35:05.771-05:00" .&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45/anno/desc6/body&amp;gt; a cnt:ContentAsText, dctypes:Text ;&lt;br&gt;  cnt:chars "an ancient town, formerly located near Sarug."@en ;&lt;br&gt;  dc:format "text/plain" ;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;I hope you'll forgive me for not spelling that all out in plain text, as all the syntax and terms are explained in the OADM. What I'm concerned about in this blog post is really what the OADM &lt;strong&gt;doesn't&lt;/strong&gt; explicitly tell me how to do, namely: show that the annotation body is actually a quotation from a published book. The verb oa:annotatedBy lets me indicate that the annotation itself was made (i.e., the footnote was written) by a resource identified by the URI "http://syriaca.org/editors.xml#tcarlson". If I'd given you a few more triples, you could have figured out that that resource is a real person named Thomas Carlson, who is one of the editors working on the &lt;a href="http://syriaca.org"&gt;Syriac Reference Portal project&lt;/a&gt;. But how do I indicate (as he very much wants to do because he's a responsible scholar and has no interest in plagiarizing anyone) that he's deliberately quoting a book called &lt;a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/255043315"&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Scattered Pearls: A History of Syriac Literature and Sciences&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;? Here's what I came up with (using terms from &lt;a href="http://purl.org/spar/cito/"&gt;Citation Typing Ontology&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/"&gt;DCMI Metadata Terms&lt;/a&gt;): &lt;br&gt;&lt;pre style="font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; color: #000000; background-color: #eee;font-size: 12px;border: 1px dashed #999999;line-height: 14px;padding: 5px; overflow: auto; width: 100%"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45/anno/desc7/body&amp;gt; a cnt:ContentAsText, dctypes:Text ;&lt;br&gt;  cnt:chars "a small town in the Mudar territory, between Ḥarran and Jarabulus. [Modern name, Suruç (tr.)]"@en ;&lt;br&gt;  dc:format "text/plain" ;&lt;br&gt;  cito:citesAsSourceDocument &amp;lt;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/255043315&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  dcterms:biblographicCitation  "The Scattered Pearls: A History of Syriac Literature and Sciences, p. 558"@en .&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;The addition of the triple containing cito:citesAsSourceDocument lets me make a machine-actionable link to the additional structured bibliographic data about the book that's available at Worldcat (but it doesn't say anything about page numbers!). The addition of the triple containing dcterms:bibliographicCitation lets me provide a human-readable citation. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'd love to have feedback on this approach from folks in the OAC, CITO, DCTERMS, and general linked data communities. Could I do better? Should I do something differently? &lt;br&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;br&gt;The SRP team is currently evaluating a sample batch of such annotations, which you're also welcome to view. The &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/srpdemo1/tree/master/rdf/place"&gt;RDF can be found here&lt;/a&gt;. These files are generated from &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/srpdemo1/tree/master/xml/places"&gt;the TEI XML here&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/srpdemo1/blob/master/xsl/place2ttl.xsl"&gt;the XSLT here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;</description><category>bibliography</category><category>collaboration</category><category>concordia</category><category>data</category><category>interop</category><category>isaw</category><category>lawdi</category><category>linkeddata</category><category>LOD</category><category>neogeography</category><category>patterns</category><category>pelagios</category><category>pleiades</category><category>rdf</category><category>tei</category><category>xml</category><category>xslt</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2013/04/citing-sources-in-digital-annotations/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2013 23:35:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ancient Studies Needs Open Bibliographic Data and Associated URIs</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/06/ancient-studies-needs-open/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;Update 1:  links throughout, minor formatting changes, proper Creative Commons Public Domain tools, parenthetical about import path from Endnote and such, fixing a few typos.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.neh.gov/"&gt;NEH&lt;/a&gt;-funded &lt;a href="http://wiki.digitalclassicist.org/Linked_Ancient_World_Data_Institute"&gt;Linked Ancient World Data Institute&lt;/a&gt;, still in progress at &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt;, has got me thinking about a number of things. One of them is bibliography and linked data. Here's a brain dump, intended to spark conversation and collaboration.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;What We Need&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;As much bibliographic data as possible, for both primary and secondary sources (print and digital), publicly released to third parties under either a public domain declaration or an unrestrictive open license.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Stable HTTP &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_resource_identifier"&gt;URIs&lt;/a&gt; for every work and author included in those datasets.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Why&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Bibliographic and citation collection and management are integral to every research and publication in project in ancient studies. We could save each other a lot of time, and get more substantive work done in the field, if it was simpler and easier to do. We could more easily and effectively tie together disparate work published on the web (and appearing on the web through retrospective digitization) if we had a common infrastructure and shared point of reference. There's already a lot of digital data in various hands that could support such an effort, but a good chunk of it is not out where anybody with good will and talent can get at it to improve it, build tools around it, etc.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;What I Want You (and Me) To Do If You Have Bibliographic Data&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Release it to the world through a third party. No matter what format it's in, give a copy to someone else whose function is hosting free data on the web. Dump it into a public repository at &lt;a href="http://github.com/"&gt;github.com&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://sourceforge.net/"&gt;sourceforge.net&lt;/a&gt;. Put it into a shared library at &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/"&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.bibsonomy.org/"&gt;Bibsonomy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.mendeley.com/"&gt;Mendeley&lt;/a&gt;, or another bibliographic content website (most have easy upload/import paths from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EndNote"&gt;Endnote&lt;/a&gt;, and other citation management applications). Hosting a copy yourself is fine, but giving it to a third party demonstrates your bona fides, gets it out of your nifty but restrictive search engine or database, and increments your bus number.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Release it under a Creative Commons &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/about/pdm"&gt;Public Domain Mark&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/about/cc0"&gt;Public Domain Dedication (CC0)&lt;/a&gt;.  Or if you can't do that, find as open a &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/"&gt;Creative Commons&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_content#Licenses"&gt;similar license&lt;/a&gt; as you can. Don't try to control it. If there's some aspect of the data that you can't (because of rights encumberance) or don't want to (why?) give away to make the world a better place, find a quick way to extract, filter, or excerpt that aspect and get the rest out.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Alert the world to your philanthropy. Blog or tweet about it. Post a link to the data on your institutional website. Above all, alert &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/people/staff/chuck-jones"&gt;Chuck Jones&lt;/a&gt; and Phoebe Acheson so it gets announced via &lt;a href="http://ancientworldonline.blogspot.com/"&gt;Ancient World Online&lt;/a&gt; and/or &lt;a href="http://ancientbiblio.wordpress.com/"&gt;Ancient World Open Bibliographies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do the same if you have other useful data, like identifiers for modern or ancient works or authors.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get in touch with me and/or anyone else to talk about the next step: setting up stable HTTP URIs corresponding to this stuff.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;b&gt;Who I'm Talking To&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;First of all, I'm talking to myself, my collaborators, and my team-mates at ISAW. I intend to eat my own dogfood.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here are other institutions and entities I know about who have potentially useful data.&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="http://openlibrary.org/"&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt; : data about books is already out there and available, and there are ways to add more&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/"&gt;Perseus Project&lt;/a&gt; : a huge, FRBR-ized collection of MODS records for Greek and Latin authors, works, and modern editions thereof.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://chs.harvard.edu/chs"&gt;Center for Hellenic Studies&lt;/a&gt;: identifiers for Greek and Latin authors and works&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.annee-philologique.com/"&gt;L'Année Philologique&lt;/a&gt; and its institutional partners like the &lt;a href="http://www.apaclassics.org/"&gt;American Philological Association&lt;/a&gt;: the big collection of analytic secondary bibliography for classics (journal articles)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://projects.chass.utoronto.ca/amphoras/tocs.html"&gt;TOCS-IN&lt;/a&gt;: a collaboratively collected batch of analytic secondary bibliography for classics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://papyri.info/"&gt;Papyri.info&lt;/a&gt; and its contributing project partners: TEI bibliographic records for  much of the bibliography produced for or cited by Greek and Latin papyrologists (plus other ancient language/script traditions in papyrology)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gnomon-online.de/"&gt;Gnomon Bibliographische Datenbank&lt;/a&gt;: masses of bibliographic data for books and articles for classics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Any and every university library system that has a dedicated or easily extracted set of associated catalog records. Especially any with unique collections (e.g., Cincinnati) or those with databases of analytical bibliography down to the level of articles in journals and collections.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ditto any and every ancient studies digital project that has bibliographic data in a database.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Comments, Reactions, Suggestions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Welcome, encouraged, and essential. By comment here or otherwise (but not private email please!).&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>backstop</category><category>bibliography</category><category>books</category><category>boundaries</category><category>collaboration</category><category>concordia</category><category>digclass</category><category>interop</category><category>isaw</category><category>lawdi</category><category>linkeddata</category><category>openness</category><category>rights</category><category>walled gardens</category><category>zotero</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/06/ancient-studies-needs-open/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2012 19:03:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Playing with PELAGIOS: The GAWD is Live</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/02/playing-with-pelagios-gawd-is-live/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;The is the lastest in an on-going series chronicling my &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/search/label/pelagiosplay"&gt;dalliances with data published by the PELAGIOS project partners&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I think it's safe to say that, thanks to the &lt;a href="http://pelagios-project.blogspot.com/"&gt;PELAGIOS&lt;/a&gt; partner institutions, that we do have a &lt;b&gt;Graph of Ancient World Data (GAWD)&lt;/b&gt; on the web. It's still in early stages, and one has to do some downloading, unzipping, and so forth to engage with it at the moment, but indeed the long-awaited day has dawned.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here's the perspective, as of last Friday, from the vantage point of &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt;. I've used SPARQL to query the GAWD for all information resources that the partners claim (via their RDF data dumps) are related to Pleiades information resources. I.e., I'm pulling out a list of information resources about texts, pictures, objects, grouped by their relationships to what Pleiades knows about ancient places (findspot, original location, etc.). I've sorted that view of the graph by the titles Pleiades gives to its place-related information resources and generated an &lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/pelagiosexp/pleiadic.html"&gt;HTML view of the result&lt;/a&gt;. It's here for your browsing pleasure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Next Steps and Desiderata&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For various technical reasons, I'm not yet touching the data of a couple of PELAGIOS partners (&lt;a href="http://explore.clarosnet.org/XDB/ASP/clarosHome/"&gt;CLAROS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://spqr.cerch.kcl.ac.uk/"&gt;SPQR&lt;/a&gt;), but the will hopefully be resolved soon. I still need to dig into figuring out what &lt;a href="http://opencontext.org/"&gt;Open Context&lt;/a&gt; is doing on this front. Other key resources -- especially those emanating from ISAW -- are not yet ready to produce RDF (but we're working on it).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are a few things I'd like the PELAGIOS partners to consider/discuss adding to their data:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Titles/labels for the information resources (using rdfs:label?). This would make it possible for me to produce more intuitive/helpful labels for users of my HTML index. Descriptions would be cool too. As would some indication of the type of thing(s) a given resource addresses (e.g., place, statue, inscription, text)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Categorization of the relationships between their information resources and Pleaides information resources. Perhaps some variation of the &lt;a href="http://gawd.atlantides.org/terms/"&gt;terms originally explored by Concordia&lt;/a&gt; (whence the GAWD moniker), as someone on the PELAGIOS list has already suggested.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;What would you like to see added to the GAWD? What would you do with it?&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>concordia</category><category>gawd</category><category>lawdi</category><category>linkeddata</category><category>LOD</category><category>nomisma</category><category>pelagios</category><category>pelagiosplay</category><category>pleiades</category><category>rdf</category><category>sparql</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/02/playing-with-pelagios-gawd-is-live/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 22:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A new Concordia term: "where" (needed for linking papyri to Pleiades resources)</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2010/01/new-concordia-term-needed-for-linking/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;In discussions this week with &lt;a href="http://sgillies.net/me"&gt;Sean&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://philomousos.blogspot.com/"&gt;Hugh&lt;/a&gt;, we explored what would be minimally necessary for web feeds describing the papyrological documents now being surfaced via &lt;a href="http://papyri.info"&gt;http://papyri.info&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the long term, we'd like to link not only to descriptive resources (at &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt; or elsewhere) for their modern places of finding but also any ancient places attested in the texts themselves (having done named-entity analysis on all 50,000+ documents, the first steps in which are now underway by &lt;a href="http://www.kuleuven.be/cv/u0009750e.htm"&gt;Mark Depauw&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://www.trismegistos.org/"&gt;Trismegistos&lt;/a&gt; team in Leiden).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the near term, we can express geographic linkages on the basis of the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nome_%28Egypt%29"&gt;nome&lt;/a&gt; attributions recorded for the papyri by the editors of the &lt;a style="font-style: italic;" xml:lang="de" title="Heidelberg Register of Greek Papyri from Egypt" href="http://www.rzuser.uni-heidelberg.de/%7Egv0/"&gt;Heidelberger Gesamtverzeichnis der griechischen Papyrusurkunden Ägyptens&lt;/a&gt; whose records are incorporated into the papyri.info contents.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But none of the terms we had previously defined in our &lt;a href="http://atlantides.org/trac/concordia/wiki/ConcordiaThesaurus"&gt;Concordia link-type thesaurus&lt;/a&gt; precisely fit this information. We did have several geographic terms (findSpot, origin, observedAt and attestsTo), but we needed to add a more generic one: "where". The nomes as indicated by HGV are geographical classifications, based on the ancient regions, made primarily for facilitating reference and review by modern scholars. They don't necessarily constitute "find spot" or "place of origin" in every case.  This "where" term idea followed naturally from &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/p/where-link-relation-type/"&gt;Sean's earlier efforts&lt;/a&gt; to advocate for a "where" link relation type. A link in a feed entry using this term will simply indicate that the described resource should be treated as being located, in a general way, at the place described by the linked resource.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Hopefully, this term will be useful not only for papyri.info, but also for other pre-existing datasets where the location information recorded about ancient artifacts is similarly less precise than the born-digital epigraphic corpora that guided the minting of our initial thesaurus terms. Hopefully it will also prove useful in &lt;a href="http://mediterraneanceramics.blogspot.com/2010/01/rdfa-patterns-for-ancient-world.html"&gt;contexts&lt;/a&gt; such as those that &lt;a href="http://sebastianheath.com/"&gt;Sebastian&lt;/a&gt; has recently been blogging about.&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>concordia</category><category>epigraphy</category><category>feeds</category><category>gawd</category><category>papyrology</category><category>pleiades</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2010/01/new-concordia-term-needed-for-linking/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2010 05:46:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Interoperation with Pleiades</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/12/interoperation-with-pleiades/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I've had a few questions lately about how other web-based publications could be designed to support interoperation with &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt;. Here's my working advice:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Any project that wants to lay the groundwork for geographic interoperability on the basis of Pleiades should:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;1. Capture and manage Pleiades identifiers (stable URLs like &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/638753/"&gt;http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/638753/&lt;/a&gt;) for each place one might want to cite.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;2. Request membership in the Pleiades community and add/modify content therein as necessary in order to create new resources (and new URLs) for places that Pleiades doesn't yet document, but which are provably historical and relevant to content controlled by the external project.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;3. Capture and manage stable URLs from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.geonames.org/"&gt;GeoNames&lt;/a&gt; that correspond to modern geographic entities that are relevant to the content controlled by the external project. Don't conflate modern and ancient locations, as this will eventually lead to heartbreak.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;4. Emit paged web feeds in the &lt;a href="http://atompub.org/rfc4287.html"&gt;Atom Syndication Format (RFC 4287)&lt;/a&gt; that also conform to the guidance documented (with in-the-wild, third-party examples) at:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/trac/concordia/wiki/ConcordiaAtomFeeds"&gt;http://www.atlantides.org/trac/concordia/wiki/ConcordiaAtomFeeds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;and make use of the terms defined at&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/trac/concordia/wiki/ConcordiaThesaurus"&gt;http://www.atlantides.org/trac/concordia/wiki/ConcordiaThesaurus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;to indicate publicly relationships such as "findspot" and "original location" between the content controlled by the external project, Pleiades resources, Wikipedia resources, GeoNames resources and resources published by other third parties.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;5. Alert us so we can include the entry-point URL for the feeds in the seeded search horizon list for the web crawler and search index service we are developing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You can see how the &lt;a href="http://www.uni-heidelberg.de/institute/sonst/adw/edh/index.html"&gt;Epigraphic Databank Heidelberg&lt;/a&gt; team has been thinking about how to accomplish this at:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/trac/concordia/wiki/PleiadesMoI"&gt;http://www.atlantides.org/trac/concordia/wiki/PleiadesMoI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;and&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/trac/concordia/wiki/EDHgeographyTable"&gt;http://www.atlantides.org/trac/concordia/wiki/EDHgeographyTable&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ancgeo</category><category>collaboration</category><category>concordia</category><category>feeds</category><category>interop</category><category>pleiades</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/12/interoperation-with-pleiades/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2009 22:01:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Determining BAtlas IDs for future Pleiades interoperation</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/06/determining-batlas-ids-for-future/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;For those who are working with datasets they'd like eventually to link up with &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt;, we created the &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2008/07/barrington-atlas-ids.html"&gt;Barrington Atlas ID scheme&lt;/a&gt;. I've just posted some more tools for helping you determine the BAtlas IDs to go with your existing geographic names or other information.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's now a draft "&lt;a href="http://atlantides.org/batlas/ba-index-with-ids.pdf"&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Barrington Atlas&lt;/span&gt; Index with Identifiers&lt;/a&gt;". In PDF (watch out: 7.2 MB) it looks like:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/Si6XsrMT6FI/AAAAAAAAABw/a7pV23zz6p4/s1600-h/pdfeg.jpg"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 400px; height: 201px;" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/Si6XsrMT6FI/AAAAAAAAABw/a7pV23zz6p4/s400/pdfeg.jpg" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5345376601499756626" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's also available in a 1.0 MB &lt;a href="http://atlantides.org/batlas/ba-index-with-ids.html.zip"&gt;zip-compressed HTML version&lt;/a&gt;, with somewhat semantic class attributes on spans that could be used to parse out different themes ahead of an attempt to match it to a names list:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/Si6YT8_ZYZI/AAAAAAAAAB4/EKjmvrpNnBw/s1600-h/htmleg.jpg"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 400px; height: 190px;" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/Si6YT8_ZYZI/AAAAAAAAAB4/EKjmvrpNnBw/s400/htmleg.jpg" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5345377276292325778" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;And of course there is already the home-brewed XML format we distributed the original IDs in (&lt;a href="http://atlantides.org/batlas/2008-09-04/baids-2008-09-04.tgz"&gt;last release tar-gzipped archive&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/Si6Y98xRHDI/AAAAAAAAACA/PH83IPv_KaU/s1600-h/xmleg.jpg"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 400px; height: 386px;" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/Si6Y98xRHDI/AAAAAAAAACA/PH83IPv_KaU/s400/xmleg.jpg" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5345377997787569202" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Share and enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>batlas</category><category>batlasids</category><category>concordia</category><category>gawd</category><category>interop</category><category>pleiades</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/06/determining-batlas-ids-for-future/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2009 22:55:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Concordia Graph</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/concordia-graph/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2009/01/semantic-web-scholarly-resources-for.html"&gt;yesterday's post&lt;/a&gt;, I should also have linked directly to the working copy of the &lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/trac/concordia/wiki/ConcordiaGraph"&gt;Concordia Graph &lt;/a&gt;... persons, places, names, objects and some basic, history-oriented relationships between them ... a subset of what hopefully &lt;a href="http://groups.google.com/group/gawd"&gt;GAWD&lt;/a&gt; will eventually address (as non-idiosyncratically as possible).&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>concordia</category><category>interop</category><category>pleiades</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/concordia-graph/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2009 21:57:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Semantic Web, Scholarly Resources for Antiquity and the Museum</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/semantic-web-scholarly-resources-for/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Our on-going work on geographically functional, cross-resource, machine-actionable citation(!) with the Web continues to get more interesting.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The kickoff was, of course, the joint NEH/JISC grant that is (under the rubric of the &lt;a href="http://concordia.atlantides.org/"&gt;Concordia&lt;/a&gt; project) funding our look at this in collaboration with the &lt;a href="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/schools/humanities/depts/cch"&gt;Centre for Computing in the Humanities&lt;/a&gt; at King's College, London. Our two workshops (and lots of discussion with other parties in between) have led us through &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2007/09/feeds-for-pleiades-data.html"&gt;KML&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2008/02/atomgeorss-for-interoperability.html"&gt;Atom+GeoRSS&lt;/a&gt;, citation vocabularies and &lt;a href="http://groups.google.com/groups/profile?show=more&amp;amp;enc_user=3woajxYAAADz2Iah2CYKpGhWfIfANf6qo4cocwWvDVg2RHsu8f1bCg&amp;amp;group=oai-ore"&gt;OAI/ORE&lt;/a&gt; on to &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/search/label/batlasids"&gt;Cool URIs&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://sgillies.net/blog/785/linking-open-geographic-data/"&gt;Linked Data&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://sgillies.net/blog/849/why-not-cidoc-crm-at-this-time/"&gt;CIDOC CRM&lt;/a&gt; and more.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Traffic is now building on the &lt;a href="http://groups.google.com/group/gawd"&gt;Graph of Ancient World Data discussion group&lt;/a&gt; (e.g., &lt;a href="http://groups.google.com/group/gawd/browse_thread/thread/226f0e5f6fb64237"&gt;Sebastian Heath's post on coin hoard data&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href="http://nomisma.org/"&gt;nomisma.org&lt;/a&gt;). Yesterday, &lt;a href="http://sgillies.net/me"&gt;Sean Gillies&lt;/a&gt; rolled out &lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/trac/pleiades/changeset/1445"&gt;some changes to the Pleiades interface&lt;/a&gt; that provide &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/cooluris/#hashuri"&gt;#this endpoints&lt;/a&gt; for Pleiades places, so that Sebastian and others can make explicit reference either to the historical places themselves (non-information resources cited like &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/639166#this"&gt;http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/639166#this&lt;/a&gt;) or our descriptions of them on the web (information resources, cited like &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/639166/"&gt;http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/639166/&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And then this afternoon I came across the latest Talis Semantic Web podcast, featuring &lt;a href="http://blogs.talis.com/nodalities/2009/01/koven-smith-talks-about-the-semantic-web-and-museums.php"&gt;Koven Smith on Semantic Web initiatives at the Metropolitan Museum of Art&lt;/a&gt;. 38 minutes well-spent. They're thinking about and exploring a number of the approaches and technologies we're interested in, but from a museum perspective. It would be interesting to discuss how these methods could be used to better bridge gaps between museums, field archaeologists, epigraphers, numismatists, papyrologists, prosopographers, historical geographers, librarians, archivists and the rest!&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ancgeo</category><category>batlasids</category><category>concordia</category><category>epigraphy</category><category>interop</category><category>papyrology</category><category>patterns</category><category>pleiades</category><category>prosopography</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/semantic-web-scholarly-resources-for/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2009 01:08:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Digital Projects (ISAW Newsletter January 2008)</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/digital-projects-isaw-newsletter/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Since the &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2009/01/isaw-newsletter-january-2008.html"&gt;ISAW Newsletter&lt;/a&gt; is only available online as a monolithic PDF, I thought I'd make the text of my contribution (about our "digital programs") available here in HTML form:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;ISAW’s digital programs are fundamental to the Institute’s mission. Convinced that the transformation of the media and information landscape now underway offers scholars unparalleled opportunities to make new discoveries, collaborate with distant colleagues, engage public interests, and tackle previously intractable problems, we have committed ourselves to an ambitious slate of digital initiatives that extend far beyond the walls of the Institute. As the examples below illustrate, we emphasize the creation and delivery of core resources such as primary and secondary texts and images, as well as geographic and archaeological reference information. We seek to serve the entire field of ancient studies by working for the durability of digital publications–and the sustainability of the projects that create and maintain them–through promotion of standards, creation of reusable free software, use of open-access licenses, and decentralization of authorial, editorial, and peer-review activities.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In early 2008, ISAW became a partner in the &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;Pleiades Project&lt;/a&gt;. Together with the &lt;a href="http://www.unc.edu/awmc/"&gt;Ancient World Mapping Center&lt;/a&gt; (AWMC), we are digitizing the most comprehensive register of geographical data for the ancient Greek and Roman world, collected by the &lt;a href="http://www.apaclassics.org/"&gt;American Philological Association&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href="http://www.unc.edu/depts/cl_atlas/"&gt;Classical Atlas Project&lt;/a&gt; to support the preparation of the &lt;a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/43970336"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Barrington Atlas of the Greek and Roman World&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (R. Talbert, ed., Princeton 2000). All of the coordinates, historical names, and other information in this rich collection are being placed online so scholars, students, and enthusiasts worldwide can browse, search, and map it, as well as offer suggestions for updates and additions. The Pleiades effort has recently expanded with funding from a Transatlantic Digitization Grant, awarded to ISAW and King’s College London, by the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) and the U.K. Joint Information Systems Committee. It supports the prototyping of mechanisms to tie Pleiades into important digital collections of epigraphic and papyrological texts from Egypt and coastal North Africa (see further: the &lt;a href="http://concordia.atlantides.org/"&gt;Concordia Project&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://groups.google.com/group/gawd"&gt;Graph of Ancient World Data&lt;/a&gt; group). This effort will lay the foundation for extensive, automated cross-linking between Pleiades and other web-based scholarly resources for the entire Greek and Roman world. We are currently seeking funding for a second, two-year development period for Pleiades/Concordia that will accelerate the digitization of content and bring users together for a series of workshops to identify needed improvements to the system and to facilitate more effective collaboration.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Over the past year ISAW has also assumed a leadership role in a group of interrelated digital papyrology projects (see &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/"&gt;http://idp.atlantides.org&lt;/a&gt;). One of these, funded by a grant to Duke University from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, has successfully upgraded and effectively integrated two of the key digital resources for study of ancient documents on papyrus: the &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/trac/idp/wiki/DDBDP"&gt;Duke Databank of Documentary Papyri&lt;/a&gt; (DDbDP) and the &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/trac/idp/wiki/HGV"&gt;Heidelberger Gesamtverzeichnis der griechischen Papyrusurkunden Ägyptens&lt;/a&gt; (HGV). Both resources will soon be provided to users via a search and display environment prototyped by the digital libraries team at Columbia University. This system, dubbed the &lt;a href="http://papyri.info/"&gt;Papyrological Navigator&lt;/a&gt;, combines DDbDP and HGV content with images and database records drawn from the 22 museum and university papyrus collections that constitute the &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/trac/idp/wiki/APIS"&gt;Advanced Papyrological Information System&lt;/a&gt; (APIS). It also links them to the extensive &lt;a href="http://www.trismegistos.org/"&gt;Trismegistos&lt;/a&gt; databases in Leuven. Under new funding provided to APIS by the NEH, work on this interface will move to the Digital Libraries team at NYU where, with collaboration from ISAW and APIS team members at Columbia, it will see extensive improvements. ISAW is currently working with partners to secure funding for a second major upgrade to the DDbDP and HGV: a collaborative, online editing environment that will speed the addition and revision of content by granting papyrologists worldwide direct authorial capabilities under a distributed system of editorial oversight.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A number of other exciting projects are in work for 2009 and beyond. We hope to expand the utility of Pleiades by linking it to a number of other systems and digital gazetteers under development at a variety of institutions around the world. Plans are being formulated for a collaborative digital encyclopedia of Coptic archaeology, an extensive database of digital images, an online calendar of museum exhibitions, a major book and journal digitization program, and a multi-institutional publication series comprising open-access primary texts and research data.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>batlas</category><category>concordia</category><category>gawd</category><category>isaw</category><category>papyrology</category><category>pleiades</category><category>rights</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/digital-projects-isaw-newsletter/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2009 21:33:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>BAtlas IDs: first full release (all maps)</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/batlas-ids-first-full-release-all-maps/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Grab the whole thing here:&lt;a href="http://atlantides.org/batlas/2008-09-04/baids-2008-09-04.tgz"&gt; http://atlantides.org/batlas/2008-09-04/baids-2008-09-04.tgz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Let me know what problems you find.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;README file for Barrington Atlas Identifiers, version published 2008-09-04&lt;br&gt;This is the first complete release.&lt;br&gt;Reference URL: &lt;a href="http://atlantides.org/batlas"&gt;http://atlantides.org/batlas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Background: &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/search/label/batlasids"&gt;http://horothesia.blogspot.com/search/label/batlasids&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;New maps covered in this release: 100, 101, 102&lt;br&gt;List of all maps presently covered: 1-102 (complete)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Major classes of change from prior versions are listed below. Consult individual files named like map22-diff.txt for output files differencing from prior version to this version.&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;No changes to previously released IDs.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>batlasids</category><category>concordia</category><category>pleiades</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/batlas-ids-first-full-release-all-maps/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2008 23:39:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>