<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about gawd)</title><link>http://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://paregorios.org/categories/gawd.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:paregorios@hotmail.com"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 23:11:11 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Playing with PELAGIOS: Open Context and Labels</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/02/playing-with-pelagios-open-context-and/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;Latest in the &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/search/label/pelagiosplay"&gt;Playing with PELAGIOS series&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I've just modified the tooling and re-run the &lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/pelagiosexp/pleiadic.html"&gt;Pleiades-oriented-view-of-the-GAWD report&lt;/a&gt; to include the &lt;a href="http://opencontext.org/export/pelagios"&gt;RDF triples just published by Open Context&lt;/a&gt; and to exploit, when available, &lt;span style="color: blue; font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;rdfs:label&lt;/span&gt; on the annotation target in order to produce more human-readable links in the HTML output. This required the addition of an &lt;span style="color: blue; font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;OPTIONAL&lt;/span&gt; clause to the SPARQL query, as well as modifications to the results-processing XSLT. The new versions are indicated/linked on the report page.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You can see the results of these changes, for example, in the &lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/pelagiosexp/antiochia-theoupolis-658381.html"&gt;Antiochia/Theoupolis page&lt;/a&gt;.</description><category>gawd</category><category>horothesia</category><category>lawdi</category><category>linkeddata</category><category>LOD</category><category>opencontext</category><category>pelagios</category><category>pelagiosplay</category><category>sparql</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/02/playing-with-pelagios-open-context-and/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2012 21:06:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Playing with PELAGIOS: The GAWD is Live</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/02/playing-with-pelagios-gawd-is-live/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;The is the lastest in an on-going series chronicling my &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/search/label/pelagiosplay"&gt;dalliances with data published by the PELAGIOS project partners&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I think it's safe to say that, thanks to the &lt;a href="http://pelagios-project.blogspot.com/"&gt;PELAGIOS&lt;/a&gt; partner institutions, that we do have a &lt;b&gt;Graph of Ancient World Data (GAWD)&lt;/b&gt; on the web. It's still in early stages, and one has to do some downloading, unzipping, and so forth to engage with it at the moment, but indeed the long-awaited day has dawned.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here's the perspective, as of last Friday, from the vantage point of &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt;. I've used SPARQL to query the GAWD for all information resources that the partners claim (via their RDF data dumps) are related to Pleiades information resources. I.e., I'm pulling out a list of information resources about texts, pictures, objects, grouped by their relationships to what Pleiades knows about ancient places (findspot, original location, etc.). I've sorted that view of the graph by the titles Pleiades gives to its place-related information resources and generated an &lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/pelagiosexp/pleiadic.html"&gt;HTML view of the result&lt;/a&gt;. It's here for your browsing pleasure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Next Steps and Desiderata&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For various technical reasons, I'm not yet touching the data of a couple of PELAGIOS partners (&lt;a href="http://explore.clarosnet.org/XDB/ASP/clarosHome/"&gt;CLAROS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://spqr.cerch.kcl.ac.uk/"&gt;SPQR&lt;/a&gt;), but the will hopefully be resolved soon. I still need to dig into figuring out what &lt;a href="http://opencontext.org/"&gt;Open Context&lt;/a&gt; is doing on this front. Other key resources -- especially those emanating from ISAW -- are not yet ready to produce RDF (but we're working on it).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are a few things I'd like the PELAGIOS partners to consider/discuss adding to their data:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Titles/labels for the information resources (using rdfs:label?). This would make it possible for me to produce more intuitive/helpful labels for users of my HTML index. Descriptions would be cool too. As would some indication of the type of thing(s) a given resource addresses (e.g., place, statue, inscription, text)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Categorization of the relationships between their information resources and Pleaides information resources. Perhaps some variation of the &lt;a href="http://gawd.atlantides.org/terms/"&gt;terms originally explored by Concordia&lt;/a&gt; (whence the GAWD moniker), as someone on the PELAGIOS list has already suggested.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;What would you like to see added to the GAWD? What would you do with it?&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>concordia</category><category>gawd</category><category>horothesia</category><category>lawdi</category><category>linkeddata</category><category>LOD</category><category>nomisma</category><category>pelagios</category><category>pelagiosplay</category><category>pleiades</category><category>rdf</category><category>sparql</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/02/playing-with-pelagios-gawd-is-live/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 22:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Pleiades, Flickr, and the Ancient World Image Bank</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2011/12/pleiades-flickr-and-ancient-world-image/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Many of you are already aware that &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://flickr.com/"&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/awib/"&gt;Ancient World Image Bank&lt;/a&gt; have joined forces to link together online, open-access imagery and ancient geographical information. This blog post is intended to answer some lingering questions that users and potential contributors have been asking about the process.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Other Blog Posts&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/about/news/geography-and-imagery"&gt;A general notice of the development on the ISAW News Blog&lt;/a&gt; (by me)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/Members/sgillies/news-items/eye-on-the-sidebar-related-photos-from-flickr"&gt;An extended discussion of the effects, from the Pleiades perspective&lt;/a&gt; (by Sean Gillies)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://code.flickr.com/blog/2011/12/16/pleiades-a-guest-post/"&gt;An extended discussion with developers' how-to on the Flickr Code Blog&lt;/a&gt; (by Sean Gillies), &lt;a href="http://sgillies.net/blog/1103/flickr-support-for-ancient-world-places"&gt;mirrored on Sean's blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2011/09/feeds-of-flickr-photos-depicting.html"&gt;The blog post here at Horothesia that started it all&lt;/a&gt; (by me)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;How to Construct a Pleiades Machine Tag&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;In Flickr, you add the machine tag the same way you add regular tags when editing an individual image or a set or group in the organizer.   The machine tag should use the following syntax:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;pleiades:TERM=#####&lt;/blockquote&gt;where "TERM" is one of the recognized terms (&lt;a href="http://gawd.atlantides.org/terms/"&gt;originally from the Concordia Thesaurus, aka the Graph of Ancient World Data, or GAWD, terms&lt;/a&gt;) listed below and "#####" is the numeric identifier of the Pleiades place you wish to associate with the photo.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You can get the identifier by visiting pleiades.stoa.org then searching for and finding the place. Copy the numeric portion of the URL of the place page and paste it into your tag.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, for example, if I wanted to tag a photo that "depicts" ancient Athens (or a portion thereof), I'd visit Pleiades and search for Athens. I'd find this place page: &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/579885/"&gt;http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/579885/&lt;/a&gt;. So, I'd grab 579885 and construct the following machine tag for use in Flickr:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;pleiades:depicts=579885&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;Recognized Terms in Pleiades Machine Tags&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;TERMS for use in Pleiades machine tags should begin with a lowercase letter. The following TERMS are recognized in Pleiades machine tags:&lt;br&gt;&lt;dl&gt;&lt;dt&gt;depicts&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;the photo so tagged can be said to "depict" the referenced ancient place or a significant or exemplary portion thereof&lt;br&gt;(this term is equivalent to CIDOC CRM p62 "depicts")&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;findspot&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;the photo so tagged shows an object that was first found in modern times at the referenced ancient place&lt;br&gt;(this term is particularly useful for items now in museums or elsewhere, especially those no longer at the initial place of finding)&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;origin&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;the photo so tagged shows an object that is believed, with reasonably high certainty, to have been originally located or produced at the referenced ancient place&lt;br&gt;(this can differ from the findspot, as when an inscription or other object was moved in antiquity)&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;observedAt&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;the photo so tagged shows an object that was observed in modern times at the referenced ancient place&lt;br&gt;(the implication being that the place observed is neither the modern findspot nor the presumed original location; I suspect this term will rarely need to be used to link photos with Pleiades place resources)&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;where&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;the photo so tagged is related in some way to the referenced ancient place, but for some unspecified reason no more specific relationship can be asserted&lt;br&gt;(this term should not be used unless none of above terms are deemed to be appropriate)&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;place&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;this term is DEPRECATED; it was originally used in exploring the Pleiades machine tag idea (and is highlighted in my previous blog post). Its semantics are assumed to be equivalent to "where". If at all possible, photos carrying this tag should be updated to use one of the more specific terms above.&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;br&gt;Please note that pleiades:place&lt;span style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;=##### (i.e., with a plural) is not a recognized machine tag. Its behavior in Flickr or Pleiades is undefined. So is the behavior of any Pleiades machine tag with a misspelling or a term not included in the list above. ("finspot" seems to be a popular typo at present).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Any photo tagged with the proper Pleiades machine tag syntax and one of the terms above will be noticed by Pleiades and picked up in the summary counts and links on individual place resource pages. In order for a photo to be considered for the &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/groups/pleiades-places/"&gt;Pleiades Places group on Flickr&lt;/a&gt; (and therefore as a "portrait image" for a Pleiades place), the photo must be tagged with a pleiades:depicts tag.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;How do I Add Pleiades Machine Tags Quickly?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It would be unreasonable of us to ask a prolific photographer with an extensive, well-tagged collection already on Flickr to go through an individually add appropriate machine tags by hand. Fortunately, Flickr provides a mechanism for easy batch editing of tags.&lt;br&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Suppose that you have tagged a large number of your photos with the name of the ancient site (e.g., Halicarnassus)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Visit the following link: &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/me/alltags/"&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/me/alltags/&lt;/a&gt;; it will give you an alphabetical list of all your tags.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Find the name of the site and click on the corresponding link. You'll see all the photos thus tagged in your photostream.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Find and click on the "Change this tag" link (Really. Skip "Edit these in a batch" link for now).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Insert the cursor after your existing tag string, type a space, then type or paste in the desired Pleiades machine tag (read the fine print on that page for an extended explanation of what's going on).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Click the "save" button. Flickr will go off and add the new tag to all those images at once.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;If you'd rather be more selective about which photos you want to add a tag to, you can choose the "Edit these in a batch" link I told you to skip above, then paste the Pleiades machine tag into the tag lists associated with only those images you wish to update.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Why Can't We Just Use Geotagging That's Already in the Photos?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Some photographers have geotagged their photos, either using a GPS-enabled digital camera or some method of post-processing. I was recently asked on twitter why we're putting people to all the trouble above when we could just use the geotagging? There are several reasons:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Not everybody's photos are machine-tagged.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Many ancient sites are coincident with urban areas (or areas of natural beauty or places where someone took a picture of their dog) and so mere proximity to an ancient site can't be interpreted as indicating a given photo is relevant to a nearby Pleiades place.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Horizontal precision and accuracy can vary widely in geotagged photos as a function of the geotagging method used and the interests and skill of the person doing the geotagging. As a result, a photo might be geotagged at a location closer to another, unrelated pleiades place.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The horizontal precision and accuracy of Pleiades coordinates also varies widely given the varying sources from which it derives and the subsequent coordinate extraction methods. This makes the process of proximity correlation even more fraught.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;This is not to say that we're not interested in exploring uses for geotagged photos in Flickr (or supporting a geotag-your-photo-using-Pleiades-coordinates tool), but I hope this discussion helps explain why we like the machine-tag approach for indicating relevance.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Please let me know, via comments here, if you have additional questions or suggestions. &lt;/div&gt;</description><category>awib</category><category>flickr</category><category>gawd</category><category>horothesia</category><category>images</category><category>machine tags</category><category>pleiades</category><category>pleiades:depicts=579885</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2011/12/pleiades-flickr-and-ancient-world-image/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2011 21:42:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A new Concordia term: "where" (needed for linking papyri to Pleiades resources)</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2010/01/new-concordia-term-needed-for-linking/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;In discussions this week with &lt;a href="http://sgillies.net/me"&gt;Sean&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://philomousos.blogspot.com/"&gt;Hugh&lt;/a&gt;, we explored what would be minimally necessary for web feeds describing the papyrological documents now being surfaced via &lt;a href="http://papyri.info"&gt;http://papyri.info&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the long term, we'd like to link not only to descriptive resources (at &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt; or elsewhere) for their modern places of finding but also any ancient places attested in the texts themselves (having done named-entity analysis on all 50,000+ documents, the first steps in which are now underway by &lt;a href="http://www.kuleuven.be/cv/u0009750e.htm"&gt;Mark Depauw&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://www.trismegistos.org/"&gt;Trismegistos&lt;/a&gt; team in Leiden).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the near term, we can express geographic linkages on the basis of the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nome_%28Egypt%29"&gt;nome&lt;/a&gt; attributions recorded for the papyri by the editors of the &lt;a style="font-style: italic;" xml:lang="de" title="Heidelberg Register of Greek Papyri from Egypt" href="http://www.rzuser.uni-heidelberg.de/%7Egv0/"&gt;Heidelberger Gesamtverzeichnis der griechischen Papyrusurkunden Ägyptens&lt;/a&gt; whose records are incorporated into the papyri.info contents.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But none of the terms we had previously defined in our &lt;a href="http://atlantides.org/trac/concordia/wiki/ConcordiaThesaurus"&gt;Concordia link-type thesaurus&lt;/a&gt; precisely fit this information. We did have several geographic terms (findSpot, origin, observedAt and attestsTo), but we needed to add a more generic one: "where". The nomes as indicated by HGV are geographical classifications, based on the ancient regions, made primarily for facilitating reference and review by modern scholars. They don't necessarily constitute "find spot" or "place of origin" in every case.  This "where" term idea followed naturally from &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/p/where-link-relation-type/"&gt;Sean's earlier efforts&lt;/a&gt; to advocate for a "where" link relation type. A link in a feed entry using this term will simply indicate that the described resource should be treated as being located, in a general way, at the place described by the linked resource.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Hopefully, this term will be useful not only for papyri.info, but also for other pre-existing datasets where the location information recorded about ancient artifacts is similarly less precise than the born-digital epigraphic corpora that guided the minting of our initial thesaurus terms. Hopefully it will also prove useful in &lt;a href="http://mediterraneanceramics.blogspot.com/2010/01/rdfa-patterns-for-ancient-world.html"&gt;contexts&lt;/a&gt; such as those that &lt;a href="http://sebastianheath.com/"&gt;Sebastian&lt;/a&gt; has recently been blogging about.&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>concordia</category><category>epigraphy</category><category>feeds</category><category>gawd</category><category>horothesia</category><category>papyrology</category><category>pleiades</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2010/01/new-concordia-term-needed-for-linking/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2010 05:46:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Determining BAtlas IDs for future Pleiades interoperation</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/06/determining-batlas-ids-for-future/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;For those who are working with datasets they'd like eventually to link up with &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt;, we created the &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2008/07/barrington-atlas-ids.html"&gt;Barrington Atlas ID scheme&lt;/a&gt;. I've just posted some more tools for helping you determine the BAtlas IDs to go with your existing geographic names or other information.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's now a draft "&lt;a href="http://atlantides.org/batlas/ba-index-with-ids.pdf"&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Barrington Atlas&lt;/span&gt; Index with Identifiers&lt;/a&gt;". In PDF (watch out: 7.2 MB) it looks like:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/Si6XsrMT6FI/AAAAAAAAABw/a7pV23zz6p4/s1600-h/pdfeg.jpg"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 400px; height: 201px;" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/Si6XsrMT6FI/AAAAAAAAABw/a7pV23zz6p4/s400/pdfeg.jpg" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5345376601499756626" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's also available in a 1.0 MB &lt;a href="http://atlantides.org/batlas/ba-index-with-ids.html.zip"&gt;zip-compressed HTML version&lt;/a&gt;, with somewhat semantic class attributes on spans that could be used to parse out different themes ahead of an attempt to match it to a names list:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/Si6YT8_ZYZI/AAAAAAAAAB4/EKjmvrpNnBw/s1600-h/htmleg.jpg"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 400px; height: 190px;" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/Si6YT8_ZYZI/AAAAAAAAAB4/EKjmvrpNnBw/s400/htmleg.jpg" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5345377276292325778" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;And of course there is already the home-brewed XML format we distributed the original IDs in (&lt;a href="http://atlantides.org/batlas/2008-09-04/baids-2008-09-04.tgz"&gt;last release tar-gzipped archive&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/Si6Y98xRHDI/AAAAAAAAACA/PH83IPv_KaU/s1600-h/xmleg.jpg"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 400px; height: 386px;" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/Si6Y98xRHDI/AAAAAAAAACA/PH83IPv_KaU/s400/xmleg.jpg" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5345377997787569202" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Share and enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>batlas</category><category>batlasids</category><category>concordia</category><category>gawd</category><category>horothesia</category><category>interop</category><category>pleiades</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/06/determining-batlas-ids-for-future/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2009 22:55:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Digital Projects (ISAW Newsletter January 2008)</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/digital-projects-isaw-newsletter/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Since the &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2009/01/isaw-newsletter-january-2008.html"&gt;ISAW Newsletter&lt;/a&gt; is only available online as a monolithic PDF, I thought I'd make the text of my contribution (about our "digital programs") available here in HTML form:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;ISAW’s digital programs are fundamental to the Institute’s mission. Convinced that the transformation of the media and information landscape now underway offers scholars unparalleled opportunities to make new discoveries, collaborate with distant colleagues, engage public interests, and tackle previously intractable problems, we have committed ourselves to an ambitious slate of digital initiatives that extend far beyond the walls of the Institute. As the examples below illustrate, we emphasize the creation and delivery of core resources such as primary and secondary texts and images, as well as geographic and archaeological reference information. We seek to serve the entire field of ancient studies by working for the durability of digital publications–and the sustainability of the projects that create and maintain them–through promotion of standards, creation of reusable free software, use of open-access licenses, and decentralization of authorial, editorial, and peer-review activities.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In early 2008, ISAW became a partner in the &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;Pleiades Project&lt;/a&gt;. Together with the &lt;a href="http://www.unc.edu/awmc/"&gt;Ancient World Mapping Center&lt;/a&gt; (AWMC), we are digitizing the most comprehensive register of geographical data for the ancient Greek and Roman world, collected by the &lt;a href="http://www.apaclassics.org/"&gt;American Philological Association&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href="http://www.unc.edu/depts/cl_atlas/"&gt;Classical Atlas Project&lt;/a&gt; to support the preparation of the &lt;a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/43970336"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Barrington Atlas of the Greek and Roman World&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (R. Talbert, ed., Princeton 2000). All of the coordinates, historical names, and other information in this rich collection are being placed online so scholars, students, and enthusiasts worldwide can browse, search, and map it, as well as offer suggestions for updates and additions. The Pleiades effort has recently expanded with funding from a Transatlantic Digitization Grant, awarded to ISAW and King’s College London, by the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) and the U.K. Joint Information Systems Committee. It supports the prototyping of mechanisms to tie Pleiades into important digital collections of epigraphic and papyrological texts from Egypt and coastal North Africa (see further: the &lt;a href="http://concordia.atlantides.org/"&gt;Concordia Project&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://groups.google.com/group/gawd"&gt;Graph of Ancient World Data&lt;/a&gt; group). This effort will lay the foundation for extensive, automated cross-linking between Pleiades and other web-based scholarly resources for the entire Greek and Roman world. We are currently seeking funding for a second, two-year development period for Pleiades/Concordia that will accelerate the digitization of content and bring users together for a series of workshops to identify needed improvements to the system and to facilitate more effective collaboration.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Over the past year ISAW has also assumed a leadership role in a group of interrelated digital papyrology projects (see &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/"&gt;http://idp.atlantides.org&lt;/a&gt;). One of these, funded by a grant to Duke University from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, has successfully upgraded and effectively integrated two of the key digital resources for study of ancient documents on papyrus: the &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/trac/idp/wiki/DDBDP"&gt;Duke Databank of Documentary Papyri&lt;/a&gt; (DDbDP) and the &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/trac/idp/wiki/HGV"&gt;Heidelberger Gesamtverzeichnis der griechischen Papyrusurkunden Ägyptens&lt;/a&gt; (HGV). Both resources will soon be provided to users via a search and display environment prototyped by the digital libraries team at Columbia University. This system, dubbed the &lt;a href="http://papyri.info/"&gt;Papyrological Navigator&lt;/a&gt;, combines DDbDP and HGV content with images and database records drawn from the 22 museum and university papyrus collections that constitute the &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/trac/idp/wiki/APIS"&gt;Advanced Papyrological Information System&lt;/a&gt; (APIS). It also links them to the extensive &lt;a href="http://www.trismegistos.org/"&gt;Trismegistos&lt;/a&gt; databases in Leuven. Under new funding provided to APIS by the NEH, work on this interface will move to the Digital Libraries team at NYU where, with collaboration from ISAW and APIS team members at Columbia, it will see extensive improvements. ISAW is currently working with partners to secure funding for a second major upgrade to the DDbDP and HGV: a collaborative, online editing environment that will speed the addition and revision of content by granting papyrologists worldwide direct authorial capabilities under a distributed system of editorial oversight.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A number of other exciting projects are in work for 2009 and beyond. We hope to expand the utility of Pleiades by linking it to a number of other systems and digital gazetteers under development at a variety of institutions around the world. Plans are being formulated for a collaborative digital encyclopedia of Coptic archaeology, an extensive database of digital images, an online calendar of museum exhibitions, a major book and journal digitization program, and a multi-institutional publication series comprising open-access primary texts and research data.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>batlas</category><category>concordia</category><category>gawd</category><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>papyrology</category><category>pleiades</category><category>rights</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/digital-projects-isaw-newsletter/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2009 21:33:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>