<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about hsv)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://paregorios.org/categories/hsv.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:ipse@paregorios.org"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;&lt;img
alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
property="dct:title"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;paregorios.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by
&lt;a xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" href="https://paregorios.org/me"
property="cc:attributionName" rel="cc:attributionURL"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; is
licensed under a &lt;a rel="license"
href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 May 2018 12:25:42 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>On Hidden Figures</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2017/01/on-hidden-figures/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div style='background-color: white; color: #1d2129; font-family: "San Francisco", -apple-system, system-ui, ".SFNSText-Regular", sans-serif; font-size: 14px; letter-spacing: -0.24px; margin-bottom: 6px;'&gt;This weekend I &lt;b&gt;finally&lt;/b&gt; got a chance to see &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4846340/"&gt;Hidden Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;The large theater was two-thirds full or so, mostly white (as one might expect in South &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huntsville,_Alabama"&gt;Huntsville&lt;/a&gt;), mostly women and girls (you missed out, dudes, it was great). &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style='background-color: white; color: #1d2129; font-family: "San Francisco", -apple-system, system-ui, ".SFNSText-Regular", sans-serif; font-size: 14px; letter-spacing: -0.24px; margin-bottom: 6px;'&gt;&lt;span style="letter-spacing: -0.24px;"&gt;There was a profound mix of audience laughter and silence throughout. At the end of the historical/photographic epilogue, there was a moment of silence into which a female voice clearly whispered: "That was amazing!" Then LOUD APPLAUSE. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style='background-color: white; color: #1d2129; font-family: "San Francisco", -apple-system, system-ui, ".SFNSText-Regular", sans-serif; font-size: 14px; letter-spacing: -0.24px; margin-bottom: 6px;'&gt;&lt;span style="letter-spacing: -0.24px;"&gt;That's the world I thought I was living in. I want it back. For real.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style='background-color: white; color: #1d2129; display: inline; font-family: "San Francisco", -apple-system, system-ui, ".SFNSText-Regular", sans-serif; font-size: 14px; letter-spacing: -0.24px; margin-top: 6px;'&gt;Let's go get it.&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><category>resist</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2017/01/on-hidden-figures/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 02:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Determinationes, past and present</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/05/determinationes-past-and-present/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Determinatio&lt;/span&gt; is a Latin term (Greek: ἀφορισμός or ὁροθέσια) for the written, serial description of boundaries, produced as necessary by Roman surveyors and routinely included in the verdicts of Roman (pro-)magistrates and &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;iudices&lt;/span&gt; when settling boundary disputes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here's an example, dating to the early second century CE:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Serving as proconsul of either Achaia or Macedonia, &lt;a href="http://www.forumromanum.org/literature/sentius_augurinusx.html"&gt;Q. Gellius Augurinus&lt;/a&gt; delivered the following verdict in a boundary dispute between the Thessalian communities of &lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?hl=en&amp;amp;client=firefox-a&amp;amp;q=Lamia+Greece&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;split=0&amp;amp;gl=us&amp;amp;ei=lIYeSub-C6Gstgel2cjsAw&amp;amp;ll=38.898515,22.434082&amp;amp;spn=0.718216,1.455688&amp;amp;z=10"&gt;Lamia&lt;/a&gt; and Hypata (mod. &lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=s_q&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=&amp;amp;q=Ypati+Greece&amp;amp;sll=38.825801,22.240448&amp;amp;sspn=0.359476,0.727844&amp;amp;gl=us&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;ll=38.855751,22.241135&amp;amp;spn=0.359325,0.727844&amp;amp;z=11&amp;amp;iwloc=A"&gt;Ypati&lt;/a&gt;). His ruling was subsequently inscribed, and was first recorded by modern scholars in 1855 in the Greek village of &lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=s_q&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=&amp;amp;q=Mexiates&amp;amp;sll=38.881412,22.309799&amp;amp;sspn=0.179598,0.363922&amp;amp;gl=us&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;ll=38.883198,22.313258&amp;amp;spn=0.179593,0.363922&amp;amp;z=12"&gt;Myxiates&lt;/a&gt;, where the stone had been reused in building a house.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;CIL 3.12306; ILS 5947a; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style="font-weight: bold;" href="http://books.google.com/books?id=LLRBfq0mbHcC&amp;amp;pg=PA19&amp;amp;lpg=PA19&amp;amp;dq=Myxiates&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=HDbcXKqYP-&amp;amp;sig=GhY2shnfLqmYzZL_WWe1fFDDKhI&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=-4IeSv6dMpTDtweiltnsAw&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=2#PPA19,M1"&gt;IG IX/2 p. 19 (before no. 60)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;; CIL 3.586; Henzen 1856; Smallwood 1966 447. See also: Stählin 1924, 220-222; RE s.v. Hypata.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Q(uinto) Gellio Sentio Augurino proco(n)s(ule) decreta / ex tabellis recitata kalendis Martis. Cum optimus maximusque princeps / Traianus Hadrianus Aug(ustus) scripserit mihi uti adhibitis menso/ribus de controversiis finium inter Lamienses et Hypataeos cognita causa / terminarem egoque in rem praesentem saepius et continuis diebus /&lt;/span&gt;5&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt; fuerim cognoverimque praesentibus utriusque civitatis defensoribus, / adhibito a me Iulio Victore evocato Augusti mensore, placet initium / finium esse ab eo loco in quo Siden fuisse comperi, quae est infra con/saeptum consecratum Neptuno, indeque descendentibus rigorem ser/vari usque ad fontem Dercynnam, qui est trans flumen Sperchion, it[a ut per] /&lt;/span&gt;10 &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;amphispora Lamiensium et Hypataeorum rigor at fontem Dercynn[am supra] / scriptum ducat et inde ad tumulum Pelion per decursum Sir [---] /  at monimentum Euryti quod est intra finem Lam[iensium --- ] / [---] Erycaniorum et Proherniorum [---] / [---] thraxum et Sido [---] /15 [---] const [ ------&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Translation (mine):&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Verdicts recited from the tablets when Quintus Gellius Sentius Augurinus was proconsul, on the kalends of March. Since the best and greatest princeps, Trajan Hadrian Augustus, wrote to me that, once surveyors had been consulted concerning the boundary disputes between the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Lamienses&lt;/span&gt; and the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Hypataeoi&lt;/span&gt;, and the case had been investigated, I should make a boundary demarcation; and, since, in the case at hand, I was present often and for successive days, and I investigated with the defenders of both cities being present and with Iulius Victor, evocatus of the emperor, a surveyor, being consulted by me, let it be that the start of the boundary be from that place in which I have learned Side was, which is below the enclosed area consecrated to Neptune; and thence in descending to preserve a straight line all the way to the spring (called) Dercynna, which is across the river Sperchion, so that a straight line leads through the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;amphispora&lt;/span&gt; of the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Lamienses&lt;/span&gt; and the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Hypataeoi&lt;/span&gt; to the above-mentioned spring Dercynna; and thence to the tumulus (called) Pelion along the slope (called) Sir... to the monument of Eurytos which is within the boundaries of the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Lamienses&lt;/span&gt; ...&lt;/blockquote&gt;This same genre is still in use in legal property descriptions in the United States today. I stumbled across another example this morning in the revised Huntsville downtown planning and zoning document, now awaiting approval by the city council (&lt;span class="main_text"&gt;&lt;span class="main_text"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.hsvcity.com/Planning/Art23-GenBusC3BufferZones2.pdf"&gt;ARTICLE 23 GENERAL BUSINESS C-3 DISTRICT REGULATIONS&lt;/a&gt;, pp. 9ff):&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Within Historic District Buffer Zone B, the maximum number of stories shall be four (4) stories with a maximum height of sixty (60) feet.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Historic District Buffer Zone B is defined as the property that lies within the following boundaries: Begin at the the intersection of the centerlines of Clinton Avenue and Monroe Street/Lincoln Street; then in a southerly direction along the centerline of Monroe Street/Lincoln Street to the intersection of the centerlines of Lincoln Street and Randolph Avenue; then West along the centerline of Randolph Avenue to the intersection of the centerlines of Randolph Avenue and Green Street; then South along the centerline of Green Street to the intersection of the centerlines of Green Street and Eustis Avenue; then West along the centerline of Eustis Avenue to the intersection of the centerlines of Eustis Avenue and Franklin Street; then South along Franklin Street to the intersection of the centerlines of Franklin ... [ it goes on and on, of course! ]&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;Truly, a morning of geekish glee for me ...&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Thanks to James at the &lt;a href="http://huntsvilledevelopment.blogspot.com/2009/05/planning-commission-approves-buffer.html"&gt;Huntsville Development Blog&lt;/a&gt; for posting the link.</description><category>boundaries</category><category>epigraphy</category><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><category>inscriptions</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/05/determinationes-past-and-present/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2009 18:11:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Coffee in Huntsville: Sam and Greg's</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/coffee-in-huntsville-sam-and-gregs/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I finally made good on my long-standing intention to drop in at &lt;a href="http://www.samandgregs.com/"&gt;Sam and Greg's Pizzeria/Gelateria&lt;/a&gt; on the north side of the square in downtown Huntsville today (&lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?hl=en&amp;amp;client=firefox-a&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;q=119+North+Side+Square,+Huntsville,+AL&amp;amp;fb=1&amp;amp;split=1&amp;amp;cid=0,0,10114298661214155859&amp;amp;ll=34.73142,-86.585183&amp;amp;spn=0.00947,0.022745&amp;amp;z=16&amp;amp;iwloc=A"&gt;map&lt;/a&gt;). The veggie pizza for lunch was great and so was a properly made cappuccino (using beans locally roasted around the corner at the &lt;a href="http://www.kaffeeklatsch.com/"&gt;Kaffeeklatsch&lt;/a&gt;, a Huntsville standby since 1977; &lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?hl=en&amp;amp;client=firefox-a&amp;amp;q=103+Jefferson+Street,+Huntsville,+AL&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;split=0&amp;amp;ll=34.731755,-86.586514&amp;amp;spn=0.00947,0.022745&amp;amp;z=16&amp;amp;iwloc=addr"&gt;map&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Both staff and fellow customers at Sam and Greg's were friendly, and the place is very comfortable. I anticipate spending alot more time there.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>coffee</category><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/coffee-in-huntsville-sam-and-gregs/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2009 01:26:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>When a free-on-HBO inaugural concert isn't (and then is)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/when-free-on-hbo-inaugural-concert-isnt/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Update 2:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I came home from the gym at 4:00 this afternoon and noticed the message indicator on my DVR was lit. The message: a notice that the inaugural concert would be live broadcast free on the local access channel 13 (so I missed it) and rebroadcast on the same channel at 6 this evening.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;.....&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So I called my cable provider (&lt;a href="http://www.mediacomcc.com/home.html"&gt;Mediacom&lt;/a&gt;) this morning -- the monopoly cable TV provider in much of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madison_County,_Alabama"&gt;Madison County Alabama&lt;/a&gt; outside the Huntsville city limits -- to ask if they would be allowing their customers access to the &lt;a href="http://www.hbo.com/weareone/"&gt;"free" HBO coverage of tomorrow's inaugural concert&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;After 10 minutes on hold, the representative returned to apologetically inform me that only current HBO subscribers would be able to see the concert. In other words: &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soup_Nazi"&gt;no soup for you&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Both &lt;a href="http://www.directv.com/DTVAPP/global/contentPageNR.jsp?assetId=P5370022"&gt;DirectTV &lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href="http://www.hbo.com/camp/200808DM/index.html"&gt;Dish&lt;/a&gt; (the two satellite providers that compete with Mediacom here) are trumpeting on their websites the fact that they are providing free HBO for the event (and more).  If I want to make Mediacom pay, I'll have to switch to satellite and get AT&amp;amp;T to install DSL at my house (and then live with the thinner data pipe). Right now I'm tempted, despite the costs, hassles and lower-value internet connection. Not that it would get me access to the concert in time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Aside: Yes, I know I can watch it streaming from HBO.com. I applaud HBO for providing that workaround for dealing with their less civic-minded local outlets. Of course, we might blame the inaugural committee for making this &lt;a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/01/16/AR2009011604921.html"&gt;an exclusive deal&lt;/a&gt; with HBO (but then somebody's got to pay for all this celebratory activity).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But to return to my main line of rant: what's Mediacom's excuse? Lameness? A callous decision to try to make money by requiring an upgrade to subscription to get HBO access for the event?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I call it FAIL.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Update:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;According to media reports, Mediacom will air the special free for folks in &lt;a href="http://www.desmoinesregister.com/article/20090117/LIFE/901170305/-1/archive&amp;amp;theme=INAUGURATION_NEWS"&gt;Des Moines Iowa&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.valdostadailytimes.com/local/local_story_016232845.html"&gt;Valdosta, Georgia&lt;/a&gt;. What makes them more special than Madison County Alabama?&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><category>rants</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/when-free-on-hbo-inaugural-concert-isnt/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2009 02:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Stearn's Coffee Defunct</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/stearns-coffee-defunct/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a href="http://stearnscoffee.com/"&gt;Stearns Coffee&lt;/a&gt;, which I had staked out as a personal replacement for the &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2008/12/end-of-era.html"&gt;recently shuttered Aromas&lt;/a&gt; but hadn't had a chance to visit prior to the &lt;a href="http://www.al.com/news/huntsvilletimes/local.ssf?/base/news/122821291569330.xml&amp;amp;coll=1"&gt;December 1st fire&lt;/a&gt;, is now closed for good. The owners just sent the following note to &lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/home.php?#/pages/Huntsville-AL/Stearns-Coffee/7362583473"&gt;their Facebook&lt;/a&gt; followers:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;So as many of you have probably guessed or assumed by now, Stearns Coffee will be unable to re-open. After carefully considering all of our options, we’ve found that we just can’t rebound financially from this. With that said, we are truly lucky to have so many customers and friends who have offered their love and support. We are so grateful to have had the opportunity to serve these people; you are what made our shop such a wonderful place to be. We will miss seeing your faces and allowing us to be a part of your lives.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Daniel &amp;amp; Marisa&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>coffee</category><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/stearns-coffee-defunct/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2009 21:49:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Paul Zimansky on Mashkan-shapir in Huntsville, 20 January 2009</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/paul-zimansky-on-mashkan-shapir-in/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, 20 January 2009 at 7:30 p.m. the &lt;a href="http://excavate-aia.blogspot.com/2009/01/aia-talk-january-20-city-of-grim-reaper.html"&gt;North Alabama Society of the Archaeological Institute of America will host&lt;/a&gt; a lecture by Prof. &lt;a href="http://www.archaeological.org/webinfo.php?page=10224&amp;amp;lid=77"&gt;Paul Zimanksy&lt;/a&gt; (Dept. of History, State University of New York, Stony Brook) entitled "City of the Grim Reaper: Rediscovery and Demise at Mashkan-shapir, Iraq."&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The lecture will be held in the Chan Auditorium on the campus of the University of Alabama in Huntsville (&lt;a href="http://theatre.uah.edu/MAP.htm"&gt;map, courtesy UAHuntsville Theatre&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>asaia</category><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><category>nasaia</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/paul-zimansky-on-mashkan-shapir-in/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2009 20:06:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>End of an era</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/12/end-of-era/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;After four years of business success, &lt;a href="http://www.meetataromas.com"&gt;the place I've dubbed my "coffice"&lt;/a&gt; is closing, so its owner and founder, Pete Abashian, can pursue other interests.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So the question for other regulars at Aromas is: who all is going to show up on the last day, Saturday, 20 December, to say goodbye and good luck to staff and friends?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And, gentle readers, if you've ever dreamed of owning and running a great coffee shop / cafe, &lt;a href="http://www.valleymls.com/%282qyi2l55bicilgruxko0pp45%29/propertyDetails.aspx?mls=285636&amp;amp;sitecode=JW6262"&gt;this one is for sale&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>coffee</category><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/12/end-of-era/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2008 20:40:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tom Tartaron on "Mycenean Coastal Worlds" in Huntsville, 2 October 2008</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/tom-tartaron-on-mycenean-coastal-worlds/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, 2 October, at 7:30 p.m. the &lt;a href="http://excavate-aia.blogspot.com/"&gt;North Alabama Society of the Archaeological Institute of America&lt;/a&gt; will host a lecture by &lt;a href="http://www.arthistory.upenn.edu/aamw/faculty.html#tartaron"&gt;Prof. Tom Tartaron&lt;/a&gt; (Dept. of Classics, University of Pennsylvania) entitled "Mycenean Coastal Worlds." Tartaron is co-director of the &lt;a href="http://mailer.fsu.edu/%7Edpullen/SHARP/index.html"&gt;Saronic Harbors Archaeological Research Project&lt;/a&gt;, which is studying the "first ever positively identified Mycenean harbor" and fortified port town at a site on the Saronic Gulf now called Kalamianos (&lt;a href="http://www.upenn.edu/pennnews/current/research/042408.html"&gt;Penn Current Research article&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href="http://www.museum.upenn.edu/new/news/fullrelease.php?which=321"&gt;Penn Museum News article&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The lecture will be held in the Chan Auditorium on the campus of the University of Alabama in Huntsville (&lt;a href="http://theatre.uah.edu/MAP.htm"&gt;map, courtesy UAHuntsville Theatre&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><category>nasaia</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/tom-tartaron-on-mycenean-coastal-worlds/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2008 19:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Moontown Fly-In 2008: 20-21 September</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/moontown-fly-in-2008-20-21-september/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Blake Mathis just sent an email to the &lt;a href="http://www.moontownairport.com/"&gt;Moontown Airport&lt;/a&gt; announcements list (where I as a non-piloting neighbor lurk; &lt;a href="http://bbs.keyhole.com/ubb/showthreaded.php/Cat/0/Number/1162741/page/2/vc/1"&gt;kml&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Annual Fly-In Reminder, This Saturday &amp;amp; Sunday, tell your friends!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;All, this is a friendly reminder of the BIG, FANTASTIC and FUN, Annual Moontown Fly-In, THIS Saturday and Sunday, September 20-21.  There is will lots of planes, lots of people, food and lots of fun.  Plan to bring your family out to an Old Fashion Grass Field fly-In, the way it used to be.  Bi-wings, homebuilt, Cubs, Champs and many more.  No admission charged for the fly-in. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Tickets are still on sale for the Saturday night dinner banquet at George’s hangar.  This annual event has featured speakers from Astronauts to Authors.  This year, the planning committee asked me to MC the evening and present to you some of our own local legends from around our community.  Come enjoy a special evenings with friends as we look to the past and learn what it was like to serve in the military during World War II, Korea and Vietnam.  Whether it was storming the beaches at Normandy or flying bombers round the clock to intimidate Russia, the brave service of these people helped make America what it is today.  They will share a few details of their service.  Hear serious stories of survival; as well as some humor that sometime kept them going.  Who knows, we might even talk George into dancing for us!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.moontownairport.com/"&gt;Visit the website&lt;/a&gt; for details on the entire weekend event and call the lounge to get your tickets for the dinner banquet, Before They Are Gone! 852-9781.  Be sure to forward this to your friends.  See you there!&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/moontown-fly-in-2008-20-21-september/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2008 20:14:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Wine, Treasure, and (Mayan) Archaeology in Huntsville</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/wine-treasure-and-mayan-archaeology-in/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Help support the lecture series of the North Alabama Society of the Archaeological Institute of America.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;On Saturday, November 15th, 7:00-9:00 PM, NASAIA will host a wine tasting at the Lowe House (210 Williams Street) the elegant, historic home of UAHuntsville President Dave Williams. Sommelier Tami Herrington of Pinnacle Imports will guide guests through the wines of South America. As you sample these ﬁne wines you can bid on the treasures available in a silent auction. As a special event, renowned NASA archaeologist Dr. &lt;a href="http://www.ghcc.msfc.nasa.gov/personnel/ghcc_personnel_sever.html"&gt;Tom Sever&lt;/a&gt; will give a brief talk on his most recent research on the Maya.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Tickets available for $25/glass, $40/couple, and $15/seniors. Please Contact Lillian Joyce for tickets: &lt;a href="mailto:JoyceL@uah.edu"&gt;JoyceL@uah.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ancgeo</category><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><category>nasaia</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/wine-treasure-and-mayan-archaeology-in/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2008 00:26:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>