<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about isaw)</title><link>http://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://paregorios.org/categories/isaw.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:paregorios@hotmail.com"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 23:11:11 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Job: Senior Digital Humanities Web Developer/Architect</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2013/08/job-senior-digital-humanities-web/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Reblogged from &lt;a href="https://isaw.nyu.edu/jobs/available-staff-positions/"&gt;https://isaw.nyu.edu/jobs/available-staff-positions/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;In order to shape and secure the future of innovative teaching and research at ISAW and beyond, we work with others to nurture new and important open information resources for the ancient world, especially those that connect and contextualize information across institutional, methodological, and technological divides. Accordingly, our Senior Digital Humanities Web Developer/Architects envision, create, and curate web applications that bridge gaps in content and function while handling the diversity of languages, scripts, geography, chronology, and methodology inherent in the study of the past-oriented humanities. You carry out this mission in constant, productive collaboration with scholars, students, and enthusiasts from both inside and outside the Institute, empowering them as co-creators, curators, and users.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;Position description and application instructions may be found online at: &lt;a href="http://www.nyucareers.com/applicants/Central?quickFind=57339"&gt;http://www.nyucareers.com/applicants/Central?quickFind=57339&lt;/a&gt;</description><category>dh</category><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>jobs</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2013/08/job-senior-digital-humanities-web/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2013 02:52:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Citing Sources in Digital Annotations</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2013/04/citing-sources-in-digital-annotations/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm collaborating with other folks both in and outside &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt; on a variety of digital scholarly projects in which &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/LinkedData.html"&gt;Linked Open Data&lt;/a&gt; is playing a big role. We're using the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resource_Description_Framework"&gt;Resource Description Framework (RDF)&lt;/a&gt; to provide descriptive information for, and make cross-project assertions about, a variety of entities of interest and the data associated with them (places, people, themes/subjects, creative works, bibliographic items, and manuscripts and other text-bearing objects). So, for example, I can produce the following assertions in RDF (using the &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TeamSubmission/turtle/"&gt;Terse RDF Triple Language, or TuRTLe&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre style="font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; color: #000000; background-color: #eee;font-size: 12px;border: 1px dashed #999999;line-height: 14px;padding: 5px; overflow: auto; width: 100%"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45&amp;gt; a &amp;lt;http://geovocab.org/spatial#Feature&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  rdfs:label "Serugh" ;&lt;br&gt;  rdfs:comment "An ancient city where Jacob of Serugh was bishop."@en ;&lt;br&gt;  foaf:primaryTopicOf &amp;lt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suruç&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  owl:sameAs &amp;lt;http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/658405#this&amp;gt; .&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;This means: 'There's a resource identified with the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_resource_identifier"&gt;Uniform Resource Identifier (URI)&lt;/a&gt; "http://syriaca.org/place/45" about which the following is asserted: &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;it is a "Feature" as defined in the &lt;a href="http://geovocab.org/spatial.html"&gt;NeoGeo Spatial Ontology&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-schema/#ch_label"&gt;human-readable version of its name&lt;/a&gt; is "Serugh";&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-schema/#ch_comment"&gt;a human-readable description&lt;/a&gt; (in the English language) of it is "An ancient city where Jacob of Serugh was bishop.";&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;it is &lt;a href="http://xmlns.com/foaf/spec/#term_isPrimaryTopicOf"&gt;the primary topic of a document&lt;/a&gt; that is identified by the URI "http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suruç"; and&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;it is &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/owl-ref/#sameAs-def"&gt;the same resource as&lt;/a&gt; that identified by another URI: "http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/658405#this".'&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br&gt;(Folks familiar with what &lt;a href="http://sgillies.net/"&gt;Sean Gillies&lt;/a&gt; has done for the &lt;a href="https://github.com/isawnyu/pleiades-rdf"&gt;Pleiades RDF&lt;/a&gt; will recognize my debt to him in the what proceeds.) &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But there are plenty of cases in which just issuing a couple of &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-rdf-concepts-20040210/#dfn-rdf-triple"&gt;triples&lt;/a&gt; to encode an assertion about something isn't sufficient; we need to be able to assign responsibility/origin for those assertions and to link them to supporting argument and evidence (i.e., standard scholarly citation practice). For this purpose, we're very pleased by the &lt;a href="http://www.openannotation.org/"&gt;Open Annotation Collaboration&lt;/a&gt;, whose &lt;i&gt;Open Annotation Data Model&lt;/i&gt; was recently updated and expanded in the form of a &lt;a href="http://www.openannotation.org/spec/core/"&gt;W3C Community Draft (8 February 2013)&lt;/a&gt; (the participants in &lt;a href="http://pelagios-project.blogspot.com/"&gt;Pelagios&lt;/a&gt; use basic OAC annotations to assert geographic relationships between their data and Pleiades places).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A basic OADM annotation uses a series of RDF triples to link together a "target" (the thing you want to make an assertion about) and a "body" (the content of your assertion). You can think of them as footnotes. The "target" is the range of text after which you put your footnote number (only in OADM you can add a footnote to any real, conceptual, or digital thing you can identify) and the "body" is the content of the footnote itself. &lt;a href="http://www.openannotation.org/spec/core/core.html#BodyTarget"&gt;The OADM draft formally explains this structure in section 2.1&lt;/a&gt;. This lets me add an annotation to the resource from our example above (the ancient city of Serugh) by using the URI "http://syriaca.org/place/45" as the target of an annotation) thus: &lt;br&gt;&lt;pre style="font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; color: #000000; background-color: #eee;font-size: 12px;border: 1px dashed #999999;line-height: 14px;padding: 5px; overflow: auto; width: 100%"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45/anno/desc6&amp;gt; a oa:Annotation ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:hasBody &amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45/anno/desc6/body&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:hasTarget &amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:motivatedBy oa:describing ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:annotatedBy &amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/editors.xml#tcarlson&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:annotatedAt "2013-04-03T00:00:01Z" ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:serializedBy &amp;lt;https://github.com/paregorios/srpdemo1/blob/master/xsl/place2ttl.xsl&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:serializedAt "2013-04-17T13:35:05.771-05:00" .&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45/anno/desc6/body&amp;gt; a cnt:ContentAsText, dctypes:Text ;&lt;br&gt;  cnt:chars "an ancient town, formerly located near Sarug."@en ;&lt;br&gt;  dc:format "text/plain" ;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;I hope you'll forgive me for not spelling that all out in plain text, as all the syntax and terms are explained in the OADM. What I'm concerned about in this blog post is really what the OADM &lt;strong&gt;doesn't&lt;/strong&gt; explicitly tell me how to do, namely: show that the annotation body is actually a quotation from a published book. The verb oa:annotatedBy lets me indicate that the annotation itself was made (i.e., the footnote was written) by a resource identified by the URI "http://syriaca.org/editors.xml#tcarlson". If I'd given you a few more triples, you could have figured out that that resource is a real person named Thomas Carlson, who is one of the editors working on the &lt;a href="http://syriaca.org"&gt;Syriac Reference Portal project&lt;/a&gt;. But how do I indicate (as he very much wants to do because he's a responsible scholar and has no interest in plagiarizing anyone) that he's deliberately quoting a book called &lt;a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/255043315"&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Scattered Pearls: A History of Syriac Literature and Sciences&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;? Here's what I came up with (using terms from &lt;a href="http://purl.org/spar/cito/"&gt;Citation Typing Ontology&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/"&gt;DCMI Metadata Terms&lt;/a&gt;): &lt;br&gt;&lt;pre style="font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; color: #000000; background-color: #eee;font-size: 12px;border: 1px dashed #999999;line-height: 14px;padding: 5px; overflow: auto; width: 100%"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45/anno/desc7/body&amp;gt; a cnt:ContentAsText, dctypes:Text ;&lt;br&gt;  cnt:chars "a small town in the Mudar territory, between Ḥarran and Jarabulus. [Modern name, Suruç (tr.)]"@en ;&lt;br&gt;  dc:format "text/plain" ;&lt;br&gt;  cito:citesAsSourceDocument &amp;lt;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/255043315&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  dcterms:biblographicCitation  "The Scattered Pearls: A History of Syriac Literature and Sciences, p. 558"@en .&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;The addition of the triple containing cito:citesAsSourceDocument lets me make a machine-actionable link to the additional structured bibliographic data about the book that's available at Worldcat (but it doesn't say anything about page numbers!). The addition of the triple containing dcterms:bibliographicCitation lets me provide a human-readable citation. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'd love to have feedback on this approach from folks in the OAC, CITO, DCTERMS, and general linked data communities. Could I do better? Should I do something differently? &lt;br&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;br&gt;The SRP team is currently evaluating a sample batch of such annotations, which you're also welcome to view. The &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/srpdemo1/tree/master/rdf/place"&gt;RDF can be found here&lt;/a&gt;. These files are generated from &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/srpdemo1/tree/master/xml/places"&gt;the TEI XML here&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/srpdemo1/blob/master/xsl/place2ttl.xsl"&gt;the XSLT here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;</description><category>bibliography</category><category>collaboration</category><category>concordia</category><category>data</category><category>horothesia</category><category>interop</category><category>isaw</category><category>lawdi</category><category>linkeddata</category><category>LOD</category><category>neogeography</category><category>patterns</category><category>pelagios</category><category>pleiades</category><category>rdf</category><category>tei</category><category>xml</category><category>xslt</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2013/04/citing-sources-in-digital-annotations/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2013 23:35:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ancient Studies Needs Open Bibliographic Data and Associated URIs</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/06/ancient-studies-needs-open/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;Update 1:  links throughout, minor formatting changes, proper Creative Commons Public Domain tools, parenthetical about import path from Endnote and such, fixing a few typos.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.neh.gov/"&gt;NEH&lt;/a&gt;-funded &lt;a href="http://wiki.digitalclassicist.org/Linked_Ancient_World_Data_Institute"&gt;Linked Ancient World Data Institute&lt;/a&gt;, still in progress at &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt;, has got me thinking about a number of things. One of them is bibliography and linked data. Here's a brain dump, intended to spark conversation and collaboration.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;What We Need&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;As much bibliographic data as possible, for both primary and secondary sources (print and digital), publicly released to third parties under either a public domain declaration or an unrestrictive open license.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Stable HTTP &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_resource_identifier"&gt;URIs&lt;/a&gt; for every work and author included in those datasets.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Why&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Bibliographic and citation collection and management are integral to every research and publication in project in ancient studies. We could save each other a lot of time, and get more substantive work done in the field, if it was simpler and easier to do. We could more easily and effectively tie together disparate work published on the web (and appearing on the web through retrospective digitization) if we had a common infrastructure and shared point of reference. There's already a lot of digital data in various hands that could support such an effort, but a good chunk of it is not out where anybody with good will and talent can get at it to improve it, build tools around it, etc.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;What I Want You (and Me) To Do If You Have Bibliographic Data&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Release it to the world through a third party. No matter what format it's in, give a copy to someone else whose function is hosting free data on the web. Dump it into a public repository at &lt;a href="http://github.com/"&gt;github.com&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://sourceforge.net/"&gt;sourceforge.net&lt;/a&gt;. Put it into a shared library at &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/"&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.bibsonomy.org/"&gt;Bibsonomy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.mendeley.com/"&gt;Mendeley&lt;/a&gt;, or another bibliographic content website (most have easy upload/import paths from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EndNote"&gt;Endnote&lt;/a&gt;, and other citation management applications). Hosting a copy yourself is fine, but giving it to a third party demonstrates your bona fides, gets it out of your nifty but restrictive search engine or database, and increments your bus number.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Release it under a Creative Commons &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/about/pdm"&gt;Public Domain Mark&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/about/cc0"&gt;Public Domain Dedication (CC0)&lt;/a&gt;.  Or if you can't do that, find as open a &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/"&gt;Creative Commons&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_content#Licenses"&gt;similar license&lt;/a&gt; as you can. Don't try to control it. If there's some aspect of the data that you can't (because of rights encumberance) or don't want to (why?) give away to make the world a better place, find a quick way to extract, filter, or excerpt that aspect and get the rest out.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Alert the world to your philanthropy. Blog or tweet about it. Post a link to the data on your institutional website. Above all, alert &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/people/staff/chuck-jones"&gt;Chuck Jones&lt;/a&gt; and Phoebe Acheson so it gets announced via &lt;a href="http://ancientworldonline.blogspot.com/"&gt;Ancient World Online&lt;/a&gt; and/or &lt;a href="http://ancientbiblio.wordpress.com/"&gt;Ancient World Open Bibliographies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do the same if you have other useful data, like identifiers for modern or ancient works or authors.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get in touch with me and/or anyone else to talk about the next step: setting up stable HTTP URIs corresponding to this stuff.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;b&gt;Who I'm Talking To&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;First of all, I'm talking to myself, my collaborators, and my team-mates at ISAW. I intend to eat my own dogfood.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here are other institutions and entities I know about who have potentially useful data.&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="http://openlibrary.org/"&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt; : data about books is already out there and available, and there are ways to add more&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/"&gt;Perseus Project&lt;/a&gt; : a huge, FRBR-ized collection of MODS records for Greek and Latin authors, works, and modern editions thereof.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://chs.harvard.edu/chs"&gt;Center for Hellenic Studies&lt;/a&gt;: identifiers for Greek and Latin authors and works&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.annee-philologique.com/"&gt;L'Année Philologique&lt;/a&gt; and its institutional partners like the &lt;a href="http://www.apaclassics.org/"&gt;American Philological Association&lt;/a&gt;: the big collection of analytic secondary bibliography for classics (journal articles)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://projects.chass.utoronto.ca/amphoras/tocs.html"&gt;TOCS-IN&lt;/a&gt;: a collaboratively collected batch of analytic secondary bibliography for classics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://papyri.info/"&gt;Papyri.info&lt;/a&gt; and its contributing project partners: TEI bibliographic records for  much of the bibliography produced for or cited by Greek and Latin papyrologists (plus other ancient language/script traditions in papyrology)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gnomon-online.de/"&gt;Gnomon Bibliographische Datenbank&lt;/a&gt;: masses of bibliographic data for books and articles for classics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Any and every university library system that has a dedicated or easily extracted set of associated catalog records. Especially any with unique collections (e.g., Cincinnati) or those with databases of analytical bibliography down to the level of articles in journals and collections.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ditto any and every ancient studies digital project that has bibliographic data in a database.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Comments, Reactions, Suggestions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Welcome, encouraged, and essential. By comment here or otherwise (but not private email please!).&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>backstop</category><category>bibliography</category><category>books</category><category>boundaries</category><category>collaboration</category><category>concordia</category><category>digclass</category><category>horothesia</category><category>interop</category><category>isaw</category><category>lawdi</category><category>linkeddata</category><category>openness</category><category>rights</category><category>walled gardens</category><category>zotero</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/06/ancient-studies-needs-open/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2012 19:03:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Feeds of Flickr Photos Depicting Pleiades Places</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2011/09/feeds-of-flickr-photos-depicting/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Some months ago, ISAW started adding &lt;b&gt;Pleiades machine tags&lt;/b&gt; to the &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/awib"&gt;Ancient World Image Bank (AWIB)&lt;/a&gt; photos we've been uploading to &lt;a href="http://flickr.com/"&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;. This post will explain what that means, how it might be useful to you and how you can add Pleiades machine tags to your own photos so we can find out about them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Updated: &lt;/b&gt;8:45pm EDT, 10 September 2011 (&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;changes highlighted in orange&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Updated:&lt;/b&gt; 10:43am EST, 20 December 2011 (some of what's here is now superseded by recent developments; see further this new post: &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2011/12/pleiades-flickr-and-ancient-world-image.html"&gt;Pleiades, Flickr, and the Ancient World Image Bank&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pleiades Machine Tags&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt; is a collaborative, open-access digital gazetteer for the ancient world. AWIB is an open-access publication that uses the Flickr photo-sharing site to publish free, reusable photos of ancient sites and artifacts. &lt;a href="http://tagaholic.me/2009/03/26/what-are-machine-tags.html"&gt;Machine tags&lt;/a&gt; are an extension to &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/help/tags/"&gt;Flickr's basic tag-this-photo functionality&lt;/a&gt; that "use a special syntax to define extra information about a tag" (&lt;a href="http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/yws-flickr/message/2736"&gt;Aaron Straup Cope, "Ladies and Gentlemen: Machine Tags," 24 January 2007&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A Pleiades machine tag looks like this:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;pleiades:place=&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;795868&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;where 795868 is the stable identifier portion of a Pleiades &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_Resource_Identifier"&gt;Uniform Resource Identifier&lt;/a&gt; (URI).  In this example, the URI corresponding to the machine tag above is:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/795868"&gt;http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;795868&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;Note what's in common between the machine tag and the URI (highlighted in yellow).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;What Pleiades Machine Tags Are Good For&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/services/api/"&gt;Flickr API&lt;/a&gt; makes it possible to request lists of machine-tagged photos in the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS"&gt;RSS webfeed format&lt;/a&gt;. So, to get a list of all photos in Flickr that are tagged with the example machine tag above, pop this into your &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/News_aggregator"&gt;feed reader&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://api.flickr.com/services/feeds/photos_public.gne?tags=pleiades%3Aplace=795868&amp;amp;lang=en-us&amp;amp;format=rss_200"&gt;http://api.flickr.com/services/feeds/photos_public.gne?tags=pleiades%3Aplace&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;795868&amp;amp;lang=en-us&amp;amp;format=rss_200&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;The same results can be viewed in HTML in a browser by resolving the following:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/tags/pleiades:place=795868" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/tags/pleiades:place=795868&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;To get a list of all photos in Flickr that are tagged with &lt;b&gt;any&lt;/b&gt; Pleiades machine tag, try this (the API syntax supports wildcards!):&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://api.flickr.com/services/feeds/photos_public.gne?tags=pleiades%3Aplace%3D&amp;amp;lang=en-us&amp;amp;format=rss_200"&gt;http://api.flickr.com/services/feeds/photos_public.gne?tags=pleiades%3Aplace%3D&amp;amp;lang=en-us&amp;amp;format=rss_200&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;The same results, viewed in HTML on the Flickr site:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/tags/pleiades:place" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/tags/pleiades:place&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;Feeds like these aren't just for feed readers anymore. You can add user-interface widgets to your blog or website to summarize the latest content for your readers (check out the right-hand column in this blog). You can hook up services like &lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/networkedblogs"&gt;Networked Blogs&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://twitterfeed.com/"&gt;Twitterfeed&lt;/a&gt; to pass on the latest changes to your Facebook friends or Twitter followers. If you've got a &lt;a href="http://nomisma.org/"&gt;web-facing numismatic database that you've already linked up with Pleiades&lt;/a&gt; for the mint locations, you could write custom code to pull a corresponding picture of the ancient site into your web interface (say, alongside the map you've already got).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Add Pleiades Machine Tags to Your Own Photos on Flickr&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Many of you have been taking amazing photos of ancient sites and artifacts for years. Many of you have posted some of them to Flickr and shared them with great groups like &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/groups/chiron/"&gt;Chiron&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/groups/562831@N24/"&gt;Visibile Parlare - Greek Inscriptions&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/groups/visible_words/"&gt;Visibile Parlare - Latin Inscriptions&lt;/a&gt;. If you'd like these photos to appear in queries and feeds (like those described above), right alongside the photos that we're publishing via AWIB, all you have to do is add the appropriate Pleiades machine tags in Flickr. Just look up your site on Pleiades, copy the numeric ID from the URI in your browser's location bar, append it to the string "pleiades:place=" and tag your Flickr photos with it. In this way, you can help us improve findability of good photos of ancient sites and the artifacts found there for everyone on the web. Who knows ... maybe enough people will join us in this effort that we can someday get the Flickr development team to give Pleiades machine tags some &lt;a href="http://code.flickr.com/blog/2009/07/06/extraextraextra/"&gt;extra love&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Kudos to:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Aaron Straup Cope for his blog post &lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;"&lt;a href="http://code.flickr.com/blog/2008/07/18/wildcard-machine-tag-urls/"&gt;Wildcard Machine Tag URLs&lt;/a&gt;" (18 July 2008)&lt;/span&gt; that showed me how to construct the API queries necessary to get the RSS feeds described above. &lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="background-color: #f6b26b;"&gt;That, and &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/services/feeds/docs/photos_public/"&gt;the Flickr API documentation on feeds&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Nate Nagy, Managing Editor of AWIB, who applies the tags and keeps AWIB rolling.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dan Pet, from the &lt;a href="http://finds.org.uk/"&gt;Portable Antiquities Scheme&lt;/a&gt;, and Ryan Baumann, from the &lt;a href="http://www.vis.uky.edu/"&gt;Center for Visualization and Virtual Environments&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Kentucky, who put me onto machine tags in the first place and helped me get up to speed.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>awib</category><category>collaboration</category><category>feeds</category><category>flickr</category><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>pleiades</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2011/09/feeds-of-flickr-photos-depicting/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2011 23:51:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Linking to Google Books Content in an Ancient Geographic Way</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2010/07/im-very-interested-in-finding-ways/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm very interested in finding ways through &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/about-projects.htm"&gt;other ISAW digital projects&lt;/a&gt; to support &lt;a href="http://www.ecs.soton.ac.uk/about/news/3325"&gt;the efforts of Leif, Elton and Eric&lt;/a&gt; on the "Google Ancient Places (GAP): Discovering historic geographical entities in the Google Books corpus" project. In particular, I'd hope we can integrate this into the web interfaces for our projects:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;ECS will work on a Web Service and Web Widget [that] will make it possible for Webmasters to add links to the ancient texts [in Google Books] within their websites, enabling the public and researchers to search for them easily.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>ancgeo</category><category>collaboration</category><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>neogeography</category><category>pleiades</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2010/07/im-very-interested-in-finding-ways/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2010 19:33:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>ISAW has a news blog</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2010/06/isaw-has-news-blog/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="http://blogs.nyu.edu/isaw/news/"&gt;ISAW now has an official news blog&lt;/a&gt;. I'm going to stop posting ISAW news here on &lt;i&gt;Horothesia&lt;/i&gt;. If you want to catch up on the latest from ISAW (e.g., the recent announcement of our newest faculty member, Lillian Tseng), head on over to &lt;a href="http://blogs.nyu.edu/isaw/news/"&gt;http://blogs.nyu.edu/isaw/news/&lt;/a&gt;.</description><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2010/06/isaw-has-news-blog/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2010 03:11:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>ISAW New Faculty Appointment: Sören Stark</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2010/04/isaw-new-faculty-appointment-soren/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;From ISAW's director, Roger Bagnall:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/"&gt;Institute for the Study of the Ancient World&lt;/a&gt; at New York University is pleased to announce the appointment of Sören Stark as Assistant Professor of Central Asian Art and Archaeology.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Professor Stark studied Oriental Archaeology and Art History, Ancient History, and European Art History at Martin-Luther-Universität Halle-Wittenberg. He received his doctorate in 2005 with a study on the archaeology and history of the pre-Muslim Turks in Central and Inner Asia, which was published in 2008 as Die Alttürkenzeit in Mittel- und Zentralasien. Archaeologische und historische Studien (Nomaden und Sesshafte 6).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;From 2005 to 2008 he led archaeological surveys and excavations in Northern Tajikistan. Before joining the faculty of ISAW he was a Junior Fellow at the Excellence Cluster TOPOI and teaching at the Freie Universität in Berlin.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;His research ranges chronologically from the Iron Age up to the pre-Mongol Middle Ages and deals with various aspects of archaeology, art history, and history in Central and Inner Asia as well as in neighboring cultural areas. His main focus lies on the political and cultural interrelations between pastoral nomads in these areas and their sedentary neighbors. Currently, he is preparing a book on territorial fortifications in Western Central Asia. He is also co-editor of a Handbook of Central Asian Archaeology and Art which is presently under preparation at Oxford University Press.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Professor Stark will begin teaching seminars at ISAW in the fall. Please join us in welcoming him to our community.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;Professor Stark's faculty profile is at &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/faculty.htm#stark"&gt;http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/faculty.htm#stark&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2010/04/isaw-new-faculty-appointment-soren/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2010 03:52:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bridging Institutional Repository and Bibliographic Management</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/11/bridging-institutional-repository-and/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;As an institution, &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt; has an interest in disseminating, preserving and promoting the research products and publications of its faculty, research staff, students, affiliates and collaborators. Our parent institution, &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu"&gt;NYU&lt;/a&gt;, has made a commitment to the persistent dissemination of such materials when voluntarily contributed to its &lt;a href="http://archive.nyu.edu/"&gt;Faculty Digital Archive (FDA)&lt;/a&gt;. We'll use the FDA as a locus for materials that fit well into &lt;a href="http://www.dspace.org/"&gt;DSpace&lt;/a&gt; (with which the FDA is realized) and that aren't rights-constrained. But we also need mechanisms for developing and publishing the whole bibliographic story of a particular faculty member, research group, project or conference with links from the individual entries to digital copies wherever they may be (e.g., the FDA, &lt;a href="http://www.jstor.org/"&gt;JSTOR&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.archive.org/"&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://books.google.com/"&gt;Google Books&lt;/a&gt;). For this function, we like &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/"&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;. Atop &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/blog/follow-libraries-and-collections-with-feeds/"&gt;Zotero's robust and ubiquitous feed documents&lt;/a&gt;, we can build interoperability with our website and other tools and venues in a way that is also completely visible to commercial and third-party search and discovery tools.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There will be a number of iterations necessary to reach a fully robust solution, but we're already taking some of the first steps.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As an early experiment with the FDA, we had a student assistant input all of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_S._Bagnall"&gt;my boss&lt;/a&gt;'s articles in PDF format, along with descriptive metadata (see: &lt;a href="http://archive.nyu.edu/handle/2451/28115"&gt;Roger Bagnall's Publications&lt;/a&gt;). The default metadata schema in the FDA wasn't a perfect fit for journal article citations, but the FDA staff is now working with us to extend the schema to meet our needs.  We're using the Zotero data model as a guide.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Given that the metadata in this collection is the only structured dataset around for Roger's articles, I wanted to be able to get it all back out to use for other things. The FDA does provide web feeds, but (unlike Zotero) these aren't comprehensive for a given context and don't incorporate all the metadata fields. But we can use FDA's &lt;a href="http://www.openarchives.org/pmh/"&gt;OAI-PMH&lt;/a&gt; interface to get the full metadata with a query like:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://archive.nyu.edu/request?verb=ListRecords&amp;amp;metadataPrefix=oai_dc&amp;amp;set=hdl_2451_28115"&gt;http://archive.nyu.edu/request?verb=ListRecords&amp;amp;metadataPrefix=oai_dc&amp;amp;set=hdl_2451_28115&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;where "hdl_2451_28115" is the identifier for the "Roger Bagnall's Publications" container I linked to above. (Special thanks to Ekaterina Pechekhonova on the NYU Digital Library team, who helped me with syntax).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As a further experiment, I wrote an &lt;a href="http://homepages.nyu.edu/%7Ete20/examples/fda-zotero/fdaoai2zoterordf.xsl"&gt;XSL transform to convert the OAI-PMH XML&lt;/a&gt; document into the &lt;a href="http://homepages.nyu.edu/%7Ete20/examples/fda-zotero/bagnall-fda.rdf"&gt;RDF XML Zotero can import&lt;/a&gt;. There are a couple of inelegant hacks in the transform (mainly to get at substrings within single fields), but I'm still happy with the results. The import into Zotero went smoothly:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/paregorios/items/collection/1505597"&gt;http://www.zotero.org/paregorios/items/collection/1505597&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Next steps: move this to a shared Zotero library so Roger, a student assistant and members of our digital projects team can collaborate to enter the rest of the publications (books, book sections, etc.) and fix any errors in the article records. Then we'll look at the process for using that metadata (via another transform) to help us populate the FDA. We'll also start working on parsing and aggregating Zotero's feeds for use on our website (in Roger's online profile and aggregated with other affiliates' feeds to provide a "recent publications" section).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We're also experimenting with Zotero for the &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/groups/pleiades"&gt;bibliography of our Pleiades project&lt;/a&gt; (a &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;collaborative online gazetteer of the Greek and Roman world&lt;/a&gt;), and as a component in a potential replacement for the &lt;a href="http://scriptorium.lib.duke.edu/papyrus/texts/clist.html"&gt;Checklist of Editions of Greek, Latin, Demotic and Coptic Papyri, Ostraca and Tablets&lt;/a&gt;. On a more personal level, I've taken to doing all my bookmarking with Zotero and have set up &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/paregorios/items/collection/1299262"&gt;a folder in my library&lt;/a&gt; (with associated feed) so that colleagues can following what I'm citing on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>bibliography</category><category>dspace</category><category>fda</category><category>horothesia</category><category>interop</category><category>isaw</category><category>papyrology</category><category>pleiades</category><category>publications</category><category>tools</category><category>zotero</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/11/bridging-institutional-repository-and/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2009 21:27:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Horse is Man's Wings: Archaeological Science and the Changing Nature of the Human-Horse Relationship in Central and East Asia</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/horse-is-mans-wings-archaeological/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. &lt;a href="http://www.archaeological.org/webinfo.php?page=10224&amp;amp;lid=180"&gt;Mim Bower&lt;/a&gt; (Cambridge University) will give a free, public lecture at &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt; on 27 October 2009 at 6:00 p.m.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;More information, including an abstract of the talk, is available on the &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/events.htm"&gt;ISAW events page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>isawevents</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/horse-is-mans-wings-archaeological/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2009 21:46:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Historian in the Future of the Ancient World: A View from Central Eurasia</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/historian-in-future-of-ancient-world/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt; has announced the third annual Leon Levy Lecture, to be held on November 5, 2009 at 6 p.m in the Oak Library, 2nd floor of the ISAW building, located at 15 East 84th Street in New York. The speaker will be Professor &lt;a href="http://www.hs.ias.edu/eas/di_cosmowebpage.htm"&gt;Nicola Di Cosmo&lt;/a&gt; of the Institute for Advanced Study. The lecture is free and open to the public but seating is limited. Interested individuals are requested to RSVP by calling 212.992.7818, or emailing &lt;a href="mailto:isaw@nyu.edu"&gt;isaw@nyu.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;More information (including abstract) is available on the &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/events.htm"&gt;ISAW events page&lt;/a&gt;. There is also an &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/public.affairs/releases/detail/2838"&gt;NYU press release&lt;/a&gt; with more details.</description><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>isawevents</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/historian-in-future-of-ancient-world/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2009 21:42:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>