<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about isawevents)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://paregorios.org/categories/isawevents.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:ipse@paregorios.org"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;&lt;img
alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
property="dct:title"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;paregorios.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by
&lt;a xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" href="https://paregorios.org/me"
property="cc:attributionName" rel="cc:attributionURL"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; is
licensed under a &lt;a rel="license"
href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 May 2018 12:25:48 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Zeugma at Pleiades and ISAW</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2011/02/zeugma-at-pleiades-and-isaw/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;In honor of &lt;a href="http://www.dtcf.ankara.edu.tr/kadro.php?doc-dr-kutalmis-gorkay=&amp;amp;id=18&amp;amp;lang=tr"&gt;Kutal Gorkay&lt;/a&gt;'s upcoming talk at ISAW (&lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/events/gorkay-2011-03-21.htm"&gt;Recent Archaeological Research in Zeugma&lt;/a&gt;: March 21, 2011), I've taken the opportunity to update the &lt;a class="citation" href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/658636"&gt;Zeugma resource at Pleiades&lt;/a&gt;. It now has:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;a precise location (taken from the visible remains of the theater)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Greek orthography for the name Zeugma (Ζεύγμα) -- I couldn't quickly find a verifiable ancient reference for the other name we inherited from the Barrington: &lt;i&gt;Seleukeia pros to Euphrate&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;an updated description and place type (settlement)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;a modestly expanded "details" section in which I link to Zeugma resources elsewhere (including &lt;a href="http://www.zeugmaarchproject.com/"&gt;the official excavation website&lt;/a&gt;, Wikipedia, Livius.org and some digital publications by David Walker at the University of Western Australia)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;I hope you'll check out both the lecture notice and the Pleiades resource. I'd of course be grateful for comments, corrections and additions to the latter. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;And if you think you could do something like this for another Pleiades place resource, by all means, please join up and give it a try. You'll find how-to instructions in my &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2011/01/adopt-place-for-valentines-day.html"&gt;Valentine's Day Pleiades Post&lt;/a&gt;. If you've got Irish interests or ancestry, why not pick &lt;a href="http://tinyurl.com/5to7php"&gt;an ancient site in Ireland&lt;/a&gt; to spruce up in celebration of St. Patrick's Day!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a class="citation" href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/658636"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Zeugma on Pleiades: http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/658636&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ancient sites in Ireland link courtesy of the &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/Members/sgillies/news-items/spatial-parameters-for-the-site-search-form"&gt;spatial search functions&lt;/a&gt; Sean Gillies recently added to Pleiades.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ancgeo</category><category>horothesia</category><category>isawevents</category><category>pleiades</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2011/02/zeugma-at-pleiades-and-isaw/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2011 03:02:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Temple Treasury Records and Local Politics in Ur III Mesopotamia</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2010/02/temple-treasury-records-and-local/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;February 16: ISAW Visiting Research Scholar Lecture&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Speaker: Xiaoli Ouyang&lt;br&gt;Location: 2nd Floor Lecture Room&lt;br&gt;Date: Tuesday, February 16&lt;br&gt;Time: 6:00 p.m.&lt;br&gt;*reception to follow&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Temple Treasury Records and Local Politics in Ur III Mesopotamia&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This lecture targets a group of Umma texts dated to the Ur III dynasty (c. 2112-2004 BCE), probably the best documented period in Mesopotamian history. Umma is the province with the largest number of texts, accounting for almost one third of the 90,000 or so records from this period. This group of texts documents the delivery of ... &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://pipsqueak.atlantides.org/isaw/events/ouyang-2010-02-16.htm"&gt;Click here for permalink and full description&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>isawevents</category><category>lectures</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2010/02/temple-treasury-records-and-local/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2010 23:19:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bringing the Frontier to the Center: Empires and Nomads from Achaemenid Persia to Tang China</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/11/bringing-frontier-to-center-empires-and/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;a lecture, presented by:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Wu Xin&lt;br&gt;Visiting Research Scholar&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/"&gt;Institute for the Study of the Ancient World&lt;/a&gt;, New York University&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;This paper presents a comparative consideration of the ideological strategies used by Achaemenid and the Tang empires to manage relations with their subjects living in Central Asia and on the Central to Eastern Eurasian steppe. For both empires, the nomadic communities to the north were an especially important constituency that was complicated by strong dynastic hereditary ties. In each case, a conscious program specifically addressing this complex and mobile community was developed and was expressed through the official language (text and images) of the imperial court. An exploration of those programs reveals striking parallels in their approach to maintaining imperial control and cooperation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;Monday, 6:00 pm&lt;br&gt;November 30, 2009&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Lecture Hall&lt;br&gt;ISAW Building&lt;br&gt;15 East 84th Street&lt;br&gt;New York, NY 10028&lt;br&gt;isaw@nyu.edu&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;this event is free and open to the public &lt;/span&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>isawevents</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/11/bringing-frontier-to-center-empires-and/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2009 04:18:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Horse is Man's Wings: Archaeological Science and the Changing Nature of the Human-Horse Relationship in Central and East Asia</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/horse-is-mans-wings-archaeological/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. &lt;a href="http://www.archaeological.org/webinfo.php?page=10224&amp;amp;lid=180"&gt;Mim Bower&lt;/a&gt; (Cambridge University) will give a free, public lecture at &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt; on 27 October 2009 at 6:00 p.m.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;More information, including an abstract of the talk, is available on the &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/events.htm"&gt;ISAW events page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>isawevents</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/horse-is-mans-wings-archaeological/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2009 21:46:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Historian in the Future of the Ancient World: A View from Central Eurasia</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/historian-in-future-of-ancient-world/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt; has announced the third annual Leon Levy Lecture, to be held on November 5, 2009 at 6 p.m in the Oak Library, 2nd floor of the ISAW building, located at 15 East 84th Street in New York. The speaker will be Professor &lt;a href="http://www.hs.ias.edu/eas/di_cosmowebpage.htm"&gt;Nicola Di Cosmo&lt;/a&gt; of the Institute for Advanced Study. The lecture is free and open to the public but seating is limited. Interested individuals are requested to RSVP by calling 212.992.7818, or emailing &lt;a href="mailto:isaw@nyu.edu"&gt;isaw@nyu.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;More information (including abstract) is available on the &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/events.htm"&gt;ISAW events page&lt;/a&gt;. There is also an &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/public.affairs/releases/detail/2838"&gt;NYU press release&lt;/a&gt; with more details.</description><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>isawevents</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/historian-in-future-of-ancient-world/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2009 21:42:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>David Klotz: The Temple of Osiris in Abydos during the Late Period</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/david-klotz-temple-of-osiris-in-abydos/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;2009-2010 Visiting Research Scholar Lecture Series&lt;br&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/"&gt;Institute for the Study of the Ancient World&lt;/a&gt;, NYU&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Temple of Osiris in Abydos during the Late Period&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;Presented by: David Klotz, Visiting Research Scholar&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Although the city of Abydos was one of the most important religious centers of Egypt from the Predynastic  Period through the New Kingdom, little remains of its monuments from the Late Period (c. 1000-300 BC).  In the early twentieth century, W.F. Petrie discovered meager traces of an Osiris temple dating to the reign of Amasis (Twenty-Sixth Dynasty, c. 570-526 BC), and recent New York University excavations have uncovered another temple built by Nectanebo I and II (Thirtieth Dynasty, c. 378-341 BC). Nonetheless, the intervening period - the era of Persian domination - remains a mystery, and the earlier temple of Amasis seems to have completely vanished.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Two new sources provide valuable information on this obscure chapter in the history of Abydos.  The first  is a statue in the Metropolitan Museum of Art (MMA 1996.91) belonging to a prominent Egyptian general from the Thirtieth Dynasty.  This object includes a difficult autobiographical inscription text in which the owner narrates how he defended Egypt from invading Persian armies and restored massive damage inflicted upon Abydos. At Sohag, meanwhile, the church of St. Shenoute at the White Monastery (c.450 AD) incorporates Pharaonic and Graeco-Roman spolia reused from earlier monuments.  The Yale White Monastery Church Documentation Project (2007-2009) recorded over twenty granite blocks from the reign of Amasis, and the decoration indicates they derive from the Osiris temple at Abydos.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The archaeological and epigraphic record suggests the Osiris temple was badly damaged - if not completely destroyed - during the period of Achaemenid rule in Egypt.  Similar accounts of Persian looting are attested at multiple Egyptian sites, but they are often dismissed as mere propaganda intended to legitimize the subsequent Ptolemaic dynasty.  The case of Abydos leads us to reevaluate our assumptions concerning the religious policies of the Great Kings of Persia.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Date: Tuesday, October 20th&lt;br&gt;Time: 6:00pm&lt;br&gt;Location: Lecture Hall&lt;br&gt;The Institute for the Study of the Ancient World&lt;br&gt;15 East 84th St.&lt;br&gt;New York, NY  10028&lt;br&gt;212-992-7843&lt;br&gt;isaw@nyu.edu&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;*This event is free and open to the public &lt;/i&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>isawevents</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/david-klotz-temple-of-osiris-in-abydos/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2009 02:38:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>David Taylor:  A Greek-speaking Eastern Roman Empire?</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/david-taylor-greek-speaking-eastern/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;A Greek-speaking Eastern Roman Empire? The View from New York&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;presented by&lt;br&gt;David Taylor, &lt;br&gt;Visiting Research Scholar&lt;br&gt;    &lt;br&gt;2009-2010 Visiting Research Scholar Lecture Series&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/"&gt;Institute for the Study of the Ancient World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Tuesday, 6:00 pm&lt;br&gt;October 6th, 2009&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Lecture Hall&lt;br&gt;ISAW Building&lt;br&gt;15 East 84th Street&lt;br&gt;New York, NY 10028&lt;br&gt;212.992.7818&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*This lecture is free and open to the public&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The overwhelming majority of the surviving epigraphic texts of the Late Antique Roman provinces of Syria and Mesopotamia are written in Greek, and in a number of recent books and articles it has been argued that Greek was in fact the ordinary daily language of the local populations. By examining examples of the full available range of ancient linguistic evidence, and drawing on sociolinguistic theory about multilingualism and diglossia, this thesis will be challenged, and a more complex pattern of language usage will be sketched out. The consequences of this for issues of local identity and culture will then be explored.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;David Taylor is the University Lecturer in Aramaic and Syriac at the University of Oxford, and during 2009-2010 he is a Visiting Research Scholar at the Institute for the Study of the Ancient World, NYU.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The next lecture of the series will be given by David Klotz on October 20th.</description><category>epigraphy</category><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>isawevents</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/10/david-taylor-greek-speaking-eastern/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2009 19:24:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Conference this weekend: The Sarcophagus East and West</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/09/conference-this-weekend-sarcophagus/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;b&gt;October 2-3, 2009&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/"&gt;The Institute for the Study of the Ancient World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;15 E. 84th Street&lt;br&gt;New York, NY 10028&lt;br&gt;(212) 992-7800&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;RSVP: &lt;a href="mailto:isaw@nyu.edu"&gt;isaw@nyu.edu&lt;/a&gt; (please indicate day(s) attending)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This conference, organized by Wu Hung and Jas' Elsner, focuses mainly on decorated stone sarcophagi from around the second century BCE to the third century CE, when this type of burial equipment not only continued to develop in the parts of Europe dominated by the Roman Empire, but also enjoyed considerable popularity in East Asia. Whereas the chronological and formal developments of each regional tradition remain an important research goal, this conference encourages comparative observations and interpretations of ancient sarcophagi in broader geo-cultural spheres and more specific ritual/religious contexts. It is hoped that by addressing these two research objectives simultaneously, this conference will help open new ways to think about the development of art and visual culture in a broadly defined ancient world, where the art historical materials available are subject to comparable methodological constraints both from archaeological excavation and from known literary and historical contexts.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;This event is free and open to the public, please RSVP.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: large;"&gt;Program&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Friday, October 2, 2009&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;9:00 Opening remarks: Roger Bagnall (Director of ISAW)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Panel 1   Chair: Roger Bagnall&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;9:20 Introductory Lecture 1&lt;br&gt;    Wu Hung (University of Chicago) - “Consistency and Variations in Han Sarcophagi”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;10:00 Introductory Lecture 2:&lt;br&gt;    Jas Elsner (Oxford University) - “Rhetoric in Pagan and Christian Sarcophagi”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;10:40   Coffee Served in Oak Library&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Panel 2   Chair: Jonathan Hay (IFA, New York University)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;11:10 Paul Zanker (Scuole Normale Superiore di Pisa) - “Understanding Images Without Texts”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;11:50 Alain Thote (Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes) - “The Chinese coffins from the first millennium BC and the early images of the after world”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;12:30   Lunch Break&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Panel 3   Chair: T. J. Clark (U.C. Berkeley)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;2:15 Richard Neer (University of Chicago) - "The Polyxena Sarcophagus from Ilion"&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;3:00 Eugene Wang (Harvard University) - “The Jouissance of Death: Mapping the Bodily Cosmos on Chinese Sarcophagi”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;3: 40 Tea Served in Oak Library&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Panel 4   Chair: Wu Hung&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;4:10  Discussion: Barry Flood (IFA, New York University)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;4:40  Discussion: Chris Hallett (U. C. Berkeley)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;5:10  Open floor discussion&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;6:00   Reception&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;***&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Saturday, October 3, 2009&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Panel 5   Chair: Barry Flood&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;9:00 Verity Platt (University of Chicago) - "Horror Vacui: Framing the Dead on Roman Sarcophagi"&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;9:40 Zheng Yan (Central Academy of Fine Arts, Beijing) - “Sarcophagus Tombs in Eastern China and the Transformation of Han Funerary Art”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;10:30   Coffee Served in Oak Library&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Panel 6   Chair: Chris Hallett&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;11:00 Janet Huskinson (Open University, UK) – “Roman Strigillated Sarcophagi and 'How Societies Remember'”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;11:40 Bjoern Ewald (University of Toronto) – “Sarcophagi in the Roman World: a Comparative Approach”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;12:30   Lunch Break&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Panel 7   Chair: Jas Elsner&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;2:15 Lillian Tseng (Yale University) - “Funerary Spatiality: Wang Hui’s Sarcophagus in Han China”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;3:00  Edmund Thomas (Durham Center for Roman Culture) – “Inside and Outside: Roman Sarcophagi as Public and Private Monuments”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;3:40   Tea Served in Oak Library&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Panel 8   Chair: Jas Elsner&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;4:10  Discussion: Jonathan Hay&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;4:40 Discussion: T.J. Clark&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;5:10 Open floor discussion &lt;/i&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>isawevents</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/09/conference-this-weekend-sarcophagus/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2009 01:12:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>ISAW Exhibition: Lost World of Old Europe (opens 11 November)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/09/isaw-exhibition-lost-world-of-old/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt; has announced its next exhibition (and associated public programming schedule).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;b&gt;The Lost World of Old Europe: The Danube Valley, 5000-3500 BC&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;November 11, 2009 -April 25, 2010&lt;/i&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Lost World of Old Europe&lt;/i&gt; brings to the United States for the first time more than 160 objects recovered by archaeologists from the graves, towns, and villages of Old Europe, a cycle of related cultures that achieved a precocious peak of sophistication and creativity in what is now southeastern Europe between 5000 and 4000 BC, and then mysteriously collapsed by 3500 BC. Long before Egypt or Mesopotamia rose to an equivalent level of achievement, Old Europe was among the most sophisticated places that humans inhabited. Some of its towns grew to city-like sizes. Potters developed striking designs, and the ubiquitous goddess figurines found in houses and shrines have triggered intense debates about women’s roles in Old European society. Old European copper-smiths were, in their day, the most advanced metal artisans in the world. Their intense interest in acquiring copper, gold, Aegean shells, and other rare valuables created networks of negotiation that reached surprisingly far, permitting some of their chiefs to be buried with pounds of gold and copper in funerals without parallel in the Near East or Egypt at the time. The exhibition, arranged through loan agreements with 20 museums in three countries (Romania, The Republic of Bulgaria and the Republic of Moldova), brings the exuberant art, enigmatic ‘goddess’ cults, and precocious metal ornaments and weapons of Old Europe to American audiences. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;Get complete information and schedule at &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions.htm"&gt;http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions.htm&lt;/a&gt;. Other ISAW-sponsored events at &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/events.htm"&gt;http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/events.htm&lt;/a&gt;.</description><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>isawevents</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/09/isaw-exhibition-lost-world-of-old/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2009 23:43:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bagnall on Amheida Excavations (NYC, 17 June 2009)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/06/bagnall-on-amheida-excavations-nyc-17/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.arce.org/"&gt;American Research Center in Egypt&lt;/a&gt; Presents:&lt;br&gt;Roger Bagnall&lt;br&gt;NYU Excavations at Amheida&lt;br&gt;Date: Wednesday, June 17th&lt;br&gt;Time: 6:00 pm&lt;br&gt;Location: &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/"&gt;Institute for the Study of the Ancient World&lt;/a&gt;, 15 E 84th St., New York, NY 10028, Second Floor Lecture Room&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Amheida is a vast archaeological site on the western edge of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dakhla_Oasis"&gt;Dakhla Oasis&lt;/a&gt; in Egypt. A team of researchers led by &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/people-bagnall_cv.htm"&gt;Dr. Roger Bagnall&lt;/a&gt;, Director of the Institute for the Study of the Ancient World at NYU, began the &lt;a href="http://www.amheida.org/"&gt;Amheida Project&lt;/a&gt; in 2001 with an intensive investigation and survey of the site.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One of the most spectacular discoveries, near the center of the town in Area 2, is the house of Serenus, who was part of the city council in the middle of the 4th century. The structure contains fifteen rooms, one of which was painted with classical wall scenes. On the northern wall, to the left of the doorway, a mythological scene depicts the legend of Perseus rescuing the beautiful Andromeda who is about to be devoured by a sea-monster, while to the right of the door is the Homeric scene of the Return of Odysseus to Ithaca, from his long voyage which brought him to Egyptian shores.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The site at Amheida will be part of a long-term scheme for the Dakhla Oasis Project. Please join us for a presentation and discussion on Amheida and its archaeological significance.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This lecture is free and open to the public, but please be sure to RSVP to &lt;a href="mailto:isaw@nyu.edu?subject=%27RSVP%20for%20Bagnall%20Amheida%20presentation%22"&gt;isaw@nyu.edu&lt;/a&gt;. For more information on the lecture and other ISAW events, please visit: &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/events.htm"&gt;http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/events.htm&lt;/a&gt;. You may also contact the ISAW events office directly at 212.992.7818. For press inquiries, please contact Suzan Toma at &lt;a href="mailto:suzan.toma@nyu.edu?subject='press%20inquiry:%20Bagnall/Amheida'"&gt;suzan.toma@nyu.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>isawevents</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/06/bagnall-on-amheida-excavations-nyc-17/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2009 23:33:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>