<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about jobs)</title><link>http://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://paregorios.org/categories/jobs.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:paregorios@hotmail.com"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 23:11:11 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Job: Senior Digital Humanities Web Developer/Architect</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2013/08/job-senior-digital-humanities-web/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Reblogged from &lt;a href="https://isaw.nyu.edu/jobs/available-staff-positions/"&gt;https://isaw.nyu.edu/jobs/available-staff-positions/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;In order to shape and secure the future of innovative teaching and research at ISAW and beyond, we work with others to nurture new and important open information resources for the ancient world, especially those that connect and contextualize information across institutional, methodological, and technological divides. Accordingly, our Senior Digital Humanities Web Developer/Architects envision, create, and curate web applications that bridge gaps in content and function while handling the diversity of languages, scripts, geography, chronology, and methodology inherent in the study of the past-oriented humanities. You carry out this mission in constant, productive collaboration with scholars, students, and enthusiasts from both inside and outside the Institute, empowering them as co-creators, curators, and users.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;Position description and application instructions may be found online at: &lt;a href="http://www.nyucareers.com/applicants/Central?quickFind=57339"&gt;http://www.nyucareers.com/applicants/Central?quickFind=57339&lt;/a&gt;</description><category>dh</category><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>jobs</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2013/08/job-senior-digital-humanities-web/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2013 02:52:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The DH Stack(s)</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/10/dh-stacks/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Lots of interesting posts in the last couple of days about Digital Humanities skills, software and cyberinfrastructure initiatives:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sean issues some &lt;a href="http://sgillies.net/blog/819/second-guessing-project-bamboo/"&gt;service-oriented caveats for Project Bamboo&lt;/a&gt; and thinks about skillsets for DH-ready graduates&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://digitalscholarship.wordpress.com/2008/10/18/digital-humanities-jobs/"&gt;Lisa surveys recent DH job postings&lt;/a&gt;, muses on DH 'fieldness' and visits the aspiring digital humanist's skillset too&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://digitalhistoryhacks.blogspot.com/"&gt;Bill T.'s whole blog&lt;/a&gt; remains essential reading in this meme-space (e.g., see his recent "&lt;a href="http://digitalhistoryhacks.blogspot.com/2008/10/navigating-digital-history.html"&gt;Navigating Digital History&lt;/a&gt;")&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Liza provides an example of &lt;a href="http://blog.threepress.org/2008/10/14/corpus-toneelkritiek-interbellum/"&gt;TEI+Python+lxml in publishing primary sources online&lt;/a&gt; (the same general stack the Duke/Heidelberg/King's/Columbia/UNC/NYU team has been using in the rework of the Duke Databank of Documentary Papyri and Heidelberger Gesamtverzeichniss -- coming soon)&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>bamboo</category><category>blogs</category><category>digclass</category><category>horothesia</category><category>jobs</category><category>patterns</category><category>tei</category><category>tools</category><category>uptake</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/10/dh-stacks/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2008 19:52:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>"A New Low in the Exploitation of Adjunct Faculty"?</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/new-low-in-exploitation-of-adjunct/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The above quote is attributed to Gwendolyn Bradley, of the American Association of University Professors, in this morning's issue of &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Inside Higher Education&lt;/span&gt; where Scott Jaschik writes about a "&lt;a href="http://insidehighered.com/news/2008/09/11/adjunct"&gt;New Form of Adjunct Abuse&lt;/a&gt;":&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;At San Antonio College ... adjuncts are being encouraged to take on extra courses, ... [but] the college is asking some part timers ... to agree in writing to pretend that they aren’t teaching 12 credits. ...&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Gerald J. Davey, an adjunct at San Antonio College who has served as the adjunct representative on the Faculty Council there, did not sign a waiver, but he has spoken with those who have and is angry about the system being used. Davey said that, in years past, once an adjunct has had a contract for 12 credits, benefits and higher pay scales have kicked in — and that the waivers are an attempt to limit what adjuncts receive from the college.&lt;/blockquote&gt;Aside:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I can't help but draw attention to this most unfortunate of "context-sensitive" advertisements that appeared alongside Jaschik's story:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/SMkgiHp7IPI/AAAAAAAAABQ/XlryJ1sge50/s1600-h/adjunctabuse.jpg"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0pt 10px 10px 0pt; float: none; cursor: pointer;" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/SMkgiHp7IPI/AAAAAAAAABQ/XlryJ1sge50/s320/adjunctabuse.jpg" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5244759011592184050" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>jobs</category><category>mores</category><category>tempora</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/new-low-in-exploitation-of-adjunct/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2008 19:24:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Get Paid to Read Greek!</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/08/get-paid-to-read-greek/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;From Greg Crane:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Contribute to the Greek and Latin &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treebank"&gt;Treebanks&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We are currently looking for advanced students of Greek and Latin to contribute syntactic analyses (via a web-based system) to our existing Latin Treebank (described below) and our emerging Greek Treebank as well (for which we have just received funding). We particularly encourage students at various levels to design research projects around this new tool. We are looking in particular for the following:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get paid to read Greek! We can have a limited number of research assistantships for advanced students of the languages who can work for the project from their home institutions. We particularly encourage students who can use the analyses that they produce to support research projects of their own.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;We also encourage classes of Greek and Latin to contribute as well. Creating the syntactic analyses provides a new way to address the traditional task of parsing Greek and Latin. Your class work can then contribute to a foundational new resource for the study of Greek and Latin - both courses as a whole and individual contributors are acknowledged in the published data.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Students and faculty interested in conducting their own original research based on treebank data will have the option to submit their work for editorial review to have it published as part of the emerging Scaife Digital Library.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;To contribute, please contact David Bamman (&lt;a href="mailto:david.bamman@tufts.edu"&gt;david.bamman@tufts.edu&lt;/a&gt;) or Gregory Crane (&lt;a href="mailto:gregory.crane@tufts.edu"&gt;gregory.crane@tufts.edu&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For more information, see &lt;a href="http://nlp.perseus.tufts.edu/syntax/treebank/"&gt;http://nlp.perseus.tufts.edu/syntax/treebank/&lt;/a&gt;.</description><category>digclass</category><category>horothesia</category><category>jobs</category><category>nlp</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/08/get-paid-to-read-greek/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2008 18:07:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>NYU Programming Job: Papyrological Navigator</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/08/nyu-programming-job-papyrological/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;New York University: Programmer/Analyst (7421BR)&lt;/p&gt;        &lt;p&gt;New York University’s Division of the Libraries seeks a Programmer/Analyst to work on the           "Papyrological Navigator" (&lt;a href="http://papyri.info/"&gt;http://papyri.info&lt;/a&gt;), a major           web-based research portal that provides scholars worldwide with access to texts,           transcriptions, images and metadata related to ancient texts on papyri, pottery           fragments and other material. The incumbent will work closely with the Project           Coordinator (at Columbia University) and with scholars involved in the project at NYU's           Institute for the Study of the Ancient World, Duke University and the University of           Heidelberg, as well as with NYU Digital Library Technology staff.&lt;/p&gt;        &lt;p&gt;The incumbent's initial responsibilities will include: migrating existing PN software           applications from Columbia University to NYU; optimizing performance as needed;           establishing a robust production environment at NYU for the ongoing ingest and           processing of new and updated Greek text transcriptions, metadata and digital images;           performing both analysis and programming of any required changes or enhancements to           current PN applications.&lt;/p&gt;        &lt;p&gt;This is a grant-funded position and is available for 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;        &lt;p&gt;Candidates should have the following skills:           &lt;/p&gt;        &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bachelor's degree in computer or information science and 3 years of relevant               experience or equivalent combination&lt;/li&gt;            &lt;li&gt;Must include experience developing applications using Java&lt;/li&gt;            &lt;li&gt;Demonstrated knowledge of Java, Tomcat, Saxon, Lucene, Apache, SQL, XML, XSLT&lt;/li&gt;            &lt;li&gt;Experience with metadata standards (e.g. &lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/"&gt;TEI&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://epidoc.sourceforge.net/"&gt;EpiDoc&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;            &lt;li&gt;Experience working in a Unix/Linux environments&lt;/li&gt;            &lt;li&gt;Preferred: Experience with image serving software (eRez/FSI), Java Portlets, Apache               Jetspeed-2, and Velocity templates.&lt;/li&gt;            &lt;li&gt;Preferred: Experience designing, building, and deploying distributed systems.&lt;/li&gt;            &lt;li&gt;Preferred: Experience working with non-Roman Unicode-based textual data (esp. Greek)&lt;/li&gt;            &lt;li&gt;Excellent communication and analytical skills&lt;/li&gt;        &lt;/ul&gt;        &lt;p&gt;Applicants should submit resume and cover letter, which reflects how applicant’s           education and experience match the job requirements.&lt;/p&gt;        &lt;p&gt;Please apply through NYU's application management system: &lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/hr/jobs/apply"&gt;www.nyu.edu/hr/jobs/apply&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;        &lt;p&gt;At this page click on "External Applicants" then "Search Openings." Type 7421BR in the           "Keyword Search" field and select search. NYU offers a generous benefit package           including 22 days of vacation annually. NYU is an Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action           Employer.&lt;/p&gt;        &lt;p&gt;New York University Libraries: Library facilities at New York University serve the           school’s 40,000 students and faculty and contain more than 4 million volumes. New York           University is a member of the Association of Research Libraries, the Research Libraries           Group, the Digital Library Federation; serves as the administrative headquarters of the           Research Library Association of South Manhattan, a consortium that includes three           academic institutions. The Library’s website URL is &lt;a href="http://library.nyu.edu/"&gt;http://library.nyu.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>epidoc</category><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>jobs</category><category>papyrology</category><category>tei</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/08/nyu-programming-job-papyrological/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2008 22:43:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>