<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about politics)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://paregorios.org/categories/politics.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:ipse@paregorios.org"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;&lt;img
alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
property="dct:title"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;paregorios.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by
&lt;a xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" href="https://paregorios.org/me"
property="cc:attributionName" rel="cc:attributionURL"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; is
licensed under a &lt;a rel="license"
href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2018 15:51:14 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>What Would TS/SCI Jesus do?</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/what-would-tssci-jesus-do/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm outraged. When I started this blog, I vowed to myself to confine its scope to my professional work and to local matters where I live. But I can't let this pass:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;In sum, our investigation concluded that [former U.S. Attorney General Alberto] Gonzales mishandled classified materials regarding two highly sensitive compartmented programs. We found that Gonzales took his classified handwritten notes home and stored them there for an indeterminate period of time. The notes contained operational aspects and other information about the NSA surveillance program that is classified at the TS/SCI level. By regulation, such material must be stored in a Sensitive Compartmented Storage Facility (SCIF). At the time he took these materials home, Gonzales did not have a SCIF at his house. Although Gonzales did have a safe at his residence at this time, we found that he did not use it to store the notes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We also found that Gonzales improperly stored other highly classified documents about the two compartmented programs in a safe at the Department that was not located in a SCIF. Several employees in the OAG had access to the safe where Gonzales stored the documents even though they lacked the necessary security clearances for this information. We concluded that Gonzales’s mishandling of both the notes and the other classified documents violated Department security requirements and procedures.&lt;/blockquote&gt;You can read the nauseating details via various liberal, elite gay-married terrorist media outlets:&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Carrie Johnson, "&lt;a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/09/02/AR2008090201029.html"&gt;Report: Gonzales Mishandled Classified Data&lt;/a&gt;," Washington Post (2 September 2008)&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Associated Press, via the New York Times: "&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/aponline/washington/AP-Gonzales-Security-Breach.html"&gt;Report Faults Gonzales on Data&lt;/a&gt;" (2 September 2008 -- now that's a soft-pedal title, isn't it?)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Terry Frieden, "&lt;a href="http://www.cnn.com/2008/POLITICS/09/02/gonzales.documents/"&gt;Report: Ex-AG Won't be Charged for Mishandling Secret Papers&lt;/a&gt;" CNN (2 September 2008 -- includes a link to PDF of the DOJ Inspector General's report, whence the quote above)&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;I'll skip most of the rest of the ranting and just say this. There are plenty of folks over the years -- hardworking, well-meaning, patriotic folks in government service, the military and working for defense contractors -- who've been investigated, counseled, sanctioned, disciplined, busted, fired and even confined for &lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;accidentally&lt;/span&gt; mishandling classified information at levels far lower than TS/SCI.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And the Department of Justice decides not to seek prosecution for a man who was too busy (or something) to properly safeguard this stuff according to well-established procedures?</description><category>horothesia</category><category>politics</category><category>rants</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/what-would-tssci-jesus-do/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2008 23:18:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>