<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about potamos)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://paregorios.org/categories/potamos.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:ipse@paregorios.org"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;&lt;img
alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
property="dct:title"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;paregorios.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by
&lt;a xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" href="https://paregorios.org/me"
property="cc:attributionName" rel="cc:attributionURL"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; is
licensed under a &lt;a rel="license"
href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 May 2018 11:48:17 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>It is happening</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2013/06/it-is-happening/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of hours ago, I was sitting out on the back deck with my wife and pets, enjoying perfect temperatures, morning birdsong, lavender-scented country air, and a cup of freshly brewed Costa Rican coffee (roasted by the good folks at the &lt;a href="http://www.kaffeeklatsch.com/"&gt;Kaffeeklatsch in Huntsville&lt;/a&gt;). Idyllic.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I was flipping through the latest news stories, blog posts, and such, brought into my phone by my feed reader (currently &lt;a href="http://www.feedly.com/"&gt;Feedly&lt;/a&gt;). I was trying to ignore the omnipresent bad news of the world, when this popped up:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-nVdEMdCeLVk/UcMIk-L73AI/AAAAAAAAAbE/PtNieGzjwxU/s1600/Screenshot_2013-06-20-08-47-12.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="screen capture of a feed summary in Feedly on my Android phone" border="0" height="400" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-nVdEMdCeLVk/UcMIk-L73AI/AAAAAAAAAbE/PtNieGzjwxU/s400/Screenshot_2013-06-20-08-47-12.png" title="feed summaries in Feedly on my Android phone" width="225"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Forma[m] Lollianus fecit?!?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; I'm predisposed by &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/demarc"&gt;my dissertation experience&lt;/a&gt; to trigger on certain Latin and Greek words because of their sometime significance for the study of Roman geography. &lt;i&gt;Forma&lt;/i&gt; is of course one of those words, and it does (probably more often than justified) get translated as "map" or "plan." Could this be — admittedly against the odds —an inscription on a map or plan drafted or surveyed by some guy named Lollianus?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If you're me, the possibility warrants &lt;a href="http://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/edh/inschrift/HD017773"&gt;a click-through&lt;/a&gt; to a corresponding record in the &lt;i&gt;Heidelberg Epigraphic Databank (EDH)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;My mappish hopes were quickly dashed, but just as quickly were replaced by interest in a group of inscribed objects I hadn't run across before: mirrors from Roman Dacia bearing makers' inscriptions. "&lt;i&gt;Forma&lt;/i&gt;" can mean "mirror"? &lt;a href="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0059%3Aentry%3Dforma"&gt;A quick check of &lt;i&gt;Lewis &amp;amp; Short&lt;/i&gt; at &lt;i&gt;Perseus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; doesn't support that idea, but builds confidence in a better interpretation: "mold, stamp, form". Was this mirror, or some part of it, somehow cast or stamped out? The EDH entry tells me there are 9 identical mirrors extant and that the inscription goes around the "&lt;i&gt;Fassung&lt;/i&gt;" (frame?). Yup.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Cool. I learned something today before breakfast. And it's knowledge I can use when I come back to doing more with the geographical/mapping/surveying vocabulary.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And then it hits me: that's not information I went looking for, not a search I initiated. New information of interest was &lt;b&gt;pushed&lt;/b&gt; to me because I had previously used a software tool to express interest in a number of information sources including, but not limited to, ancient inscriptions. The software kept an eye on new output from those sources and made it available to me for review and engagement in a mode and at a time and place of my choosing. And because the source data was online, open, and linked in a standard format, I was able to drink coffee and pet my dog on the back deck in Moontown, Alabama while making use of the scholarly work done yesterday(!) by Brigitte Gräf in Heidelberg, Germany.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Isn't this one of the &lt;a href="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/index.html"&gt;things we've been working toward&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;h3&gt;How did that happen?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br&gt;Sometime earlier this year, Frank Grieshaber in Heidelberg rolled out web page listings and corresponding &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atom_%28standard%29"&gt;Atom feeds&lt;/a&gt; of recently changed content in the EDH (e.g., &lt;a href="http://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/inschrift/lastUpdates"&gt;latest updates to the inscriptions database&lt;/a&gt;). I added them, along with similar data-oriented feeds, to a feed aggregator I dubbed &lt;a href="http://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/inschrift/lastUpdates"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Planet Potamos&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (with "Potamos" trying lamely to evoke a rushing river of data; the "Planet" acknowledges &lt;a href="http://www.planetplanet.org/"&gt;the feed aggregation software I use&lt;/a&gt;). I put the same feed subscriptions into my personal feed reader (I could also have put the &lt;i&gt;Potamos&lt;/i&gt; aggregator's feed, but it only updates periodically and I'm an immediacy junkie). I installed and configured my feed reader on every device I use.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The rest is magic. Magic made the old-fashioned way by lots of people in many different places and times developing standards, building software, creating data, doing research, and sharing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;h3&gt;What next?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br&gt;Well, I hope that Frank and his colleagues in Heidelberg will eventually add thumbnail images (where they have them) to the EDH feeds. I hope that the other epigraphic databases (and indeed all kinds of ancient studies web applications) will set up similar feeds. I hope that we can all start using more linked-data approaches in and alongside such feeds in order to communicate seminal interpretive/discovery facets (like geography, personography, temporality and genre) in machine-actionable ways. I hope the spirit and practice of openness that lubricates and accelerates this sort of synergy continues to grow and flower.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As for me, I'm thinking about how I might set up some kind of filtering mechanism that would highlight or prioritize content in my feed reader that's potentially relevant to my (e.g.) geo/map/survey vocabulary interests. Hmmmmm....&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</description><category>atlantis</category><category>collaboration</category><category>data</category><category>demarc</category><category>feeds</category><category>horothesia</category><category>inscriptions</category><category>interop</category><category>linkeddata</category><category>LOD</category><category>openness</category><category>perseus</category><category>potamos</category><category>tools</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2013/06/it-is-happening/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2013 20:54:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New in Potamos: New Testament Virtual Manuscript Room</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2013/03/new-in-potamos-new-testament-virtual/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I've just added to the &lt;a href="http://planet.atlantides.org/potamos/"&gt;Potamos Atlantis feed aggregator&lt;/a&gt; the "&lt;a href="http://ntvmr.uni-muenster.de/community/vmr/api/statistics/recentedits/rss/"&gt;Recent Additions feed&lt;/a&gt;" from the &lt;a href="http://ntvmr.uni-muenster.de/home"&gt;New Testament Virtual Manuscript Room of the Münster Institut für Neutestamentliche Textforschung&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>atlantis</category><category>data</category><category>feeds</category><category>horothesia</category><category>potamos</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2013/03/new-in-potamos-new-testament-virtual/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 23:38:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New in Potamos: tDAR</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2013/03/new-in-potamos-tdar/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I've just added the &lt;a href="http://core.tdar.org/search/rss?query="&gt;update feed&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://www.tdar.org/"&gt;The Digital Archaeological Record (tDar)&lt;/a&gt; to the&lt;a href="http://planet.atlantides.org/potamos/"&gt; Potamos Atlantis feed aggregator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>atlantis</category><category>data</category><category>feeds</category><category>horothesia</category><category>potamos</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2013/03/new-in-potamos-tdar/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 00:40:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New in Potamos</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2013/03/new-in-potamos/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I have added the following data feeds to the &lt;a href="http://planet.atlantides.org/potamos/"&gt;Potamos Atlantis feed aggregator&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://numismatics.org/search/"&gt;American Numismatic Society database&lt;/a&gt; (Greek, Roman, and Byzantine departments)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://numismatics.org/ocre/"&gt;Online Coins of the Roman Empire&lt;/a&gt; (OCRE)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://opencontext.org/"&gt;OpenContext&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>atlantis</category><category>data</category><category>feeds</category><category>horothesia</category><category>potamos</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2013/03/new-in-potamos/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2013 03:17:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>