<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about rights)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://paregorios.org/categories/rights.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:paregorios@hotmail.com"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 16:22:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Ancient Studies Needs Open Bibliographic Data and Associated URIs</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2012/06/ancient-studies-needs-open/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;Update 1:  links throughout, minor formatting changes, proper Creative Commons Public Domain tools, parenthetical about import path from Endnote and such, fixing a few typos.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.neh.gov/"&gt;NEH&lt;/a&gt;-funded &lt;a href="http://wiki.digitalclassicist.org/Linked_Ancient_World_Data_Institute"&gt;Linked Ancient World Data Institute&lt;/a&gt;, still in progress at &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt;, has got me thinking about a number of things. One of them is bibliography and linked data. Here's a brain dump, intended to spark conversation and collaboration.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;What We Need&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;As much bibliographic data as possible, for both primary and secondary sources (print and digital), publicly released to third parties under either a public domain declaration or an unrestrictive open license.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Stable HTTP &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_resource_identifier"&gt;URIs&lt;/a&gt; for every work and author included in those datasets.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Why&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Bibliographic and citation collection and management are integral to every research and publication in project in ancient studies. We could save each other a lot of time, and get more substantive work done in the field, if it was simpler and easier to do. We could more easily and effectively tie together disparate work published on the web (and appearing on the web through retrospective digitization) if we had a common infrastructure and shared point of reference. There's already a lot of digital data in various hands that could support such an effort, but a good chunk of it is not out where anybody with good will and talent can get at it to improve it, build tools around it, etc.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;What I Want You (and Me) To Do If You Have Bibliographic Data&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Release it to the world through a third party. No matter what format it's in, give a copy to someone else whose function is hosting free data on the web. Dump it into a public repository at &lt;a href="http://github.com/"&gt;github.com&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://sourceforge.net/"&gt;sourceforge.net&lt;/a&gt;. Put it into a shared library at &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/"&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.bibsonomy.org/"&gt;Bibsonomy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.mendeley.com/"&gt;Mendeley&lt;/a&gt;, or another bibliographic content website (most have easy upload/import paths from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EndNote"&gt;Endnote&lt;/a&gt;, and other citation management applications). Hosting a copy yourself is fine, but giving it to a third party demonstrates your bona fides, gets it out of your nifty but restrictive search engine or database, and increments your bus number.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Release it under a Creative Commons &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/about/pdm"&gt;Public Domain Mark&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/about/cc0"&gt;Public Domain Dedication (CC0)&lt;/a&gt;.  Or if you can't do that, find as open a &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/"&gt;Creative Commons&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_content#Licenses"&gt;similar license&lt;/a&gt; as you can. Don't try to control it. If there's some aspect of the data that you can't (because of rights encumberance) or don't want to (why?) give away to make the world a better place, find a quick way to extract, filter, or excerpt that aspect and get the rest out.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Alert the world to your philanthropy. Blog or tweet about it. Post a link to the data on your institutional website. Above all, alert &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/people/staff/chuck-jones"&gt;Chuck Jones&lt;/a&gt; and Phoebe Acheson so it gets announced via &lt;a href="http://ancientworldonline.blogspot.com/"&gt;Ancient World Online&lt;/a&gt; and/or &lt;a href="http://ancientbiblio.wordpress.com/"&gt;Ancient World Open Bibliographies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do the same if you have other useful data, like identifiers for modern or ancient works or authors.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get in touch with me and/or anyone else to talk about the next step: setting up stable HTTP URIs corresponding to this stuff.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;b&gt;Who I'm Talking To&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;First of all, I'm talking to myself, my collaborators, and my team-mates at ISAW. I intend to eat my own dogfood.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here are other institutions and entities I know about who have potentially useful data.&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="http://openlibrary.org/"&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt; : data about books is already out there and available, and there are ways to add more&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/"&gt;Perseus Project&lt;/a&gt; : a huge, FRBR-ized collection of MODS records for Greek and Latin authors, works, and modern editions thereof.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://chs.harvard.edu/chs"&gt;Center for Hellenic Studies&lt;/a&gt;: identifiers for Greek and Latin authors and works&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.annee-philologique.com/"&gt;L'Année Philologique&lt;/a&gt; and its institutional partners like the &lt;a href="http://www.apaclassics.org/"&gt;American Philological Association&lt;/a&gt;: the big collection of analytic secondary bibliography for classics (journal articles)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://projects.chass.utoronto.ca/amphoras/tocs.html"&gt;TOCS-IN&lt;/a&gt;: a collaboratively collected batch of analytic secondary bibliography for classics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://papyri.info/"&gt;Papyri.info&lt;/a&gt; and its contributing project partners: TEI bibliographic records for  much of the bibliography produced for or cited by Greek and Latin papyrologists (plus other ancient language/script traditions in papyrology)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gnomon-online.de/"&gt;Gnomon Bibliographische Datenbank&lt;/a&gt;: masses of bibliographic data for books and articles for classics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Any and every university library system that has a dedicated or easily extracted set of associated catalog records. Especially any with unique collections (e.g., Cincinnati) or those with databases of analytical bibliography down to the level of articles in journals and collections.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ditto any and every ancient studies digital project that has bibliographic data in a database.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Comments, Reactions, Suggestions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Welcome, encouraged, and essential. By comment here or otherwise (but not private email please!).&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>backstop</category><category>bibliography</category><category>books</category><category>boundaries</category><category>collaboration</category><category>concordia</category><category>digclass</category><category>horothesia</category><category>interop</category><category>isaw</category><category>lawdi</category><category>linkeddata</category><category>openness</category><category>rights</category><category>walled gardens</category><category>zotero</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2012/06/ancient-studies-needs-open/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2012 19:03:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Digital Projects (ISAW Newsletter January 2008)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/digital-projects-isaw-newsletter/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Since the &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2009/01/isaw-newsletter-january-2008.html"&gt;ISAW Newsletter&lt;/a&gt; is only available online as a monolithic PDF, I thought I'd make the text of my contribution (about our "digital programs") available here in HTML form:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;ISAW’s digital programs are fundamental to the Institute’s mission. Convinced that the transformation of the media and information landscape now underway offers scholars unparalleled opportunities to make new discoveries, collaborate with distant colleagues, engage public interests, and tackle previously intractable problems, we have committed ourselves to an ambitious slate of digital initiatives that extend far beyond the walls of the Institute. As the examples below illustrate, we emphasize the creation and delivery of core resources such as primary and secondary texts and images, as well as geographic and archaeological reference information. We seek to serve the entire field of ancient studies by working for the durability of digital publications–and the sustainability of the projects that create and maintain them–through promotion of standards, creation of reusable free software, use of open-access licenses, and decentralization of authorial, editorial, and peer-review activities.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In early 2008, ISAW became a partner in the &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;Pleiades Project&lt;/a&gt;. Together with the &lt;a href="http://www.unc.edu/awmc/"&gt;Ancient World Mapping Center&lt;/a&gt; (AWMC), we are digitizing the most comprehensive register of geographical data for the ancient Greek and Roman world, collected by the &lt;a href="http://www.apaclassics.org/"&gt;American Philological Association&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href="http://www.unc.edu/depts/cl_atlas/"&gt;Classical Atlas Project&lt;/a&gt; to support the preparation of the &lt;a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/43970336"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Barrington Atlas of the Greek and Roman World&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (R. Talbert, ed., Princeton 2000). All of the coordinates, historical names, and other information in this rich collection are being placed online so scholars, students, and enthusiasts worldwide can browse, search, and map it, as well as offer suggestions for updates and additions. The Pleiades effort has recently expanded with funding from a Transatlantic Digitization Grant, awarded to ISAW and King’s College London, by the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) and the U.K. Joint Information Systems Committee. It supports the prototyping of mechanisms to tie Pleiades into important digital collections of epigraphic and papyrological texts from Egypt and coastal North Africa (see further: the &lt;a href="http://concordia.atlantides.org/"&gt;Concordia Project&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://groups.google.com/group/gawd"&gt;Graph of Ancient World Data&lt;/a&gt; group). This effort will lay the foundation for extensive, automated cross-linking between Pleiades and other web-based scholarly resources for the entire Greek and Roman world. We are currently seeking funding for a second, two-year development period for Pleiades/Concordia that will accelerate the digitization of content and bring users together for a series of workshops to identify needed improvements to the system and to facilitate more effective collaboration.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Over the past year ISAW has also assumed a leadership role in a group of interrelated digital papyrology projects (see &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/"&gt;http://idp.atlantides.org&lt;/a&gt;). One of these, funded by a grant to Duke University from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, has successfully upgraded and effectively integrated two of the key digital resources for study of ancient documents on papyrus: the &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/trac/idp/wiki/DDBDP"&gt;Duke Databank of Documentary Papyri&lt;/a&gt; (DDbDP) and the &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/trac/idp/wiki/HGV"&gt;Heidelberger Gesamtverzeichnis der griechischen Papyrusurkunden Ägyptens&lt;/a&gt; (HGV). Both resources will soon be provided to users via a search and display environment prototyped by the digital libraries team at Columbia University. This system, dubbed the &lt;a href="http://papyri.info/"&gt;Papyrological Navigator&lt;/a&gt;, combines DDbDP and HGV content with images and database records drawn from the 22 museum and university papyrus collections that constitute the &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/trac/idp/wiki/APIS"&gt;Advanced Papyrological Information System&lt;/a&gt; (APIS). It also links them to the extensive &lt;a href="http://www.trismegistos.org/"&gt;Trismegistos&lt;/a&gt; databases in Leuven. Under new funding provided to APIS by the NEH, work on this interface will move to the Digital Libraries team at NYU where, with collaboration from ISAW and APIS team members at Columbia, it will see extensive improvements. ISAW is currently working with partners to secure funding for a second major upgrade to the DDbDP and HGV: a collaborative, online editing environment that will speed the addition and revision of content by granting papyrologists worldwide direct authorial capabilities under a distributed system of editorial oversight.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A number of other exciting projects are in work for 2009 and beyond. We hope to expand the utility of Pleiades by linking it to a number of other systems and digital gazetteers under development at a variety of institutions around the world. Plans are being formulated for a collaborative digital encyclopedia of Coptic archaeology, an extensive database of digital images, an online calendar of museum exhibitions, a major book and journal digitization program, and a multi-institutional publication series comprising open-access primary texts and research data.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>batlas</category><category>concordia</category><category>gawd</category><category>horothesia</category><category>isaw</category><category>papyrology</category><category>pleiades</category><category>rights</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2009/01/digital-projects-isaw-newsletter/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2009 21:33:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Digital Archimedes Palimpsest</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/10/digital-archimedes-palimpsest/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This just in:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Ten years ago today, a private American collector purchased the Archimedes Palimpsest. Since that time he has guided and funded the project to conserve, image, and study the manuscript. After ten years of work, involving the expertise and goodwill of an extraordinary number of people working around the world, the Archimedes Palimpsest Project has released its data. It is a historic dataset, revealing new texts from the ancient world. It is an integrated product, weaving registered images in many wavebands of light with XML transcriptions of the Archimedes and Hyperides texts that are spatially mapped to those images. It has pushed boundaries for the imaging of documents, and relied almost exclusively on current international standards. We hope that this dataset will be a persistent digital resource for the decades to come. We also hope it will be helpful as an example for others who are conducting similar work. It published under a Creative Commons 3.0 attribution license, to ensure ease of access and the potential for widespread use. A complete facsimile of the revealed palimpsested texts is available on Googlebooks as "The Archimedes Palimpsest." It is hoped that this is the first of many uses to which the data will be put.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For information on the Archimedes Palimpsest Project, please visit:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.archimedespalimpsest.org/"&gt;www.archimedespalimpsest.org &lt;/a&gt;&lt;http: org=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For the dataset, please visit:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.archimedespalimpsest.net/"&gt;www.archimedespalimpsest.net &lt;/a&gt;&lt;http: net=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We have set up a discussion forum on the Archimedes Palimpsest Project. Any member can invite anybody else to join. If you want to become a member, please email:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:wnoel@thewalters.org"&gt;wnoel@thewalters.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I would be grateful if you would circulate this to your friends and colleagues.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Thank you very much&lt;br&gt;Will Noel&lt;br&gt;The Walters Art Museum&lt;br&gt;October 29th, 2008.&lt;/http:&gt;&lt;/http:&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;I found it a bit tricky to find the Google Books version of this, so &lt;a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=_zX8OG3QoF4C&amp;amp;pg=PT146&amp;amp;dq=The+Archimedes+Palimpsest&amp;amp;as_brr=1"&gt;here's the link&lt;/a&gt;.</description><category>digclass</category><category>horothesia</category><category>patterns</category><category>publications</category><category>rights</category><category>tei</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/10/digital-archimedes-palimpsest/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2008 22:41:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>More on the Zotero lawsuit</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/more-on-zotero-lawsuit/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="http://www.unc.edu/%7Ehcayless/"&gt;Hugh Cayless&lt;/a&gt;, who originally tweet-alerted me to &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2008/09/reuters-endnote-sues-george-mason-over.html"&gt;the Zotero lawsuit&lt;/a&gt;, now has blogged about it (with some encouraging words for &lt;a href="http://www.dancohen.org/"&gt;Dan Cohen&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://chnm.gmu.edu/"&gt;the GMU team&lt;/a&gt;): "&lt;a href="http://philomousos.blogspot.com/2008/09/go-zotero.html"&gt;Go Zotero!&lt;/a&gt;"</description><category>bibliography</category><category>horothesia</category><category>macinations</category><category>mores</category><category>rights</category><category>tempora</category><category>tools</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/more-on-zotero-lawsuit/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2008 18:34:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Reuters (EndNote) sues George Mason over Zotero</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/reuters-endnote-sues-george-mason-over/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="http://www.courthousenews.com/2008/09/17/Reuters_Says_George_Mason_University_Is_Handing_Out_Its_Proprietary_Software.htm"&gt;By way of the Courthouse News Service&lt;/a&gt; we hear that:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/"&gt;Thomson Reuters&lt;/a&gt; demands $10 million and an injunction to stop George Mason University from distributing its new Web browser application, &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/"&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; ... Reuters claims George Mason is violating its license agreement and destroying the &lt;a href="http://www.endnote.com/"&gt;EndNote&lt;/a&gt; customer base.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>bibliography</category><category>horothesia</category><category>macinations</category><category>mores</category><category>rights</category><category>tempora</category><category>tools</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/reuters-endnote-sues-george-mason-over/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2008 01:17:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Copyright and artifacts</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/copyright-and-artifacts/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Kevin Smith's "&lt;a href="http://library.duke.edu/blogs/scholcomm/2008/09/06/grecian-urn/"&gt;Copyright use case on a Grecian urn&lt;/a&gt;," &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Scholarly Communications @ Duke&lt;/span&gt; (6 September 2008) is worth a read. One highlight:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;owning an object in the public domain, like a classical vase, does not create any intellectual property rights.  Simply by owning and displaying the vase the museum does not gain a copyright interest where there was no such interest before&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>rights</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/copyright-and-artifacts/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2008 19:38:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>