<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about rockets)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://paregorios.org/categories/rockets.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:ipse@paregorios.org"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;&lt;img
alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
property="dct:title"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;paregorios.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by
&lt;a xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" href="https://paregorios.org/me"
property="cc:attributionName" rel="cc:attributionURL"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; is
licensed under a &lt;a rel="license"
href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 May 2018 11:48:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Sarah Parcak on Egypt in Huntsville, September 17</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/sarah-parcak-on-egypt-in-huntsville/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The North Alabama Society of the Archaeological Institute of America is hosting Dr. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarah_Parcak"&gt;Sarah Parcak &lt;/a&gt;for two talks next Wednesday:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Women and Power in Antiquity: A New Kingdom Case Study from Deir el-Medina, Thebes, 2:20 p.m. in &lt;a href="http://www.uah.edu/map/buildings/roberts.php"&gt;Roberts&lt;/a&gt; 419 on the &lt;a href="http://www.uah.edu/"&gt;UAH&lt;/a&gt; campus&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Making the Mummies Dance from Space: Using Satellite Imagery to Find Ancient Egypt, 7:30 p.m. in the Chan Auditorium (first floor &lt;a href="http://www.uah.edu/map/buildings/adsci.php"&gt;Business Administration Building&lt;/a&gt;) on the UAH campus&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;You can read more about Dr. Parcak's work, and much else, on the NASAIA blog, &lt;a href="http://excavate-aia.blogspot.com/"&gt;Excavate!&lt;/a&gt;</description><category>ancgeo</category><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><category>nasaia</category><category>rockets</category><category>tools</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/sarah-parcak-on-egypt-in-huntsville/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2008 00:20:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tastes like mushrooms</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/04/tastes-like-mushrooms/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed reading William J. Broad's "&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/01/science/01patc.html"&gt;Inside the Black Budget&lt;/a&gt;" in today's &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;New York Times&lt;/span&gt;, even though in the end I think the title is a little misleading (there's also &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/slideshow/2008/03/31/science/0401-PATCH_index.html"&gt;an accompanying slideshow&lt;/a&gt;). The article is an imperfect mashup between a soft piece on the Bush White House, the Pentagon's black budget and Trevor Paglen's new book &lt;a style="font-style: italic;" href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/154704808"&gt;I Could Tell You but Then You Would Have to Be Destroyed by Me&lt;/a&gt; (Brooklyn, Melville Publishing House, 2007; ISBN: 9781933633329). I found the patches aspect to be the most interesting angle, even though the black budget and its increase under this administration is a news-worthy topic of significant importance.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Soldiers, veterans and defense contractors know that patches, both official and unofficial, are a ubiquitous part of the visual culture of the military and the industries that support it. As the article notes, patches and their heraldry "are real if often unofficial efforts at building team spirit." They are sometimes also vehicles for advertising, and for satire and social commentary,  aspects that go unaddressed in Broad's article.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I was surprised that there was no effort to decode a patch that's mentioned prominently:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href="http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2008/03/31/science/01patch_slide02.jpg"&gt;One patch shows a space alien&lt;/a&gt; with huge eyes holding a stealth bomber near its mouth. “To Serve Man” reads the text above, a reference to a classic “Twilight Zone” episode in which man is the entree, not the customer. “Gustatus Similis Pullus” reads the caption below, dog Latin for “Tastes Like Chicken.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;It's just a guess, but I don't think that's a patch for a unit that &lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;flies&lt;/span&gt; stealth aircraft.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And then there's "semper in obscurus," featuring &lt;a href="http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2008/04/01/science/01patch.xlarge2.jpg"&gt;a big mushroom&lt;/a&gt;. This is blandly captioned by the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Times&lt;/span&gt; (presumably following Paglen) thus: "Special Projects Office: Oversaw F-117A stealth fighter support." Can our intrepid researcher and reporter not have heard the standard line -- ubiquitous in defense circles -- about being treated like a mushroom?:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;They keep me in the dark and feed me bullshit.&lt;/blockquote&gt;I don't think that one's got a straightforward positive morale message.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Somewhere I've still got a very unofficial patch that started circulating among active-duty personnel at &lt;a href="http://www.grissom.afrc.af.mil/"&gt;Grissom Air Force Base&lt;/a&gt; in the early 1990s, shortly after its realignment to the Air Force Reserve was announced. It features an individual in BDUs reclining in a desk chair with his feet up  on the desk and his hands clasped behind his head. A box on the desk, labeled "IN", is piled high with papers; there's a spiderweb in the "OUT" box. The caption is an acronym: FITBIC. There was more than one expansion widely offered for that acronym. The one intended for anyone senior who asked was: "Faith, Integrity, Trust. Because I care." I'll leave it to you, gentle readers, to puzzle out the other supplement.</description><category>horothesia</category><category>rockets</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/04/tastes-like-mushrooms/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2008 20:42:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>NSSDC ID: 1958-001A</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/01/nssdc-id-1958-001a/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;div style="float: right;"&gt;&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/explorer/launch.html"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0pt 0pt 10px 10px; cursor: pointer;" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_tcSZVmUJxp0/R6Hvd0k5nuI/AAAAAAAAAAU/vYryUgRiXrw/s200/explorerlaunch.jpg" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5161669943551958754" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p style="text-align: center; font-size: 0.6em; font-style: italic;"&gt;Image: NASA&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;The &lt;a href="http://nssdc.gsfc.nasa.gov/nmc/masterCatalog.do?sc=1958-001A"&gt;catalog entry&lt;/a&gt; blandly reads:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Explorer 1 was the first successfully launched U. S. spacecraft. Launched late on 31 January 1958 ... on an adapted Jupiter-C rocket ... Explorer 1 was the first spacecraft to successfully detect the durably trapped radiation in the Earth's magnetosphere&lt;/blockquote&gt;It was a real pleasure to read John Noble Wilford's piece in Tuesday's NYT ("&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/29/science/space/29space.html"&gt;Remembering When U.S. Finally (and Really) Joined the Space Race&lt;/a&gt;") on the significance and impact of the Explorer launch. His recap of the events and efforts leading up to &lt;a href="http://www.nasm.si.edu/exhibitions/GAL100/images/exp1team.jpg"&gt;the jubilant press-conference picture&lt;/a&gt; -- the one in which von Braun, Pickering and Van Allen triumphantly hold up a model of the satellite, and which for some reason the Times didn't run a copy of online -- caught me emotionally off guard.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Like so many of my peers, I've harbored, since childhood, a soft spot for the romance of space exploration. Part of its enduring infectiousness, I suppose, is its seamless blend of ethereal outlandishness and gritty mundanity. This is a heady brew, distilled from reality, promulgated by von Braun and others, and still shaping U.S. space policy (see &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/18/books/review/Roland-t.html"&gt;Alex Roland's quasi-review&lt;/a&gt; of Michael Neufeld's &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Von Braun: Dreamer of Space, Engineer of War&lt;/span&gt;, Knopf, 2007; &lt;a href="http://worldcat.org/isbn/9780307262929"&gt;ISBN: 9780307262929&lt;/a&gt;). From time to time, working on projects we cared about, we've all felt something like what Wilford's subjects (the Redstone/Explorer teams) were feeling in the run-up to that launch: all that hard work and those late nights as the team pulled together (and threatened to fly apart) under the pressure of the deadlines and the ambitions and the sheer challenge of what you were trying to do.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And, oh, what they were trying to do ...&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;These are just two examples of &lt;a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/news/science/topics/space/index.html?scp=1-spot&amp;amp;sq=space+&amp;amp;st=nyt"&gt;some great space reporting in the Times&lt;/a&gt; this past year, both presentist and retrospective. There was also &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/25/science/space/25sput.html"&gt;Wilford's treatment of the Sputnik anniversary&lt;/a&gt; (25 September 2007) and &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/21/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/21viewct.html"&gt;Christine Woodside's first-siting story&lt;/a&gt; (21 October 2007). And, also in the big space issue on 25 September, there was Dennis Overbye's poignant essay "&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/25/science/space/25cosm.html"&gt;One Giant Leap, Followed by Baby Steps&lt;/a&gt;," which did feature another amazing photograph:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;There, on a pillar of violence, is your dream of transcendence, of freedom, of escape from killer rocks in the sky, boiling oceans or whatever postmodern plague science comes up with. Of galactic immortality.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;There's been alot of retrospective, and hooplah, here in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huntsville,_Alabama"&gt;Huntsville&lt;/a&gt; during the run-up to this, the 50th anniversary of the U.S. entry into space. People who've lived or visited here know just how closely bound to space and rocketry our sense of place and community identity are. This got a bit easier to explain to outsiders when Shaila Dawan's "&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/31/us/31huntsville.html"&gt;When the Germans, and Rockets, Came to Town&lt;/a&gt;" ran in the NYT on 31 December 2007. Although I must point out ... peanuts have never been a big crop around here. For 1950, try cotton.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Locally, the &lt;a href="http://www.al.com/huntsvilletimes/"&gt;Huntsville Times&lt;/a&gt; has been reprinting historic, space-related front pages on a daily basis. There's also been some interesting original reporting, like:&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.al.com/news/huntsvilletimes/index.ssf?/base/news/1201688165113390.xml&amp;amp;coll=1"&gt;Mike Marshall on an honorific for the von Braun team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.al.com/news/huntsvilletimes/index.ssf?/base/news/1201688220113390.xml&amp;amp;coll=1"&gt;Patricia McCarter on efforts to honor "the man behind Sputnik"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;The &lt;a href="http://us50thspace.com/"&gt;50th Anniversary website&lt;/a&gt; provides plenty more of this sort of thing (remembrances, audio, video, images), and also includes information about the &lt;a href="http://www.usspace50.com/"&gt;America in Space Technical Symposium&lt;/a&gt; going on today and &lt;a href="http://www.al.com/news/huntsvilletimes/index.ssf?/base/news/1201774599162280.xml&amp;amp;coll=1"&gt;the gala celebration tonight&lt;/a&gt; (purportedly to be streamed live at &lt;a href="http://www.al.com/"&gt;al.com&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I think I'll put on my propeller beanie and &lt;a href="http://www.meetataromas.com/"&gt;head down to Pete's&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe he's brewing Rocket City Blend today ...&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/18/books/review/Roland-t.html"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</description><category>horothesia</category><category>hsv</category><category>rockets</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2008/01/nssdc-id-1958-001a/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2008 22:26:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>