<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about tei)</title><link>http://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://paregorios.org/categories/tei.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:paregorios@hotmail.com"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 23:11:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Stable Orbits or Clear Air Turbulence: Capacity, Scale, and Use Cases in Geospatial Antiquity</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2016/04/stable-orbits-or-clear-air-turbulence/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;br&gt;I delivered the following talk on 8 April 2016 at the &lt;a href="http://awmc.unc.edu/wordpress/conference-2016-mapping-the-past/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mapping the Past: GIS Approaches to Ancient History &lt;/i&gt;conference&lt;/a&gt; at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. &lt;span style="color: red;"&gt;Update (19 April 2016):&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL6fnz6T_aLm2A4dTkGVXbL2PiZbV0itzg"&gt;video is now available on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;, courtesy of the &lt;a href="http://awmc.unc.edu/"&gt;Ancient World Mapping Center&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How many of you are familiar with &lt;a href="http://www.joguldi.com/"&gt;Jo Guldi's&lt;/a&gt; on-line essay on &lt;a href="http://spatial.scholarslab.org/spatial-turn/"&gt;the "Spatial Turn" in western scholarship&lt;/a&gt;? I highly recommend it. It was published in 2011 as a framing narrative for the &lt;a href="http://spatial.scholarslab.org/"&gt;Spatial Humanities website&lt;/a&gt;, a publication of &lt;a href="http://scholarslab.org/"&gt;the Scholar's Lab at the University of Virginia&lt;/a&gt;. The website was intended partly to serve as a record of the &lt;a href="http://spatial.scholarslab.org/about/"&gt;NEH-funded Institute for Enabling Geospatial Scholarship&lt;/a&gt;. That Institute, organized in a series of three thematic sessions, was hosted by the Scholars Lab in 2009 and 2010. The essay begins as follows:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;“Landscape turns” and “spatial turns” are referred to throughout the academic disciplines, often with reference to GIS and the neogeography revolution ... By “turning” we propose a backwards glance at the reasons why travelers from so many disciplines came to be here, fixated upon landscape, together. For the broader questions of landscape – worldview, palimpsest, the commons and community, panopticism and territoriality — are older than GIS, their stories rooted in the foundations of the modern disciplines. These terms have their origin in a historic conversation about land use and agency.&lt;/blockquote&gt;Professor Guldi's essay takes us on a tour through the halls of the Academy, making stops in a variety of departments, including Anthropology, Literature, Sociology, and History. She traces the intellectual innovations and responses -- prompted in no small part by the study and critique of the modern nation state -- that iteratively gave rise to many of the research questions and methods that concern us at this conference. I don't think it would be a stretch to say that not only this conference but its direct antecedents and siblings -- &lt;a href="http://awmc.unc.edu/"&gt;the Ancient World Mapping Center&lt;/a&gt; and its projects, &lt;a href="http://www.unc.edu/depts/cl_atlas"&gt;the &lt;i&gt;Barrington Atlas&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and its inheritors -- are all symptoms of the spatial turn.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So what's the point of my talk this evening? Frankly, I want to ask: to what degree do we know what we're doing? I mean, for example, is spatial practice a subfield? Is it a methodology?  It clearly spans chairs in the Academy. But does it answer -- better or uniquely? -- a particular kind of research question? Is spatial inquiry a standard competency in the humanities, or should it remain the domain of specialists? Does it inform or demand a specialized pedagogy? Within ancient studies in particular, have we placed spatially informed scholarship into a stable orbit that we can describe and maintain, or are we still bumping and bouncing around in an unruly atmosphere, trying to decide whether and where to land?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Some will recognize in this framework questions -- or should we say anxieties -- that are also very much alive for the digital humanities. The two domains are not disjoint. Spatial analysis and visualization are core DH activities. The fact that the Scholar's Lab proposed and the &lt;a href="http://www.neh.gov/divisions/odh"&gt;NEH Office of Digital Humanities&lt;/a&gt; funded the Geospatial Institute I mentioned earlier underscore this point.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, when it comes to spatial analysis and visualization, what are our primary objects of interest? "&lt;a href="http://support.esri.com/en/knowledgebase/GISDictionary/term/location"&gt;Location&lt;/a&gt;" has to be listed as number one, right? Location, and relative location, are important because they are variables in almost every equation we could care about. Humans are physical beings, and almost all of our technology and interaction -- even in the digital age -- are both enabled and constrained by physical factors that vary not only in time, but also in three-dimensional space. If we can locate people, places, and things in space -- absolutely or relatively -- then we can open our spatial toolkit. Our opportunities to explore become even richer when we can access the way ancient people located themselves, each other, places, and things in space: the rhetoric and language they used to describe and depict those locations.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The connections between places and between places and other things are also important. The related things can be of any imaginable type: objects, dates, events, people, themes. We can express and investigate these relationships with a variety of spatial and non-spatial information structures: directed &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graph_(abstract_data_type)"&gt;graphs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_science"&gt;networks&lt;/a&gt; for example. There are digital tools and methods at our disposal for working with these mental constructs too, and we'll touch on a couple of examples in a minute. But I'd like the research questions, rather than the methods, to lead the discussion.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;When looking at both built and exploited natural landscapes, we are often interested in the functions humans impart to space and place. These observations apply not only to physical environments, but also to their descriptions in literature and their depictions in art and cartography. And so spatial function is also about spatial rhetoric, performance, audience, and reception.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Allow me a brief example: the sanctuary of Artemis Limnatis at Volimnos in the Tayegetos mountains (cf. &lt;a href="http://journals.cambridge.org/abstract_S0068245414000100"&gt;Koursoumis 2014&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/demarc"&gt;Elliott 2004&lt;/a&gt;, 74-79 no. 10). Its location is demonstrated today only by scattered architectural, artistic, and epigraphic remains, but epigraphic and literary testimony make it clear that it was just one of several such sanctuaries that operated at various periods and places in the Peloponnese.  Was this ancient place of worship located in a beautiful spot, evocative of the divine? Surely it was! But it -- and its homonymous siblings -- also existed to claim, mark, guard, consecrate, and celebrate political and economic assertions about the land it overlooked. Consequently, the sanctuary was a locus of civic pride for the &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/570480"&gt;Messenians&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/570685"&gt;Spartans&lt;/a&gt;, such that -- from legendary times down to at least the reign of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vespasian"&gt;Vespasian&lt;/a&gt; -- it occasioned both bloodshed and elite competition for the favor of imperial powers. Given the goddess's epithet (she is Artemis Of The Borders), the sanctuary's location, and its history of contentiousness, I don't think we're surprised that a writer like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tacitus"&gt;Tacitus&lt;/a&gt; should take notice of delegations from both sides arriving in Rome to argue for and against the most recent outcome in the struggle for control of the sanctuary. I can't help but imagine him smirking as he drops it into the text of his &lt;a href="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Tac.+Ann.+4.43&amp;amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.02.0078"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Annals&lt;/i&gt; (4.43)&lt;/a&gt;, entirely in indirect discourse and deliberately ambiguous of course about whether the delegations appeared before the emperor or the Senate. It must have given him a grim sort of satisfaction to be able to record a notable interaction between Greece and Rome during the reign of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiberius"&gt;Tiberius&lt;/a&gt; that also served as a metaphor for the estrangement of emperor and senate, of new power and old prerogatives.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Epigraphic and literary analysis can give us insight into issues of spatial function, and so can computational methods. The two approaches are complementary, sometimes informing, supporting, and extending each other, other times filling in gaps the other method leaves open. Let's spend some time looking more closely at the computational aspects of spatial scholarship.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A couple of weeks ago, I got to spend some time talking to &lt;a href="https://vivo.brown.edu/display/lmmignon"&gt;Lisa Mignone&lt;/a&gt; at Brown about her innovative work on the visibility of temples at Rome with respect to the valley of the Tiber and the approaches to the city. Can anyone doubt that, among the factors at play in the ancient siting and subsequent experience of such major structures, there's a visual expression of power and control at work? Mutatis mutandis, you can feel something like it today if you get the chance to walk the Tiber at length. Or, even if you just go out and contemplate the sight lines to the monuments and buildings of &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/maps/KT6i8uLcQHM2"&gt;McCorkle Place&lt;/a&gt; here on the UNC campus. To be sure, in any such analysis there is a major role for the mind of the researcher ... in interpretation, evaluation, narration, and argument, and that researcher will need to be informed as much as possible by the history, archaeology, and literature of the place. But, depending on scale and the alterations that a landscape has undergone over time, there is also the essential place of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viewshed"&gt;viewshed&lt;/a&gt; analysis. Viewsheds are determined by assessing the visibility of every point in an area from a particular point of interest. Can I see &lt;a href="http://ncbg.unc.edu/coker-arboretum/"&gt;the University arboretum&lt;/a&gt; from the north-facing windows of the Ancient World Mapping Center on the 5th floor of &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/maps/uGptAWj5rou"&gt;Davis Library&lt;/a&gt;? Yes, the arboretum is in the Center's viewshed. Well, certain parts of it anyway. Can I see &lt;a href="http://www.unc.edu/interactive-tour/the-pit/"&gt;the Pit&lt;/a&gt; from there? No. Mercifully, the Pit is not in the Center's viewshed.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In one methodological respect, Professor Mignone's work is not new. Viewshed analysis has been widely used for years in archaeological and historical study, at levels ranging from the house to the public square to the civic territory and beyond. I doubt anyone could enumerate all the published studies without a massive amount of bibliographical work. Perhaps the most well known -- if you'll permit an excursion outside the domain of ancient studies -- is &lt;a href="https://umaine.edu/history/faculty/anneknowles/"&gt;Anne Kelly Knowles&lt;/a&gt;' work (with multiple collaborators) on the Battle of Gettysburg. What could the commanders see and when could they see it? There's &lt;a href="http://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/A-Cutting-Edge-Second-Look-at-the-Battle-of-Gettysburg-1-180947921/"&gt;a fascinating, interactive treatment of the data and its implications&lt;/a&gt; published on the website of &lt;i&gt;Smithsonian Magazine&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Off the top of my head, I can point to a couple of other examples in ancient studies. Though their mention will only scratch the surface of the full body of work, I think they are both useful examples. There's &lt;a href="http://www.archatlas.org/SitesFromSatellites/sites.php?name=mycenae"&gt;Andrew Sherrat's 2004 treatment of Myceneae&lt;/a&gt;, which explores the site's visual and topographical advantages in an accessible, online form. It makes use of cartographic illustration and accessible text to make its points about strategically and economically interesting features of the site.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I also recall a poster by &lt;a href="http://classics.cofc.edu/about/faculty-and-staff/newhard-james.php"&gt;James Newhard&lt;/a&gt; and several collaborators that was presented at the 2012 meeting of the &lt;a href="https://www.archaeological.org/"&gt;Archaeological Institute of America&lt;/a&gt;. It reported on the use of viewshed analysis and other methods as part of an integrated approach to identifying Byzantine defensive systems in North Central Anatolia. The idea here was that the presence of a certain kind of viewshed -- one offering an advantage for surveillance of strategically useful landscape elements like passes and valleys -- might lend credance to the identification of ambiguous archaeological remains as fortifications. Viewshed analysis is not just revelatory, but can also be used for predictive and taxonomic tasks.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In our very own conference, we'll hear from Morgan Di Rodi and &lt;a href="https://oxford.academia.edu/MariaKopsacheili"&gt;Maria Kopsachelli&lt;/a&gt; about their use of viewshed analysis and other techniques to refine understanding of multiple archaeological sites in northwest Greece. So we'll get to see viewsheds in action!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Like most forms of computational spatial analysis, viewshed work is most rigorously and uniformly accomplished with GIS software, supplied with appropriately scaled location and elevation data. To do it reliably by hand for most interesting cases would be impossible. These dependencies on software and data, and the know-how to use them effectively, should draw our attention to some important facts. First of all, assembling the prerequisites of non-trivial spatial analysis is challenging and time consuming. More than once, I've heard Prof. Knowles say that something like ninety percent of the time and effort in a historical GIS project goes into data collection and preparation.  Just as we depend on the labor of librarians, editors, philologists, Renaissance humanists, medieval copyists, and their allies for our ability to leverage the ancient literary tradition for scholarly work, so too we depend on the labor of mathematicians, geographers, programmers, surveyors, and their allies for the data and computational artifice we need to conduct viewshed analysis. This inescapable debt -- or, if you prefer, this vast interdisciplinary investment in our work -- is a topic to which I'd like to return at the end of the talk.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Before we turn our gaze to other methods, I'd like to talk briefly about other kinds of sheds. &lt;a href="http://gis4geomorphology.com/watershed/"&gt;Watershed&lt;/a&gt; analysis -- the business of calculating the entire area drained and supplied by a particular water system -- is a well established method of physical geography and the inspiration for the name viewshed. It has value for cultural, economic, and historical study too, and so should remain on our spatial RADAR. In fact, &lt;a href="https://classicalstudies.duke.edu/people/melissa-huber"&gt;Melissa Huber&lt;/a&gt;'s talk on the Roman water infrastructure under &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claudius"&gt;Claudius&lt;/a&gt; will showcase this very method.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Among &lt;a href="http://clas.uiowa.edu/classics/people/sarah-e-bond"&gt;Sarah Bond&lt;/a&gt;'s current research ideas is a "smells" map of ancient Rome. Where in the streets of ancient Rome would you have encountered the odors of a bakery or a latrine a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fullo#Archaeological_remains_of_fullonicae"&gt;fullonica&lt;/a&gt;. And -- God help you -- what would it have smelled like? Will it be possible at some point to integrate airflow and prevailing wind models with urban topography and location data to calculate "smellsheds" or "nosescapes" for particular installations and industries? I sure hope so! Sound sheds ought to be another interesting possibility; we ought to look for leadership to the work of people like &lt;a href="https://jeffdveitch.me/"&gt;Jeff Veitch&lt;/a&gt; who is investigating acoustics and architecture at &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/422995"&gt;Ostia&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href="https://vpcp.chass.ncsu.edu/"&gt;Virtual Paul's Cross project&lt;/a&gt; at North Carolina State.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Every bit as interesting as &lt;i&gt;what&lt;/i&gt; the ancients could see, and from where they could see it, is the question of &lt;i&gt;how&lt;/i&gt; they saw things in space and how they described them. Our curiosity about ancient geographic mental models and worldview drives us to ask questions like ones &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Talbert"&gt;Richard Talbert&lt;/a&gt; has been asking: did the people living in a Roman province think of themselves as "of the province" in the way modern Americans think of themselves as being North Carolinians or Michiganders? Were the Roman provinces strictly administrative in nature, or did they contribute to personal or corporate identity in some way? Though not a field that has to be plowed only with computers, questions of ancient worldview do sometimes yield to computational approaches.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Consider, for example, the work of &lt;a href="http://www.open.ac.uk/people/eteb2"&gt;Elton Barker&lt;/a&gt; and colleagues under the rubric of the &lt;a href="http://hestia.open.ac.uk/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Hestia&lt;/i&gt; project&lt;/a&gt;. Here's how they describe it:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;Using a digital text of Herodotus’s &lt;i&gt;Histories&lt;/i&gt;, Hestia uses web-mapping technologies such as GIS, &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/earth/"&gt;Google Earth&lt;/a&gt; and the Narrative TimeMap to investigate the cultural geography of the ancient world through the eyes of one of its first witnesses. &lt;/blockquote&gt;In &lt;i&gt;Hestia&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collocation"&gt;word collocation&lt;/a&gt; -- a mainstay of computational &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Text_mining#Text_analysis_processes"&gt;text analysis&lt;/a&gt; -- is brought together and integrated with location-based measures to interrogate not only the &lt;i&gt;spatial&lt;/i&gt; proximity of places mentioned by Herodotus, but also the &lt;i&gt;textual&lt;/i&gt; proximities of those place references. With these keys, the &lt;i&gt;Hestia&lt;/i&gt; team opens the door to Herodotus' geomind and that of the culture he lived in: what combinations of actual location, historical events, cultural assumptions, and literary agenda shape the mention of places in his narrative?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Hestia&lt;/i&gt; is not alone in exploring this particular frontier. Tomorrow we'll hear from &lt;a href="https://ryanmatthewhorne.wordpress.com/"&gt;Ryan Horne&lt;/a&gt; about his collaborative work on the &lt;a href="https://bigancientmediterranean.wordpress.com/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Big Ancient Mediterranean&lt;/i&gt; project&lt;/a&gt;. Among its pioneering aspects is the incorporation of data about more than the collocation of placenames in primary sources and the relationships of the referenced places with each other. BAM also scrutinizes personal names and the historical persons to whom they refer. Who is mentioned with whom where? What can we learn from exploring the networks of connection that radiate from such intersections?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The introduction of a temporal axis into geospatial calcuation and visualization is also usually necessary and instructive in spatial ancient studies, even if it still proves to be more challenging in standard GIS software than one might like. &lt;a href="https://www.iwu.edu/history/faculty/Coles-Amanda.html"&gt;Amanda Coles&lt;/a&gt; has taken on that challenge, and will be telling us more about what it's helped her learn about the interplay between warfare, colonial foundations, road building, and the Roman elites during the Republic.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Viewsheds, worldviews, and temporality, oh my!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How about spatial economies? How close were sources of production to their markets? How close in terms of distance? How close in terms of travel time? How close in terms of cost to move goods?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Maybe we are interested in urban logistics. How quickly could you empty the colosseum? How much bread could you distribute to how many people in a particular amount of time at a particular place? What were the constraints and capacities for transport of the raw materials? What do the answers to such questions reveal about the practicality, ubiquity, purpose, social reach, and costs of communal activities in the public space? How do these conclusions compare with the experiences and critiques voiced in ancient sources?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How long would it take a legion to move from one place to another in a particular landscape? What happens when we compare the effects of landscape on travel time with the built architecture of the &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limes"&gt;limes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; or the information we can glean about unit deployment patterns from military documents like the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vindolanda_tablets"&gt;Vindolanda tablets&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.livius.org/bn-bz/bu_njem/bu_njem_ostraca.html"&gt;the ostraca from Bu Njem&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The computational methods involved in these sorts of investigations have wonderful names, and like the others we've discussed, require spatial algorithms realized in specialized software. Consider &lt;a href="http://wiki.gis.com/wiki/index.php/Cost_Surface"&gt;cost surfaces&lt;/a&gt;: for a particular unit of area on the ground, what is the cost in time or effort to pass through it? Consider &lt;a href="http://wiki.gis.com/wiki/index.php/Cost_Over_a_Network"&gt;network cost models&lt;/a&gt;: for specific paths between nodal points, what is the cost of transit? Consider least &lt;a href="http://wiki.gis.com/wiki/index.php/Cost_Path_Analysis"&gt;cost path&lt;/a&gt; analysis: given a cost surface or network model, what is the cheapest path available between two points?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Many classicists will have used &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="http://orbis.stanford.edu/"&gt;Orbis: The Stanford Geospatial Network Model of the Roman World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. The &lt;i&gt;Orbis&lt;/i&gt; team, assembled by &lt;a href="http://web.stanford.edu/~scheidel/"&gt;Walter Scheidel&lt;/a&gt;, has produced an online environment in which one can query a network model of travel costs between key nodal points in the Roman world, varying such parameters as time of year and mode of transport. This model, and its digital modes of access, bring us to another vantage point. How close were two places in the Roman world, not as the crow flies, not in terms of miles along the road, but as the boat sailed or the feet walked.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.topoi.org/person/weissova-barbora/"&gt;Barbora Weissova&lt;/a&gt; is going to talk to us tomorrow about her work in and around &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/511268"&gt;Nicaea&lt;/a&gt;. Among her results, she will discuss another application of Least Cost Path Analysis: predicting the most likely route for a lost ancient roadway.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's not just about travel, transport, and cost. Distribution patterns are of interest too, often combined with ceramic analysis, or various forms of isotopic or metallurgical testing, to assess the origin, dissemination, and implications of ancient objects found in the landscape. Inscriptions, coins, portable antiquities, architectural and artistic styles, pottery, all have been used in such studies. &lt;a href="http://history.unc.edu/people/graduate-students/corey-ellithorpe/"&gt;Corey Ellithorpe&lt;/a&gt; is going to give us a taste of this approach in numismatics by unpacking the relationship between Roman imperial ideology and regional distribution patterns of coins.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'd like to pause here for just a moment and express my hope that you'll agree with the following assessment. I think we are in for an intellectual feast tomorrow. I think we should congratulate the organizers of the conference for such &lt;a href="http://awmc.unc.edu/wordpress/conference-2016-mapping-the-past/full-schedule/"&gt;an interesting, and representative, array of papers and presentations&lt;/a&gt;. That there is on offer such a tempting smorgasbord is also, of course, all to the credit of the presenters and their collaborators. And surely it must be a factor as we consider the ubiquity and disciplinarity of spatial applications in ancient studies.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Assiduous students of the conference program will notice that I have neglected yet to mention a couple of the papers. Fear not, for they feature in the next section of my talk, which is -- to borrow a phrase from Meghan Trainor and Kevin Kadish -- all about that data.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, conference presenters, would you agree with the dictum I've attributed to Anne Knowles? Does data collection and preparation take up a huge chunk of your time?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Spatial data, particularly spatial data for ancient studies, doesn't normally grow on trees, come in a jar, or sit on a shelf. The ingredients have to be gathered and cleaned, combined and cooked. And then you have to take care of it, transport it, keep track of it, and refashion it to fit your software and your questions. Sometimes you have to start over, hunt down additional ingredients, or try a new recipe. This sort of iterative work -- the cyclic remaking of the experimental apparatus and materials -- is absolutely fundamental to spatially informed research in ancient studies.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If you were hoping I'd grind an axe somewhere in this talk, you're in luck. It's axe grinding time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There is absolutely no question in my mind that the collection and curation of data is part and parcel of research. It is a research activity. It has research outcomes. You can't answer questions without it. If you aren't surfacing your work on data curation in your CV, or if you're discounting someone else's work on data curation in decisions about hiring, tenure, and promotion, then I've got &lt;a href="http://bobdylan.com/songs/times-they-are-changin/"&gt;an old Bob Dylan song&lt;/a&gt; I'd like to play for you.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Archive and publish your datasets. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Treat them as publications in your CV. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Write a review of someone else's published dataset and try to get it published. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Document your data curation process in articles and conference presentations.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br&gt;Right. Axes down.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, where does our data come from? Sometimes we can get some of it in prepared form, even if subsequent selection and reformatting is required. For some areas and scales, modern topography and elevation can be had in various raster and vector formats. Some specialized datasets exist that can be used as a springboard for some tasks. It's here that the &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; project&lt;/a&gt;, which I direct, seeks to contribute. By digitizing not the maps from the &lt;i&gt;Barrington Atlas&lt;/i&gt;, but the places and placenames referenced on those maps and in the map-by-map directory, we created a digital dataset with potential for wide reuse. By wrapping it in &lt;a href="https://github.com/isawnyu/pleiades-gazetteer/"&gt;a software framework&lt;/a&gt; that facilitates display, basic cartographic visualization, and collaborative updates, we broke out of the constraints of scale and cartographic economy imposed by the paper atlas format. &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; now knows many more places than the &lt;i&gt;Barrington&lt;/i&gt; did, most of these outside the cultures with which the Atlas was concerned. More precise coordinates are coming in too, as are more placename variants and bibliography. All of this data is built for reuse. You can collect it piece by piece from the web interface or download it in a number of formats. You can even write programs to talk directly to Pleiades for you, requesting and receiving data in a computationally actionable form. The AWMC has &lt;a href="http://awmc.unc.edu/wordpress/map-files/"&gt;data for reuse too&lt;/a&gt;, including historical coastlines and rivers and map base materials. It's all downloadable in GIS-friendly formats.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; and the AWMC only help for some things. It's telling that only a couple of the projects represented at this conference made use of &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; data. That's not because &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; is bad or because the authors didn't know about &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; or the Center. It's because the questions they're asking require data that &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; is not designed to provide. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's proof of the point I'd like to underline: usually -- because your research question is unique in some way, otherwise you wouldn't be pursuing it -- you're going to have to get your hands dirty with data collection.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But before we get dirty, I'm obliged to point out that, although &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; has received significant, periodic support from the &lt;a href="http://www.neh.gov/"&gt;National Endowment for the Humanities&lt;/a&gt; since 2006, the views, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed in this lecture do not necessarily reflect those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We've already touched on the presence of spatial language in literature. For some studies, the placenames, placeful descriptions, and narratives of space found in both primary and secondary sources constitute raw data we'd like to use. Identifying and extracting such data is usually a non-trivial task, and may involve a combination of manual and computational techniques, the latter depending on the size and tractability of the textual corpus in question and drawing on established methods in natural language processing and named entity recognition. It's here we may encounter "&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoparsing"&gt;geoparsing&lt;/a&gt;" as a term of art. Many digital textual projects and collections are doing geoparsing: individual epigraphic and papyrological publications using the &lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml"&gt;Text Encoding Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://epidoc.sf.net/"&gt;EpiDoc&lt;/a&gt; Guidelines; the &lt;a href="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/"&gt;Perseus Digital Library&lt;/a&gt;; the &lt;a href="http://commons.pelagios.org/"&gt;Pelagios Commons&lt;/a&gt; by way of its &lt;a href="http://pelagios.org/recogito"&gt;Recogito&lt;/a&gt; platform. The &lt;a href="http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~chgis/"&gt;China Historical GIS&lt;/a&gt; is built up entirely from textual sources, tracking each placename and each assertion of administrative hierarchy back to its testimony.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For your project, you may be able to find geoparsed digital texts that serve your needs, or you may need to do the work yourself. Either way, some transformation on the results of geoparsing is likely to be necessary to make them useful in the context of your research question and associated apparatus.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Relevant here is &lt;a href="http://www.kenyon.edu/directories/campus-directory/biography/micah-myers/"&gt;Micah Myers&lt;/a&gt;'s conference paper. He is going to bring together for us &lt;a href="http://mappingancienttexts.net/"&gt;the analysis and visualization of travel as narrated in literature&lt;/a&gt;. I gather from his abstract that he'll show us not only a case study of the process, but discuss the inner workings of the on-line publication that has been developed to disseminate the work.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Geophysical and archaeological survey may supply your needs. Perhaps you'll have to do fieldwork yourself, or perhaps you can collect the information you need from prior publications or get access to archival records and excavation databases. Maybe you'll get lucky and find a dataset that's been published into &lt;a href="http://opencontext.org/"&gt;OpenContext&lt;/a&gt;, the British &lt;a href="http://archaeologydataservice.ac.uk/"&gt;Archaeology Data Service&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://www.tdar.org/"&gt;tDAR: the Digital Archaeological Record&lt;/a&gt;. But using this data requires constant vigilance, especially when it was collected for some purpose other than you own. What were the sampling criteria? What sorts of material were intentionally ignored? What circumstances attended collection and post-processing?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Sometimes the location data we need comes not from a single survey or excavation, but from a large number of possibly heterogeneous sources. This will be the case for many spatial studies that involve small finds, inscriptions, coins, and the like. Fortunately, many of the major documentary, numismatic, and archaeological databases are working toward the inclusion of uniform geographic information in their database records. This development, which exploits &lt;a href="http://pleiades.stoa.org/help/what-are-pleiades-uris"&gt;the unique identifying numbers that &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; bestows&lt;/a&gt; on each ancient place, was first championed by &lt;a href="http://www.lancaster.ac.uk/history/about-us/people/leif-isaksen"&gt;Leif Isaksen&lt;/a&gt;, Elton Barker, and &lt;a href="http://rsimon.github.io/"&gt;Rainer Simon&lt;/a&gt; of the Pelagios Commons project. If you get data from a project like the &lt;a href="http://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/home"&gt;Heidelberg Epigraphic Databank&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://papyri.info/"&gt;papyri.info&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="http://arachne.dainst.org/"&gt;Arachne database of the German Archaeological Institute&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="http://numismatics.org/ocre/"&gt;Online Coins of the Roman Empire&lt;/a&gt;, or the Perseus Digital Library, you can count on being able to join it easily with &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; data and that of other &lt;a href="http://pelagios-project.blogspot.com/p/partners.html"&gt;Pelagios partners&lt;/a&gt;. Hopefully this will save some of us some time in days to come.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Sometimes what's important from a prior survey will come to us primarily through maps and plans. Historical maps may also carry information we'd like to extract and interpret. There's a whole raft of techniques associated with the scanning, &lt;a href="http://www.georeference.org/doc/georegistration.htm"&gt;georegistration&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://support.esri.com/en/knowledgebase/GISDictionary/term/georectification"&gt;georectification&lt;/a&gt; (or warping) of maps so that they can be layered and subjected to feature tracing (or extraction) in GIS software. Some historic cartofacts -- one thinks of &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/exhibitions/space/tpeut.html"&gt;the Peutinger map&lt;/a&gt; and medieval &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mappa_mundi"&gt;mappae mundi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; as examples -- are so out of step with our expectations of cartesian uniformity that these techniques don't work. Recourse in such cases may be had to first digitizing features of interest in the cartesian plane of the image itself, assigning spatial locations to features later on the basis of other data. Digitizing and vectorizing plans and maps resulting from multiple excavations in order to build up a comprehensive archaeological map of a region or site also necessitates not only the use of GIS software but the application of careful data management practices for handling and preserving a collection of digital files that can quickly grow huge.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We'll get insight into just such an effort tomorrow when Tim Shea reports on Duke's "&lt;a href="http://www.dukewired.org/projects/digital-athens/"&gt;Digital Athens Project&lt;/a&gt;".&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Let's not forget remote sensing! In RS we use sensors -- devices that gather information in various sections of the electro-magnetic spectrum or that detect change in local physical phenomena. We mount these sensors on platforms that let us take whatever point of view is necessary to achieve the resolution, scale, and scope of interest: satellites, airplanes, drones, balloons, wagons, sleds, boats, human hands. The sensors capture emitted and reflected light in the visible, infrared, and ultraviolet wavelengths or magnetic or electrical fields. They emit and detect the return of laser light, radio frequency energy, microwaves, millimeter waves, and, especially underwater, sound waves. Specialized software is used to analyze and convert such data for various purposes, often into rasterized intensity or distance values that can be visualized by assigning brightness and color scales to the values in the raster grid. Multiple images are often mosaicked together to form continuous images of a landscape or 360 degree seamless panoramas.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Remotely sensed data facilitate the detection and interpretation of landforms, vegetation patterns, and physical change over time, revealing or enhancing understanding of built structures and exploited landscapes, as well as their conservation. This is the sort of work that &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarah_Parcak"&gt;Sarah Parcak&lt;/a&gt; has been popularizing, but it too has decades of practice behind it. In 1990, &lt;a href="http://nsstc.uah.edu/ats/tomsever/about.html"&gt;Tom Sever&lt;/a&gt;'s dissertation reported on a remote-sensing analysis of the Anasazi road system, revealing a component of the built landscape that was not only invisible on the ground, but that demonstrates that the Anasazi were far more willing than even the Romans to create arrow-straight roads in defiance of topographical impediments. More recently, Prof. Sever and his NASA colleague &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/centers/marshall/about/marshallfaces/irwin.html#.Vwl1ORMrIlI"&gt;Daniel Irwin&lt;/a&gt; have been using RS data for parts of Guatemala, Honduras, and Mexico, to distinguish between vegetation that thrives in alkaline soils and vegetation that doesn't. Because of the Mayan penchant for coating monumental structures with significant quantities of lime plaster, this data has proved remarkably effective in the locating of previously unknown structures beneath forest canopy. The results seem likely to overturn prevailing estimates of the extent of Mayan urbanism, illustrating a landscape far more cleared and built upon than heretofore proposed (cf. &lt;a href="http://nsstc.uah.edu/ats/tomsever/docs/sever_irwin_2003.pdf"&gt;Sever 2003&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Given the passion with which I've already spoken about the care and feeding of data, you'll be unsurprised to learn that I'm really looking forward to &lt;a href="http://vis.duke.edu/people/nevio-danelon-ph-d/"&gt;Nevio Danelon&lt;/a&gt;'s presentation tomorrow on the capture and curation of remotely sensed data in a digital workflow management system designed to support visualization processes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I think it's worth noting that both Professor Parcak's recently collaborative work on a possible Viking settlement in Newfoundland, as well as Prof. Sever's dissertation, represent a certain standard in the application of remote sensing to archaeology. RS analysis is tried or adopted for most archaeological survey and excavation undertaken today. The choice of sensors, platforms, and analytical methods will of course vary in response to landscape conditions, expected archaeological remains, and the realities of budget, time, and know-how.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Similarly common, I think, in archaeological projects is the consideration of geophysical, alluvial, and climatic features and changes in the study area. The data supporting such considerations will come from the kinds of sources we've already discussed, and will have to be managed in appropriate ways. But it's in this area -- ancient climate and landscape change -- that I think ancient studies has a major deficit in both procedure and data. Computational, predictive modeling of ancient climate, landscape, and ground cover has made no more than tentative and patchy inroads on the way we think about and map the ancient historical landscape. That's a deficit that needs addressing in an interdisciplinary and more comprehensive way.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'd be remiss if, before moving on to conclusions, I kept the focus so narrowly on research questions and methods that we miss the opportunity to talk about pedagogy, public engagement, outreach, and cultural heritage preservation. Spatial practice in the humanities is increasingly deeply involved in such areas. The Ancient World Mapping Center's &lt;a href="http://awmc.unc.edu/wordpress/alacarte/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Antiquity a-la Carte&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; website enables users to create and refine custom maps from &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; and other data that can then be cited, downloaded, and reused. It facilitates the creation of map tests, student projects, and maps to accompany conference presentations and paper submissions. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Meanwhile, governments, NGOs, and academics alike are brining the full spectrum of spatial methods to bear as they try to prevent damage to cultural heritage sites through assessment, awareness, and intervention. The &lt;a href="http://www.asor.org/"&gt;American Schools of Oriental Research&lt;/a&gt; conducts &lt;a href="http://www.asor-syrianheritage.org/"&gt;damage assessments and site monitoring&lt;/a&gt; with funding in part from the US State Department. The &lt;a href="http://uscbs.org/"&gt;U.S. Committee of the Blue Shield&lt;/a&gt; works with academics to prepare geospatial datasets that are offered to the Department of Defense to enhance compliance with &lt;a href="http://uscbs.org/1954-hague-convention.html"&gt;the 1954 Hague Convention for the Protection of Cultural Property in the Event of Armed Conflict&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;These are critical undertakings as well, and should be considered an integral part of our spatial antiquity practice.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, how should we gather up the threads of this discussion so we can move on to the more substantive parts of the conference?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'd like to conclude as I began, by recommending an essay. In this case, I'm thinking of &lt;a href="http://nowviskie.org/"&gt;Bethany Nowiskie&lt;/a&gt;'s recent &lt;a href="http://nowviskie.org/2015/on-capacity-and-care/"&gt;essay on "capacity and care" in the digital humanities&lt;/a&gt;. Bethany is the former director of UVA's Scholars Lab. She now serves as Director of the &lt;a href="https://www.diglib.org/"&gt;Digital Library Federation&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href="http://www.clir.org/"&gt;Council on Library and Information Resources&lt;/a&gt;. I had the great good fortune to hear Bethany deliver a version of this essay as &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LoGr3rPiGE8"&gt;a keynote talk&lt;/a&gt; at a project director's meeting hosted by the NEH Office of Digital Humanities in Washington in September of last year. You can find the essay version on her personal website.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Bethany thinks the Humanities must expand its capacity in order not only to survive the 21st century, but to contribute usefully to its grand challenges. To cope with increasing amounts and needs for data of every kind. To move gracefully in analysis and regard from large scales to small ones and to connect analysis at both levels. To address audiences and serve students in an expanding array of modes. To collaborate across disciplines and heal the structurally weakening divisions that exist between faculty and "&lt;a href="http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/alt-ac/"&gt;alternate academics&lt;/a&gt;", even as the entire edifice of faculty promotion and tenure threatens to shatter around us.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What is Bethany's prescription? An ethic of care. She defines an ethic of care as "a set of practices", borrowing the following quotation from the political scientist &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_Tronto"&gt;Joan Tronto&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;a species of [collective] activity that includes everything we do to maintain, contain, and repair our world, so that we can live in it as well as possible.&lt;/blockquote&gt;I think our practice of spatial humanities in ancient studies is just such a collective activity. We don't have to turn around much to know that we are cradled in the arms and buoyed up on the shoulders of a vast cohort, stretching back through time and out across the globe. Creating data and handing it on. Debugging and optimizing algorithms. Critiquing ideas and sharpening analytical tools.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The vast majority of projects on the conference schedule, or that I could think of to mention in my talk, are explicitly and immediately collaborative.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And we can look around this room and see like-minded colleagues galore. Mentors. Helpers. Friends. Comforters. Makers. Guardians.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And we have been building the community infrastructure we need to carry on caring about each other and about the work we do to explain the human past to the human present and to preserve that understanding for the human future. We have centers and conferences and special interest groups and training sessions. We involve undergraduates in research and work with interested people from outside the academy. We have increasingly useful datasets and increasingly interconnected information systems. Will all these things persist? No, but we get to play a big role in deciding what and when and why.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So if there's a stable orbit to be found, I think it's in continuing to work together and to do so mindfully, acknowledging our debts to each other and repaying them in kind.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'm reminded of a conversation I had with &lt;a href="http://www.informatics.org/scottmadry.html"&gt;Scott Madry&lt;/a&gt;, back in the early &lt;a href="http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2010/01/04/what-do-you-call-it"&gt;aughts&lt;/a&gt; when we were just getting the Mapping Center rolling and &lt;i&gt;Pleiades&lt;/i&gt; was just an idea. As many of you know, Scott together with &lt;a href="http://anthropology.unc.edu/person/carole-l-crumley/"&gt;Carole Crumley&lt;/a&gt; and numerous other collaborators here at UNC and beyond, have been running a multidimensional research project in Burgundy since the 1970s. At one time or another the &lt;a href="http://burgundylandscapes.web.unc.edu/"&gt;Burgundy Historical Landscapes project&lt;/a&gt; has conducted most of the kinds of studies I've mentioned tonight, all the while husbanding a vast and growing store of spatial and other data across a daunting array of systems and formats.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I think that the conversation I'm remembering with Scott took place after he'd spent a couple of hours teaching undergraduate students in my seminar on Roman roads and land travel how to do &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orthophoto"&gt;orthophoto&lt;/a&gt; analysis the old fashioned way: with stereo prints and stereoscopes. He was having them do the Sarah Parcak thing: looking for crop marks and other indications of potentially buried physical culture. After the students had gone, Scott and I were commiserating about the challenges of maintaining and funding long-running research projects. I was sympathetic, but know now that I really didn't understand those challenges then. Scott did, and I remember what he said. He said: "We were standing on that hill in Burgundy twenty years ago, and as we looked around I said to Carol: 'somehow, we are going to figure out what happened here, no matter how long it takes.'"&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;That's what I'm talking about.</description><category>ancgeo</category><category>awmc</category><category>awmc2016</category><category>batlas</category><category>collaboration</category><category>conferences</category><category>cultural heritage protection</category><category>dh</category><category>digclass</category><category>epidoc</category><category>hgis</category><category>horothesia</category><category>neogeography</category><category>nlp</category><category>pelagios</category><category>perseus</category><category>pleiades</category><category>rants</category><category>tei</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2016/04/stable-orbits-or-clear-air-turbulence/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2016 04:03:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Eighteen Years of EpiDoc. Now what?</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2014/10/eighteen-years-of-epidoc-now-what/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;Transcript of my keynote address, delivered to the &lt;a href="http://www.eagle-network.eu/about/events/eagle2014/"&gt;EAGLE 2014 International Conference&lt;/a&gt; on Monday, September 29, 2014, at the &lt;a href="http://www.ens.fr/?lang=fr"&gt;École normale supérieure&lt;/a&gt; in Paris:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Thank you.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Allow me to begin by thanking the organizers of this conference. The conference chairs: &lt;a href="http://www.lettere.uniroma1.it/users/silvia-orlandi"&gt;Silvia Orlandi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.antiquite.ens.fr/enseignants/permanences-et-contact/latin-126/article/francois-berard"&gt;Francois Berard&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.college-de-france.fr/site/en-john-scheid/#course"&gt;John Scheid&lt;/a&gt;. Members of the Steering Committee: &lt;a href="http://www.isti.cnr.it/about/people.php?id=69"&gt;Vittore Casarosa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://uni-heidelberg.academia.edu/PietroMariaLiuzzo"&gt;Pietro Liuzzo&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://uniroma1.academia.edu/RaffaellaSantucci"&gt;Raffaella Santucci&lt;/a&gt;. The local organizing committee: Elizabeth Le Bunetel and Philippe Martineau. &lt;a href="http://www.eagle-network.eu/about/events/eagle2014/programme-committee/"&gt;Members of the EAGLE 2014 General Committee&lt;/a&gt; -- you are too numerous to mention, but no less appreciated. To the sponsors of &lt;a href="http://www.eagle-network.eu/"&gt;EAGLE Europeana&lt;/a&gt;: the &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/cip/index_en.htm"&gt;Competitiveness and Innovation Framework Programme&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/index_en.htm"&gt;European Commission&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="http://www.europeana.eu/"&gt;Europeana&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="http://wiki.wikimedia.it/wiki/Pagina_principale"&gt;Wikimedia Italia&lt;/a&gt;. To the presenters and poster-authors and their collaborators. To those who have made time out of busy schedules to prepare for, support, or attend this event. Colleagues and friends. Thank you for the invitation to speak and to be part of this important conference.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;OK. Please get out your laptops and start up the &lt;a href="http://www.oxygenxml.com/"&gt;Oxygen XML Editor&lt;/a&gt;. If you actually read the syllabus for the course, you'd have already downloaded &lt;a href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/"&gt;the latest copy of the EpiDoc schema&lt;/a&gt;...&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Just kidding.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I have perhaps misled you with my title. This talk will not just be about &lt;a href="http://epidoc.sf.net/"&gt;EpiDoc&lt;/a&gt;. Instead, I'd like to use EpiDoc as an entrance point into some thoughts I've had about what we are doing here. About where we are going. I'd like to take EpiDoc as an example -- and the EAGLE 2014 Conference as a metaphor -- for something much larger: the whole disparate, polyvalent, heterarchical thing that we sometimes call "Épigraphie et électronique". Digital epigraphy. Res epigraphica digitalis.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Before we try to unpack how we got here and where we're going, I'd like to ask for your help in trying to illuminate who we are. I'd like you to join me in a little exercise in public self-identification. Not only is this an excellent way to help fill the generous block of time that the conference organizers have given me for this talk, it's also much less awkward than trooping out to the Place de la Sorbonne and doing trust falls on the edge of the fountain. ... Right?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Seriously. This conference brings together a range of people and projects that really have had no specific venue to meet, and so we are in some important ways unknown to each other. It's my hypothesis that, if we learn a bit about each other up front, we prime the pump of collaboration and exchange for the rest of the conference. After all, why do we travel to conferences at all if it is not for the richness of interacting with each other, both during sessions and outside them. OK, and as &lt;a href="https://www.kcl.ac.uk/artshums/depts/chs/people/academic/roueche.aspx"&gt;Charlotte Roueché&lt;/a&gt; is ever vigilant to remind us, for the museums.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;OK then, are you ready?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Independent of any formal position or any academic or professional credential, raise your hand if you would answer "yes" to this question: "Are you an epigraphist?"&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What about "are you an information scientist?"&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Historians?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Oh, yes, you can be more than one of these -- you'll recall I rolled out the word "heterarchy" in my introduction!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How about "Wikipedian?" "Cultural Heritage Professional?" "Programmer?" "Philologist?" "Computer Scientist?" "Archivist?" "Museologist?" "Linguist?" "Archaeologist?" "Librarian?" "Physicist?" "Engineer?" "Journalist?" "Clergy?"&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Phooey! No clergy!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Let's get at another distinction. How many of you would identify yourselves as teachers?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What about students?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Researchers? Administrators? Technicians? Interested lay persons?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;OK, now that we have your arms warmed up, let's move on to voices.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If you can read, speak, or understand a reasonable amount of the English language, please join me in saying "I understand English."&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ready? "I understand English."&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;OK. Now, if we can read, speak, or understand a reasonable amount of French, shall we say "Je comprends le français?"&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;"Je comprends le français."&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What about Arabic?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Bulgarian? Catalan? Flemish? German? Of course there are many more represented here, but I think you get my point.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;OK. Now let's build this rhetorical construct one step higher.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This one involves standing up if that's physically appropriate for you, so get yourselves ready! If cannot stand, by all means choose some other, more appropriate form of participation.&lt;br&gt;Independent of any formal position or any academic credential, I want you to stand up if you consider yourself a "scholar".&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Now, please stay standing -- or join those standing -- if you consider yourself a "student".&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Yes, I did it. I reintroduced the word "student" from another category of our exercise. I am not only a champion of heterarchy, but also of recursive redefinition.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And now, please stay standing -- or join those standing -- if you consider yourself an "enthusiast."&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If you're not standing, please stand if you can.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Now, pick out some one near you that you have not met. Shake their hand and introduce yourself. Ask them what they are so enthusiastic about that they were compelled to come to this conference!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Alright. Please resume your seats.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I think we're warmed up.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Let me encourage you to adopt a particular mindset while you are here at this conference. I hope that you will find it to be both amenable and familiar. It's the active recognition of the valuable traits we all share: intelligence, inquisitiveness, inventiveness, incisiveness, interdependence. Skill. Stamina. Uniqueness. Respect for the past. Congeniality.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I am here, in part, because I have a deep, inescapable interest in the study of ancient documents and in the application of computational methods and new media to their resurrection, preservation, and contemplation, and to their reintegration into the active cultural memory of the human people.&lt;br&gt;I have looked over &lt;a href="http://www.eagle-network.eu/about/events/eagle2014/agenda-programme/"&gt;the programme for this conference&lt;/a&gt;, and I have the distinct impression that your reasons for being here are somewhat similar to mine. I am delighted to have this opportunity to visit with old friends and fellow laborers. And to make the acquaintance of so many new ones. I expect to be dazzled by the &lt;a href="http://www.eagle-network.eu/about/events/eagle2014/digital-poster-exhibition/"&gt;posters&lt;/a&gt; and presentations to come. Are you as excited as I am?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;My title did promise some EpiDoc.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How many of you know EpiDoc?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How many of you know what EpiDoc is?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How many of you have heard of EpiDoc?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The word "EpiDoc" is a portmanteau, composed of the abbreviated word "epigraphy" and the abbreviated word "document" or "documentation" (I can't remember which). It has become a misnomer, as EpiDoc is used for much more than epigraphic documents and documentation. It has found &lt;a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-193.xml;query=;brand=default"&gt;a home in papyrology&lt;/a&gt; and in the study of texts transmitted to us from antiquity via the literary and book-copying cultures of the intervening ages. It has at least informed, if not been directly used, in other allied subfields like numismatics and sigillography. It's quite possible I'll learn this week of even broader usages.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;EpiDoc is a digital format and method for the encoding of both transcribed and descriptive information about ancient texts and the objects that supported and transmitted them. Formally, it is a wholly conformant customization of the &lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/"&gt;Text Encoding Initiative&lt;/a&gt;'s standard for the representation of texts in digital form. It is serialized in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XML"&gt;XML&lt;/a&gt; -- &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XML"&gt;the Extensible Markup Language&lt;/a&gt; -- a specification developed and maintained by the &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/"&gt;World-Wide Web Consortium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;EpiDoc is more than format and method. It is a community of practice. The term embraces all the people who learn, use, critique, and talk about EpiDoc. It also takes in the Guidelines, tools, and other helps that have been created and curated by those people. All of them are volunteers, scraping together the time to work on EpiDoc out of their personal time, their academic time, and out of the occasional grant. There has never been formal funding devoted to the development or maintenance of the EpiDoc guidelines or software. If you are a participant in the EpiDoc community, you are a hero.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;EpiDoc was born in the late 1990s in a weird little room in the northwest corner of the third floor of &lt;a href="http://classics.unc.edu/departmental-history/murphey-hall-history/"&gt;Murphey Hall&lt;/a&gt; on the campus of the &lt;a href="http://unc.edu/"&gt;University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill&lt;/a&gt;. The room is no longer there. It was consumed in a much-needed and long-promised renovation in 2003 or so. It was the old &lt;a href="http://classics.unc.edu/"&gt;Classics Department&lt;/a&gt; computer lab: a narrow space with a sturdy, home-made, built-in counter along two walls and a derelict bookshelf. It was part of a suite of three rooms, the most spacious of which was normally granted as an office to that year's graduate fellow.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The room had been appropriated by Classics graduate students &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/noelfiser"&gt;Noel Fiser&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://philomousos.com/"&gt;Hugh Cayless&lt;/a&gt;, together with classical archaeology graduate student &lt;a href="http://www.classics.ucla.edu/people/faculty/kmcdonnell/"&gt;Kathryn McDonnell&lt;/a&gt;, and myself (an interloper from the &lt;a href="http://history.unc.edu/what-we-study/ancient-history/"&gt;History Department&lt;/a&gt;). The Classics department -- motivated and led by these graduate students with I-forget-which-faculty-member serving as figurehead -- had secured internal university funding to digitize the department's collection of 35 millimeter slides and build a website for searching and displaying the resulting images. They bought a server with part of the grant. It soon earned the name &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alecto"&gt;Alecto&lt;/a&gt; after one of the Furies in Greek mythology. I've searched in vain for a picture of the lab, which at some point we sponge-painted in bright colors evocative of the frescoes from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santorini#Minoan_Akrotiri"&gt;Minoan Santorini&lt;/a&gt;. The world-wide web was less than a decade old.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I was unconscious then of the history of computing and the classics at Chapel Hill. To this day, I don't know if that suite of rooms had anything to do with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Woodley_Packard"&gt;David Packard&lt;/a&gt; and his time at Chapel Hill. At the &lt;a href="http://ciegl.classics.ox.ac.uk/"&gt;Epigraphic Congress in Oxford&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://vivo.brown.edu/display/jbodel"&gt;John Bodel&lt;/a&gt; pointed to &lt;a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/294681"&gt;Packard's Livy concordance&lt;/a&gt; as one of the seminal moments in the history of computing and the classics, and thus the history of digital epigraphy. I'd like to think that we intersected that heritage not just in method, but in geography.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I had entered the graduate program in ancient history in the fall of 1995. I had what I would later come to understand to have been a spectacular slate of courses for my first term: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Talbert"&gt;Richard Talbert&lt;/a&gt; on the Roman Republic, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerzy_Linderski"&gt;Jerzy Linderski&lt;/a&gt; on Roman Law, and &lt;a href="http://classics.unc.edu/people/faculty-2/george-houston/"&gt;George Houston&lt;/a&gt; on Latin Epigraphy.&lt;br&gt;Epigraphy was new to me. I had seen and even tried my hand at reading the odd Latin or Greek inscription, but I had no knowledge of the history or methods of discipline, and very little skill. As George taught it, the Latin Epigraphy course was focused on the research use of the published apparatus of Latin epigraphy. The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corpus_Inscriptionum_Latinarum"&gt;CIL&lt;/a&gt;. The journals. The regional and local corpora. What you could do with them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If I remember correctly, the &lt;a href="http://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/home"&gt;Epigraphic Database Heidelberg&lt;/a&gt; was not yet online, nor were the &lt;a href="http://epigraphy.packhum.org/inscriptions/"&gt;Packard Greek inscriptions&lt;/a&gt; (though you could search them on CDROM). Yes, the same Packard. Incidentally, I think we'll hear something very exciting about the Packard Greek Inscriptions in tomorrow's Linked Ancient World Data panel.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Anyway, at some point I came across the early version of what is now called the &lt;a href="http://www.manfredclauss.de/"&gt;Epigraphische Datenbank Clauss - Slaby&lt;/a&gt;, which was online. Back then it was a simple search engine for digital transcripts of the texts in the &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L'Ann%C3%A9e_%C3%A9pigraphique"&gt;L'Annee Epigraphique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; up from 1888 through 1993. Crucially, one could also download all the content in plain text files. If I understand it correctly, these texts were also destined for publication via the Heidelberg database (and eventually Rome too) after verification by autopsy or inspection of photographs or &lt;a href="http://blogs.cornell.edu/culconservation/2013/12/13/epigraphic-squeezes-part-i/"&gt;squeezes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;At some point, I got interested in abbreviations. My paper for George's class was focused on "the epigraphy of water" in Roman North Africa. I kept running across abbreviations in the inscriptions that didn't appear in any of the otherwise helpful lists one finds in &lt;a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/8330250"&gt;Cagnat&lt;/a&gt; or one of the other handbooks.  In retrospect, the reasons are obvious: the handbook author tailors the list of abbreviations to the texts and types of texts featured in the handbook itself. Selected for importance and range, the statistical distribution of textual types and language, and of features like abbreviation, are not the same as those for the entire corpus. So, what is a former programmer to do? Why not download the texts from Clauss' site and write a program to hunt for parentheses. The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leiden_Conventions"&gt;Leiden Conventions&lt;/a&gt; make parentheses a strong indicator of abbreviations that have been expanded by an editor, so the logic for the program seemed relatively straightforward.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Mercifully, the hacktastical code that I wrote to do this task has, I think, perished from the face of the earth. The results, which I serialized into HTML form, &lt;a href="http://classics.case.edu/asgle/bookshelf/abbreviations-in-latin-inscriptions/"&gt;may still be consulted on the website of the American Society of Greek and Latin Epigraphy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As useful as the results were, I was dissatisfied with the experience. The programming language I had used -- called "&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_(programming_language)"&gt;C&lt;/a&gt;" -- was not a very good fit for the kind of text processing involved. Moreover, as good as the Leiden Conventions are, parentheses are used for things other than abbreviations. So, there was manual post-processing to be done. And then there were the edge cases, like abbreviations that stand alone in one document, but are incorporated into longer abbreviations in others. And then there were expanded use cases: searching for text in one inscription that was abbreviated in another. Searching for abbreviations or other strings in text that was transcribed from the original, rather than in editorial supplement or restoration. And I wanted a format and software tools that was a better fit for textual data and this class of problems.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;XML and the associated &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XSL"&gt;Extensible Stylesheet Language (XSL)&lt;/a&gt; -- both then fairly new -- seemed like a good alternative approach. So I found myself confronted with a choice: should I take XML and invent my own schema for epigraphic texts, or should I adopt and adapt something someone else had already created? This consideration -- to make or to take -- is still of critical importance not only for XML, but for any format specification or standards definition process. It's important too for most digital projects. What will you build and on what will you build it?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are pros and cons. By adopting an existing standard or tool, you can realize a number of benefits. You don't reinvent the wheel. You build on the strengths and the lessons of others. You can discuss problems and approaches with others who are using the same method. You probably make it easier to share and exchange your tools and any data you create. It's possible that many of the logic problems that aren't obvious to you at the beginning have already been encountered by the pioneers.&lt;br&gt;But standards and specifications can also be walled gardens in which decisions and expert knowledge are hoarded by the founders or another elite group. They can undermine openness and innovation. They can present a significant learning curve. You can use a complex standard and find that you've built a submarine to cross the Seine. Something simpler might have worked better.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Back then, there was a strong narrative around warning people off the cavalier creation of new XML schemas. The injunction was articulated in a harsh metaphor: "every time someone creates a new schema, a kitten dies." Behind this ugly metaphor was the recognition of another potential pitfall: building an empty cathedral. Your data format -- your personal or parochial specification -- might embody everything you imagined or needed, but be largely useless to, or unused by, anyone else.&lt;br&gt;So, being a cat lover, and being lazy (all the best programmers are lazy), I went looking for an existing schema. I found it in the Text Encoding Initiative. Whether the TEI (and EpiDoc) fit your particular use case is something only you can decide. For me, at that time and since, it was a good fit. I was particularly attracted to a core concept of the TEI: one should encode the intent behind the formatting and structure in a document -- the semantics of the authorial and editorial tasks -- rather than just the specifics of the formatting. So, where the Leiden Conventions would have us use parentheses to mark the editorial expansion of an abbreviation, the TEI gives us XML elements that mean "&lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-abbr.html"&gt;abbreviation&lt;/a&gt;" and "&lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-expan.html"&gt;expansion&lt;/a&gt;." Where a modern Latin epigraphic edition would use a subscript dot to indicate that the identity of a character is ambiguous without reference to context, the TEI gives us the "&lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-unclear.html"&gt;unclear&lt;/a&gt;" element.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This encoding approach pays off. I'll give just one example. For a few years now, I've been helping &lt;a href="http://www.efeo.fr/en/biographies/notices/griffiths.htm"&gt;Arlo Griffiths&lt;/a&gt; (who directs &lt;a href="http://www.efeo.fr/base.php?code=223"&gt;the Jakarta research center of the École française d'Extrême-Orient&lt;/a&gt;) to develop &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/publications/inscriptions/campa/"&gt;a corpus of the surviving inscriptions of the Campa Kingdoms&lt;/a&gt;. This is a small corpus, perhaps 400 extant inscriptions, from coastal Vietnam, that includes texts in both Sanskrit and the incompletely understood Old Cam language. The script involved has not yet made its way into the &lt;a href="http://www.unicode.org/"&gt;Unicode&lt;/a&gt; specification. The standard transliteration scheme for this script, as well as some of the other editorial conventions used in the publication of Cam inscriptions, overlaps and conflicts with the Leiden conventions. But with TEI/EpiDoc there is no confusion or ambiguity. The XML says what the editor means to say, and the conventions of transcription are preserved unchanged, perhaps someday to be converted programmatically to Unicode when Unicode is ready.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;EpiDoc transitioned from a personal project to a public one when another potential use case came along. For some time, a committee commissioned by the &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.aiegl.org/"&gt;Association Internationale d'Épigraphie Grecque et Latine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; had been working under the direction of &lt;a href="http://viaf.org/viaf/6103425"&gt;Silvio Panciera&lt;/a&gt;, then the chair of Latin epigraphy at La Sapienza in Rome. Their goal was to establish a comprehensive database of Greek and Latin inscriptions, primarily for the purpose of searching the texts and associated descriptive information or metadata. It was &lt;a href="http://www.queens.ox.ac.uk/academics/fellows/governing-body/charles-crowther/"&gt;Charles Crowther&lt;/a&gt; at Oxford's new &lt;a href="http://www.csad.ox.ac.uk/"&gt;Centre for the Study of Ancient Documents&lt;/a&gt; who put me in contact with the committee. And it was Charles who championed the eventual recommendation of the committee that the system they envisioned must be able to import and export structured documents governed by a standard schema. He was thinking of EpiDoc.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Many years have passed and many things have changed, and I'm forced to leave out the names of so many people whose hard work and acumen has brought about those changes. Here in Paris today Panciera's vision stands on the cusp of realization. It has also been transcended, for we are not here to talk about a standalone textual database or a federation of such, but about the incorporation of Greek and Latin epigraphy -- in all its historiographical variety and multiplicity of reception -- into the digital cultural heritage system of Europe (Europeana) and into the independent digital repository of a global people: Wikipedia and Wikidata. That EpiDoc can play a role in this grand project just blows me away.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And it's not just about EAGLE, Europeana, Wikipedia, and EpiDoc. It's about a myriad other databases, websites, images, techniques, projects, technologies, and tools. It's about you and the work that you do.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Even as we congratulate ourselves on our achievements and the importance of our mission, I hope you'll let me encourage you to keep thinking forward. We are doing an increasingly good job of bringing computational approaches into many aspects of the scholarly communication process. But plenty remains to be done. We are starting to make the transition from using computer hardware and software to make conventional books and digital imitations thereof; "born digital" is starting to mean something more than narrative forms in PDF and HTML, designed to be read directly by each single human user and, through them, digested into whatever database, notebook, or other research support system that person uses. We are now publishing data that is increasingly designed for harvesting and analyzing by automated agents and that is increasingly less encumbered by outdated and obstructive intellectual property regimes. Over time, our colleagues will begin to spend less time seeking and ingesting data, and more time analyzing, interpreting, and communicating results. We are also lowering the barriers to appreciation and participation in global heritage by a growing and more connected and more vulnerable global people.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Will we succeed in this experiment? Will we succeed in helping to build a mature and responsible global culture in which heritage is treasured, difference is honored, and a deep common cause embraced and protected? Will we say three years from now that building that database or encoding those texts in EpiDoc was the right choice? In a century, will our work be accessible and relevant to our successors and descendants? In 5? In 10?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I do not know. But I am thrilled, honored, and immensely encouraged to see you here, walking this ancient road and blazing this ambitious and hopeful new trail. This is our opportunity to help reunite the world's people and an important piece of their heritage. We are a force against the recasting of history into political rhetoric. We stand against the convenient ignorance of our past failures and their causes. We are the antidote to the destruction of ancient statues of the Buddha, to the burning of undocumented manuscripts, to papyri for sale on eBay, to fields of holes in satellite images where once there was an unexcavated ancient site.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Let's do this thing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</description><category>conferences</category><category>digclass</category><category>eagle2014</category><category>epidoc</category><category>epigraphy</category><category>horothesia</category><category>inscriptions</category><category>openness</category><category>papyrology</category><category>tei</category><category>walled gardens</category><category>xml</category><category>xslt</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2014/10/eighteen-years-of-epidoc-now-what/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 23:06:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Batch XML validation at the command line</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2014/04/batch-xml-validation-at-command-line/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Updated: 8 August, 2017 to reflect changes in the installation pattern for jing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Against a &lt;a href="http://relaxng.org/"&gt;RelaxNG&lt;/a&gt; schema. I had help figuring this out from &lt;a href="http://philomousos.com/"&gt;Hugh&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://ryanfb.github.io/"&gt;Ryan&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href="http://blogs.library.duke.edu/dcthree/"&gt;DC3&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;$ find &lt;i&gt;{searchpath}&lt;/i&gt; -name "*.xml" -print | parallel --tag jing &lt;i&gt;{relaxngpath}&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;The &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;find&lt;/span&gt; command hunts down all files ending with ".xml" in the directory tree under &lt;i&gt;searchpath&lt;/i&gt;. The &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;parallel&lt;/span&gt; command takes that list of files and fires off (in parallel) a &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;jing&lt;/span&gt; validation run for each of them. The &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;--tag&lt;/span&gt; option passed to &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;jing&lt;/span&gt; ensures we get the name of the file passed through with each error message. This turns out (in general terms as seen by me) to be much faster than running each &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;jing&lt;/span&gt; call in sequence, e.g. with the &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;--exec&lt;/span&gt; primary in &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;find&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As I'm running on a Mac, I had to install &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/parallel/"&gt;GNU Parallel&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://www.thaiopensource.com/relaxng/jing.html"&gt;Jing RelaxNG Validator&lt;/a&gt;. That's what &lt;a href="http://brew.sh/"&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt; is for:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;&lt;strike&gt;$ brew install jing&lt;/strike&gt;&lt;br&gt;$ brew install jing-trang&lt;br&gt;$ brew install parallel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;NB: you may have to install a down version of Java before you can get the jing-trang formula to work in homebrew (e.g., &lt;span style="font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;"&gt;brew install java6&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What's the context, you ask? I have lots of reasons to want to be able to do this. The proximal cause was batch-validating all the &lt;a href="http://epidoc.sf.net/"&gt;EpiDoc&lt;/a&gt; XML files for the inscriptions that are included in the &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/publications/inscriptions/campa/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Corpus of Campā Inscriptions&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; before regenerating the site for an update today. I wanted to see quickly if there were any encoding errors in the XML that might blow up the XSL transforms we use to generate the site. So, what I actually ran was: &lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;$ curl -O http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng&lt;br&gt;$ find ./texts/xml -name '*.xml' -print | parallel --tag jing tei-epidoc.rng&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Thanks to everybody who built all these tools!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</description><category>collaboration</category><category>efficiency</category><category>epidoc</category><category>horothesia</category><category>tei</category><category>tools</category><category>validation</category><category>xml</category><category>xslt</category><category>yaks</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2014/04/batch-xml-validation-at-command-line/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 00:07:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Citing Sources in Digital Annotations</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2013/04/citing-sources-in-digital-annotations/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm collaborating with other folks both in and outside &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/"&gt;ISAW&lt;/a&gt; on a variety of digital scholarly projects in which &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/LinkedData.html"&gt;Linked Open Data&lt;/a&gt; is playing a big role. We're using the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resource_Description_Framework"&gt;Resource Description Framework (RDF)&lt;/a&gt; to provide descriptive information for, and make cross-project assertions about, a variety of entities of interest and the data associated with them (places, people, themes/subjects, creative works, bibliographic items, and manuscripts and other text-bearing objects). So, for example, I can produce the following assertions in RDF (using the &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TeamSubmission/turtle/"&gt;Terse RDF Triple Language, or TuRTLe&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre style="font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; color: #000000; background-color: #eee;font-size: 12px;border: 1px dashed #999999;line-height: 14px;padding: 5px; overflow: auto; width: 100%"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45&amp;gt; a &amp;lt;http://geovocab.org/spatial#Feature&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  rdfs:label "Serugh" ;&lt;br&gt;  rdfs:comment "An ancient city where Jacob of Serugh was bishop."@en ;&lt;br&gt;  foaf:primaryTopicOf &amp;lt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suruç&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  owl:sameAs &amp;lt;http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/658405#this&amp;gt; .&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;This means: 'There's a resource identified with the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_resource_identifier"&gt;Uniform Resource Identifier (URI)&lt;/a&gt; "http://syriaca.org/place/45" about which the following is asserted: &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;it is a "Feature" as defined in the &lt;a href="http://geovocab.org/spatial.html"&gt;NeoGeo Spatial Ontology&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-schema/#ch_label"&gt;human-readable version of its name&lt;/a&gt; is "Serugh";&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-schema/#ch_comment"&gt;a human-readable description&lt;/a&gt; (in the English language) of it is "An ancient city where Jacob of Serugh was bishop.";&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;it is &lt;a href="http://xmlns.com/foaf/spec/#term_isPrimaryTopicOf"&gt;the primary topic of a document&lt;/a&gt; that is identified by the URI "http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suruç"; and&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;it is &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/owl-ref/#sameAs-def"&gt;the same resource as&lt;/a&gt; that identified by another URI: "http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/658405#this".'&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br&gt;(Folks familiar with what &lt;a href="http://sgillies.net/"&gt;Sean Gillies&lt;/a&gt; has done for the &lt;a href="https://github.com/isawnyu/pleiades-rdf"&gt;Pleiades RDF&lt;/a&gt; will recognize my debt to him in the what proceeds.) &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But there are plenty of cases in which just issuing a couple of &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-rdf-concepts-20040210/#dfn-rdf-triple"&gt;triples&lt;/a&gt; to encode an assertion about something isn't sufficient; we need to be able to assign responsibility/origin for those assertions and to link them to supporting argument and evidence (i.e., standard scholarly citation practice). For this purpose, we're very pleased by the &lt;a href="http://www.openannotation.org/"&gt;Open Annotation Collaboration&lt;/a&gt;, whose &lt;i&gt;Open Annotation Data Model&lt;/i&gt; was recently updated and expanded in the form of a &lt;a href="http://www.openannotation.org/spec/core/"&gt;W3C Community Draft (8 February 2013)&lt;/a&gt; (the participants in &lt;a href="http://pelagios-project.blogspot.com/"&gt;Pelagios&lt;/a&gt; use basic OAC annotations to assert geographic relationships between their data and Pleiades places).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A basic OADM annotation uses a series of RDF triples to link together a "target" (the thing you want to make an assertion about) and a "body" (the content of your assertion). You can think of them as footnotes. The "target" is the range of text after which you put your footnote number (only in OADM you can add a footnote to any real, conceptual, or digital thing you can identify) and the "body" is the content of the footnote itself. &lt;a href="http://www.openannotation.org/spec/core/core.html#BodyTarget"&gt;The OADM draft formally explains this structure in section 2.1&lt;/a&gt;. This lets me add an annotation to the resource from our example above (the ancient city of Serugh) by using the URI "http://syriaca.org/place/45" as the target of an annotation) thus: &lt;br&gt;&lt;pre style="font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; color: #000000; background-color: #eee;font-size: 12px;border: 1px dashed #999999;line-height: 14px;padding: 5px; overflow: auto; width: 100%"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45/anno/desc6&amp;gt; a oa:Annotation ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:hasBody &amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45/anno/desc6/body&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:hasTarget &amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:motivatedBy oa:describing ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:annotatedBy &amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/editors.xml#tcarlson&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:annotatedAt "2013-04-03T00:00:01Z" ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:serializedBy &amp;lt;https://github.com/paregorios/srpdemo1/blob/master/xsl/place2ttl.xsl&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  oa:serializedAt "2013-04-17T13:35:05.771-05:00" .&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45/anno/desc6/body&amp;gt; a cnt:ContentAsText, dctypes:Text ;&lt;br&gt;  cnt:chars "an ancient town, formerly located near Sarug."@en ;&lt;br&gt;  dc:format "text/plain" ;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;I hope you'll forgive me for not spelling that all out in plain text, as all the syntax and terms are explained in the OADM. What I'm concerned about in this blog post is really what the OADM &lt;strong&gt;doesn't&lt;/strong&gt; explicitly tell me how to do, namely: show that the annotation body is actually a quotation from a published book. The verb oa:annotatedBy lets me indicate that the annotation itself was made (i.e., the footnote was written) by a resource identified by the URI "http://syriaca.org/editors.xml#tcarlson". If I'd given you a few more triples, you could have figured out that that resource is a real person named Thomas Carlson, who is one of the editors working on the &lt;a href="http://syriaca.org"&gt;Syriac Reference Portal project&lt;/a&gt;. But how do I indicate (as he very much wants to do because he's a responsible scholar and has no interest in plagiarizing anyone) that he's deliberately quoting a book called &lt;a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/255043315"&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Scattered Pearls: A History of Syriac Literature and Sciences&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;? Here's what I came up with (using terms from &lt;a href="http://purl.org/spar/cito/"&gt;Citation Typing Ontology&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/"&gt;DCMI Metadata Terms&lt;/a&gt;): &lt;br&gt;&lt;pre style="font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; color: #000000; background-color: #eee;font-size: 12px;border: 1px dashed #999999;line-height: 14px;padding: 5px; overflow: auto; width: 100%"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;http://syriaca.org/place/45/anno/desc7/body&amp;gt; a cnt:ContentAsText, dctypes:Text ;&lt;br&gt;  cnt:chars "a small town in the Mudar territory, between Ḥarran and Jarabulus. [Modern name, Suruç (tr.)]"@en ;&lt;br&gt;  dc:format "text/plain" ;&lt;br&gt;  cito:citesAsSourceDocument &amp;lt;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/255043315&amp;gt; ;&lt;br&gt;  dcterms:biblographicCitation  "The Scattered Pearls: A History of Syriac Literature and Sciences, p. 558"@en .&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;The addition of the triple containing cito:citesAsSourceDocument lets me make a machine-actionable link to the additional structured bibliographic data about the book that's available at Worldcat (but it doesn't say anything about page numbers!). The addition of the triple containing dcterms:bibliographicCitation lets me provide a human-readable citation. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'd love to have feedback on this approach from folks in the OAC, CITO, DCTERMS, and general linked data communities. Could I do better? Should I do something differently? &lt;br&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;br&gt;The SRP team is currently evaluating a sample batch of such annotations, which you're also welcome to view. The &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/srpdemo1/tree/master/rdf/place"&gt;RDF can be found here&lt;/a&gt;. These files are generated from &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/srpdemo1/tree/master/xml/places"&gt;the TEI XML here&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/srpdemo1/blob/master/xsl/place2ttl.xsl"&gt;the XSLT here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;</description><category>bibliography</category><category>collaboration</category><category>concordia</category><category>data</category><category>horothesia</category><category>interop</category><category>isaw</category><category>lawdi</category><category>linkeddata</category><category>LOD</category><category>neogeography</category><category>patterns</category><category>pelagios</category><category>pleiades</category><category>rdf</category><category>tei</category><category>xml</category><category>xslt</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2013/04/citing-sources-in-digital-annotations/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2013 23:35:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>First pass at extracting useful data from my dissertation</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/05/first-pass-at-extracting-useful-data/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;You'll find context in &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2012/05/open-access-epigraphic-evidence-for.html"&gt;yesterday's post on the dissertation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It turns out it wasn't as hard as I anticipated to start getting useful information extracted from my born-digital-for-printing-on-dead-trees dissertation. Here's a not-yet-perfect xml serialization (borrowing tags from the TEI) of "instance" information found in the diss narrative:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/demarc/blob/master/xml/instances.xml"&gt;https://github.com/paregorios/demarc/blob/master/xml/instances.xml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Each instance is a historical event (or in some cases event series) relating to boundary demarcation or dispute within the empire. Here's a comparison between the original formatting for paper and the xml.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For paper:&lt;br&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-nu_yP3-852Q/T71bfc35IOI/AAAAAAAAAQE/MTtfTmuT0PQ/s1600/wookie.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left:1em; margin-right:1em"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="390" width="400" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-nu_yP3-852Q/T71bfc35IOI/AAAAAAAAAQE/MTtfTmuT0PQ/s400/wookie.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;br&gt;XML:&lt;br&gt;&lt;pre style="font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; color: #000000; background-color: #eee;font-size: 12px;border: 1px dashed #999999;line-height: 14px;padding: 5px; overflow: auto; width: 100%"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;div type="instance" xml:id="INST9"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;  &amp;lt;idno type="original"&amp;gt;INST9&amp;lt;/idno&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;  &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;A Negotiated Boundary between the &amp;lt;placeName &lt;br&gt;    type="ancient"&amp;gt;Zamucci&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt; and the &amp;lt;placeName &lt;br&gt;    type="ancient"&amp;gt;Muduciuvi&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;  &amp;lt;p rend="indent"&amp;gt;Burton 2000, no. 78&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Date(s): &amp;lt;date&amp;gt;AD 86&amp;lt;/date&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;  &amp;lt;p type="treDisputeStatement"&amp;gt;This boundary marker was placed in &lt;br&gt;    accordance with the agreement of both parties (&amp;lt;foreign xml:lang="la"&amp;gt;ex &lt;br&gt;    conven/tione utrarumque nationum&amp;lt;/foreign&amp;gt;), and therefore may be taken as&lt;br&gt;    evidence of a &amp;lt;hi rend="bold"&amp;gt;boundary dispute&amp;lt;/hi&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;  &amp;lt;p rend="indent"&amp;gt;This single boundary marker from coastal &amp;lt;placeName &lt;br&gt;    type="modern"&amp;gt;Libya&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt; provides the only evidence for the resolution&lt;br&gt;    of a boundary dispute between these two indigenous peoples. The date of the &lt;br&gt;    demarcation, as calculated from the imperial titulature, places the event in &lt;br&gt;    the same year as the reported ‘destruction’ of the &amp;lt;placeName &lt;br&gt;    type="ancient"&amp;gt;Nasamones&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt; by &amp;lt;placeName type="ancient"&amp;gt;Legio III &lt;br&gt;    Augusta&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt; as a consequence of a tax revolt in which tax collectors &lt;br&gt;    were killed.&amp;lt;note n="286"&amp;gt; Zonaras 11.19. &amp;lt;/note&amp;gt; It is not clear whether &lt;br&gt;    the boundary action was related to the conflict, or merely took advantage of&lt;br&gt;    the temporary presence of the legionary legate in what ought to have been&lt;br&gt;    part of the proconsular province. Surviving documentation for proconsuls&lt;br&gt;    during the 80s AD is incomplete, and therefore we cannot say who was&lt;br&gt;    governing &amp;lt;placeName type="ancient"&amp;gt;Africa Proconsularis &amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt;at the &lt;br&gt;    time of this demarcation.&amp;lt;note n="287"&amp;gt; Thomasson 1996, 45-48. &amp;lt;/note&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;    Neither party seems to have been related to the &amp;lt;placeName &lt;br&gt;    type="ancient"&amp;gt;Nasamones&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt;; rather, they are thought to be sub-&lt;br&gt;    tribes of the &amp;lt;placeName type="ancient"&amp;gt;Macae.&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt;&amp;lt;note &lt;br&gt;    n="288"&amp;gt;Mattingly 1994, 27-28, 32, 74, 76.. &amp;lt;/note&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One thing that made this a lot easier than it might of been was the way I used styles in Microsoft Word back when I created the original version of the document. Rather than just painting formatting onto my text for headings, paragraphs, strings of characters, and so forth, I created a custom "style" for each type of thing I wanted to paint (e.g., an "instance heading" or a "personal name"). I associated the desired visual formatting with each of these, but the names themselves (since the captured semantic distinctions that I was interested in) provided hooks today for writing this stuff out as sort-of TEI XML.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's more to do, obviously, but this was a satisfying first step.</description><category>demarc</category><category>horothesia</category><category>openness</category><category>tei</category><category>xml</category><category>xslt</category><category>yaks</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/05/first-pass-at-extracting-useful-data/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2012 03:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Give Me the Zotero Item Keys!</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/02/give-me-zotero-item-keys/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;I fear and hope that this post will cause someone smarter than me to pipe up and say UR DOIN IT WRONG ITZ EZ LYK DIS ...&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Here's the use case:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/"&gt;Integrating Digital Papyrology project&lt;/a&gt; (and friends) have a &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/groups/papyrology"&gt;Zotero group library&lt;/a&gt; populated with 1,445 bibliographic records that were developed on the basis of an old, built-by-hand &lt;a href="http://library.duke.edu/rubenstein/scriptorium/papyrus/texts/clist.html"&gt;Checklist of Editions of Greek and Latin Papyri (etc.)&lt;/a&gt;. A lot of checking and improving was done to the data in Zotero.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Separately, there's now a much larger pile of bibliographic records related to papyrology that were collected (on different criteria) by the &lt;a href="http://www.ulb.ac.be/philo/cpeg/bp.htm"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Bibliographie Papyrologique&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; project. They have been machine-converted (into &lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/"&gt;TEI&lt;/a&gt; document fragments) from a &lt;i&gt;sui generis&lt;/i&gt; Filemaker Pro database and are now &lt;a href="http://papyri.info/bibliosearch"&gt;hosted via papyri.info&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="https://github.com/papyri/idp.data/tree/master/Biblio"&gt;the raw data is on github&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There is considerable overlap between these two datasets, but also signifcant divergeance. We want to merge "matching" records in a carefully supervised way, making sure not to lose any of the extra goodness that BP adds to the data but taking full advantage of the corrections and improvements that were done to the Checklist data.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We started by doing an export-to-RDF of the Zotero data and, as a first step, that was banged up (programmatically) against the TEI data on the basis of titles. Probable matches were hand-checked and a resulting pairing of papyri.info bibliographic ID numbers against Zotero short titles was produced. You can see &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/biblio-matching/matches-2012-02.xml"&gt;the resulting XML here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;I should point out that almost everything up to here including the creation and improvement of the data, as well as anything below regarding the bibliography in papyri.info, is the work of others. Those others include Gabriel Bodard, Hugh Cayless, James Cowey, Carmen Lantz, Adam Prins, Josh Sosin, and Jen Thum. And the BP team. And probably others I'm forgetting at the moment or who have labored out of my sight. I erect this shambles of a lean-to on the shoulders of giants.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To guide the work of our bibliographic researchers in analyzing the matched records, I wanted to create an HTML file that looks like this:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace; font-size: small;"&gt;Checklist Short Title = Papyri.info ID number and Full Title String&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace; font-size: x-small;"&gt;BGU 10 = PI idno 7513: Papyrusurkunden aus ptolemäischer Zeit. (Ägyptische Urkunden aus den Staatlichen Museen zu Berlin. Griechische Urkunden. X. Band.)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace; font-size: x-small;"&gt;etc.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;In that list, I wanted items to the left to be linked to the online view of the Zotero record at zotero.org and items on the right linked to the online view of the TEI record at papyri.info. The XML data we got from the initial match process provided the papyri.info bibliographic ID numbers, from which it's easy to construct the corresponding URIs, e.g., &lt;a href="http://papyri.info/biblio/7513"&gt;http://papyri.info/biblio/7513&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But Zotero presented a problem. URIs for bibliographic records in Zotero server use alphanumeric "item keys" like this: CJ3WSG3S (as in &lt;a href="https://www.zotero.org/groups/papyrology/items/itemKey/CJ3WSG3S/"&gt;https://www.zotero.org/groups/papyrology/items/itemKey/CJ3WSG3S/&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;That item key string is not, to my knowledge, included in any of the export formats produced by the Zotero desktop client, nor is it surfaced in its interface (argh).&lt;/b&gt; It appears possible to hunt them down programmatically via the &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/support/dev/server_api/read_api"&gt;Zotero Read API&lt;/a&gt;, though I haven't tried it for reasons that will be explained shortly. It is certainly possible to hunt for them manually via the web interface, but I'm not going to try that for more than about 3 records.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;How I got the Zotero item keys&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, I have two choices at this point: write some code to automate hunting the item keys via the Zotero Read API or crack open the Zotero &lt;a href="http://www.sqlite.org/"&gt;SQLLite&lt;/a&gt; database on my local client and see if the item keys are lurking in there too. Since I'm on a newish laptop on which I hadn't yet installed &lt;a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/xcode/id448457090?mt=12"&gt;XCode&lt;/a&gt;, which seems to be a prerequisite to installing support for a &lt;a href="http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0405/"&gt;Python virtual environment&lt;/a&gt;, which is the preferred way to get &lt;a href="http://www.pip-installer.org/en/latest/installing.html"&gt;pip&lt;/a&gt;, which is the preferred install prerequisite for &lt;a href="https://github.com/urschrei/pyzotero"&gt;pyzotero&lt;/a&gt;, which is the python wrapper for the Zotero API, I had to make some choices about which yaks to shave.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I decided to start the (notoriously slow) XCode download yak and then have a go at the SQLLite yak while that was going on.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I grabbed the trial version of &lt;a href="http://www.razorsql.com/"&gt;RazorSQL&lt;/a&gt; (which looked like a good shortcut after a few minutes of Googling), made a copy of my Zotero database, and started poking around. I thought about looking for detailed documentation (&lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/support/zotero_data"&gt;starting here I guess&lt;/a&gt;), but direct inspection started yielding results so I just kept going commando-style. It became clear at once that I wasn't going to find a single table containing my bibliographic entries. The Zotero client database is all normalized and modularized and stuff. So I viewed table columns and table contents as necessary and started building a SQL query to get at what I wanted. Here's what ultimately worked:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;pre style="background-color: #eeeeee; border: 1px dashed #999999; color: black; font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; font-size: 12px; line-height: 14px; overflow: auto; padding: 5px; width: 100%;"&gt;&lt;code&gt;SELECT itemDataValues.value, items.key FROM items &lt;br&gt;INNER JOIN libraries ON items.libraryID = libraries.libraryID&lt;br&gt;INNER JOIN groups ON libraries.libraryID = groups.libraryID&lt;br&gt;INNER JOIN itemData ON items.itemID = itemData.itemID&lt;br&gt;INNER JOIN itemDataValues ON itemData.valueID = itemDataValues.valueID&lt;br&gt;INNER JOIN fields ON itemData.fieldID = fields.fieldID&lt;br&gt;WHERE groups.name= "Papyrology" AND fields.fieldID=116&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;The SELECT statement gets me two values for each match dredged up by the rest of the query: a value stored in the itemDataValues table and a key stored in the items table. The various JOINs are used to get us close to the specific value (i.e., a short title) that we want. 116 in the fieldID field of the fields table corresponds to the short title field you see in your Zotero client. I found that out by inspecting the fields table; I could have used more JOINs to be able to use the string "shortTitle" in my WHERE clause, but that would have just taken more time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The results of that query against my database looked like this:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;pre style="background-color: #eeeeee; border: 1px dashed #999999; color: black; font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; font-size: 12px; line-height: 14px; overflow: auto; padding: 5px; width: 100%;"&gt;&lt;code&gt;P.Cair.Preis.    2245UKTH&lt;br&gt;CPR 18           26K8TAJT&lt;br&gt;P.Bodm. 28       282XKDE9&lt;br&gt;P.Gebelen        29ETKPXC&lt;br&gt;O.Krok           2BBMS7NS&lt;br&gt;P.Carlsb. 5      2D2ZNT4C&lt;br&gt;P.Mich.Aphrod.   2DTD2NIZ&lt;br&gt;P.Carlsb. 9      2FWF6T6I&lt;br&gt;P.Col. 1         2G4CF756&lt;br&gt;P.Lond.Copt. 2   2GAEU5QP&lt;br&gt;P.Harr. 1        2GCCNGJV&lt;br&gt;O.Deir el-Bahari 2GH3FEA2&lt;br&gt;P.Harrauer       2H3T6EU2&lt;br&gt;(etc).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, copy that tabular result out of the RazorSQL GUI, paste it into a new &lt;a href="http://www.libreoffice.org/"&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/a&gt; spreadsheet and save it and I've got &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/biblio-matching/zdump-content.xml"&gt;an XML file&lt;/a&gt; that I can dip into from &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/biblio-matching/matches2html.xsl"&gt;the XSLT I had already started on&lt;/a&gt; to produce my HTML view.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/biblio-matching/matches-2012-02.html"&gt;Here's the resulting HTML file&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;On we go.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Oh, and for those paying attention to such things, XCode finished downloading about two-thirds of the way through this process ...&lt;/i&gt;</description><category>bibliography</category><category>horothesia</category><category>papyrology</category><category>tei</category><category>xml</category><category>xslt</category><category>yaks</category><category>zotero</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2012/02/give-me-zotero-item-keys/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2012 04:04:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Flavia Faustina, version 3: chi-rho, dolium, multiple editors, rationale</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2010/12/flavia-faustina-version-3-chi-rho/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="https://github.com/ryanfb/"&gt;Ryan Baumann&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://history.illinoisstate.edu/faculty_staff/biographydetail.asp?u=gtsouva"&gt;Georgia Tsouvala&lt;/a&gt; have joined the mob!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ryan forked &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/Mob-Epigraphy"&gt;my Mob Epigraphy repository on github&lt;/a&gt; and added markup to the &lt;a href="http://epidoc.sf.net/"&gt;EpiDoc&lt;/a&gt; XML file to represent the Chi-Rho and &lt;i&gt;dolium&lt;/i&gt;(?) that appear below the inscribed text. Then he sent me a pull request. &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/Mob-Epigraphy/commit/052c32fb8adc4e4aa8535340039cb54547754563"&gt;I merged his changes&lt;/a&gt; and pushed them back to github, and then &lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/Mob-Epigraphy/commit/a0104b7c004ec33eb41839c757d8f5c1fad09719"&gt;I pushed a few more modifications&lt;/a&gt; to show his contribution in the EpiDoc/TEI header and to modify the stylesheets to handle whitespace and multiple editors better (and to write out an HTML doctype). Here's the result:&lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/mob-epigraphy/st-paul-outside/flavia-faustina/3/"&gt;Flavia Faustina 3 HTML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/Mob-Epigraphy/blob/a0104b7c004ec33eb41839c757d8f5c1fad09719/st-paul-outside/flavia-faustina.xml"&gt;Flavia Faustina 3 EpiDoc XML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;Ryan's change -- which parallels the treatment in ICVR II as reported via EDB -- raises some questions in my mind:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Is the second illustration really a &lt;i&gt;dolium&lt;/i&gt;? It doesn't look that much like what's illustrated at &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dolium"&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dolium&lt;/a&gt;. Why would a &lt;i&gt;dolium&lt;/i&gt; appear on a Christian sepulchral inscription? Maybe someone like &lt;a href="http://sebastianheath.com/"&gt;Sebastian Heath&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://kcl.academia.edu/CharlotteTupman"&gt;Charlotte Tupman&lt;/a&gt; will have an idea about that.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Are those two items really glyphs that should be "read" as part of the inscription and therefore marked up using the &lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-g.html"&gt;TEI "g" element&lt;/a&gt; (as Ryan has done), or should they be treated as figures or illustrations and therefore marked up a different way? If they are "glyphs", then what would be the corresponding &lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-glyph.html"&gt;glyph definition markup&lt;/a&gt; (if any) and where should it go in an EpiDoc file? Maybe someone like &lt;a href="http://wiki.digitalclassicist.org/User:GabrielBodard"&gt;Gabriel Bodard&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://eer.hypotheses.org/"&gt;Marion Lamé&lt;/a&gt; will have an opinion about that.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;div&gt;Meanwhile, Georgia wrote to me as follows:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;I like &lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/mob-epigraphy/st-paul-outside/flavia-faustina/2/"&gt;version 2&lt;/a&gt;. For one, I could see it and read it without any problems; something I could not do with &lt;a href="http://www.atlantides.org/mob-epigraphy/st-paul-outside/flavia-faustina/1/"&gt;version 1&lt;/a&gt;. I like the idea of being able to see pictures, texts, and translations of inscriptions on a single page. My question is: what are you trying to do here? What's the purpose, goal, etc. of Mob Epigraphy? And how can others help, contribute, etc.?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;My goal with &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/search/label/mob-epigraphy"&gt;Mob Epigraphy&lt;/a&gt; is two-fold. First, I want to create more on-line, open examples of real inscriptions marked up in EpiDoc. Secondly, I want to see how far we can push an openly collaborative model in the practice of digital epigraphy, welcoming all interested parties in editing the text and pushing the boundaries on what we can and can't do with standard encoding and web publication.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How to contribute? There are many ways. This post highlights two examples. Ryan saw something missing and, exploiting the digital collaboration infrastructure provided by github, pitched in to fill the gap. Georgia had comments and questions and, after having some trouble with Blogger's comment functionality, sent me an email. Both are great ways to contribute, and I bet readers of this post can come up with more -- like suggesting answers to my questions above, or proposing more robust or interesting documentation of the inscription or elaboration of the encoding or HTML representation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2010/12/flavia-faustina-version-2-style.html"&gt;Previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>collaboration</category><category>epidoc</category><category>epigraphy</category><category>horothesia</category><category>inscriptions</category><category>mob-epigraphy</category><category>publications</category><category>tei</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2010/12/flavia-faustina-version-3-chi-rho/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2010 03:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Digital Archimedes Palimpsest</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/10/digital-archimedes-palimpsest/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This just in:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Ten years ago today, a private American collector purchased the Archimedes Palimpsest. Since that time he has guided and funded the project to conserve, image, and study the manuscript. After ten years of work, involving the expertise and goodwill of an extraordinary number of people working around the world, the Archimedes Palimpsest Project has released its data. It is a historic dataset, revealing new texts from the ancient world. It is an integrated product, weaving registered images in many wavebands of light with XML transcriptions of the Archimedes and Hyperides texts that are spatially mapped to those images. It has pushed boundaries for the imaging of documents, and relied almost exclusively on current international standards. We hope that this dataset will be a persistent digital resource for the decades to come. We also hope it will be helpful as an example for others who are conducting similar work. It published under a Creative Commons 3.0 attribution license, to ensure ease of access and the potential for widespread use. A complete facsimile of the revealed palimpsested texts is available on Googlebooks as "The Archimedes Palimpsest." It is hoped that this is the first of many uses to which the data will be put.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For information on the Archimedes Palimpsest Project, please visit:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.archimedespalimpsest.org/"&gt;www.archimedespalimpsest.org &lt;/a&gt;&lt;http: org=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For the dataset, please visit:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.archimedespalimpsest.net/"&gt;www.archimedespalimpsest.net &lt;/a&gt;&lt;http: net=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We have set up a discussion forum on the Archimedes Palimpsest Project. Any member can invite anybody else to join. If you want to become a member, please email:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:wnoel@thewalters.org"&gt;wnoel@thewalters.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I would be grateful if you would circulate this to your friends and colleagues.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Thank you very much&lt;br&gt;Will Noel&lt;br&gt;The Walters Art Museum&lt;br&gt;October 29th, 2008.&lt;/http:&gt;&lt;/http:&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;I found it a bit tricky to find the Google Books version of this, so &lt;a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=_zX8OG3QoF4C&amp;amp;pg=PT146&amp;amp;dq=The+Archimedes+Palimpsest&amp;amp;as_brr=1"&gt;here's the link&lt;/a&gt;.</description><category>digclass</category><category>horothesia</category><category>patterns</category><category>publications</category><category>rights</category><category>tei</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/10/digital-archimedes-palimpsest/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2008 22:41:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The DH Stack(s)</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/10/dh-stacks/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Lots of interesting posts in the last couple of days about Digital Humanities skills, software and cyberinfrastructure initiatives:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sean issues some &lt;a href="http://sgillies.net/blog/819/second-guessing-project-bamboo/"&gt;service-oriented caveats for Project Bamboo&lt;/a&gt; and thinks about skillsets for DH-ready graduates&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://digitalscholarship.wordpress.com/2008/10/18/digital-humanities-jobs/"&gt;Lisa surveys recent DH job postings&lt;/a&gt;, muses on DH 'fieldness' and visits the aspiring digital humanist's skillset too&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://digitalhistoryhacks.blogspot.com/"&gt;Bill T.'s whole blog&lt;/a&gt; remains essential reading in this meme-space (e.g., see his recent "&lt;a href="http://digitalhistoryhacks.blogspot.com/2008/10/navigating-digital-history.html"&gt;Navigating Digital History&lt;/a&gt;")&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Liza provides an example of &lt;a href="http://blog.threepress.org/2008/10/14/corpus-toneelkritiek-interbellum/"&gt;TEI+Python+lxml in publishing primary sources online&lt;/a&gt; (the same general stack the Duke/Heidelberg/King's/Columbia/UNC/NYU team has been using in the rework of the Duke Databank of Documentary Papyri and Heidelberger Gesamtverzeichniss -- coming soon)&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>bamboo</category><category>blogs</category><category>digclass</category><category>horothesia</category><category>jobs</category><category>patterns</category><category>tei</category><category>tools</category><category>uptake</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/10/dh-stacks/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2008 19:52:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>First Thousand Years of Greek: Utilities</title><link>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/first-thousand-years-of-greek-utilities/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I recently &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2008/08/first-thousand-years-of-greek.html"&gt;blogged&lt;/a&gt; the announcement of the &lt;abbr title="Center for Hellenic Studies"&gt;CHS&lt;/abbr&gt;-sponsored &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;First Thousand Years of Greek&lt;/span&gt; project. It looks as if &lt;a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/10590621399352493304"&gt;Neel&lt;/a&gt; is beginning to roll out &lt;a href="http://chs75.harvard.edu/projects/diginc/first1kyears"&gt;related code, documentation and information&lt;/a&gt; on the CHS &lt;a style="font-style: italic;" href="http://chs75.harvard.edu/projects/diginc/home"&gt;Digital Incunabula&lt;/a&gt; site.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>digclass</category><category>grc1k</category><category>horothesia</category><category>tei</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://paregorios.org/posts/2008/09/first-thousand-years-of-greek-utilities/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2008 01:54:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>