<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>paregorios.org (Posts about yaks)</title><link>https://paregorios.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://paregorios.org/categories/yaks.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:ipse@paregorios.org"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;&lt;img
alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
property="dct:title"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;paregorios.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by
&lt;a xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" href="https://paregorios.org/me"
property="cc:attributionName" rel="cc:attributionURL"&gt;Tom Elliott&lt;/a&gt; is
licensed under a &lt;a rel="license"
href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 May 2018 12:25:46 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Batch XML validation at the command line</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2014/04/batch-xml-validation-at-command-line/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Updated: 8 August, 2017 to reflect changes in the installation pattern for jing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Against a &lt;a href="http://relaxng.org/"&gt;RelaxNG&lt;/a&gt; schema. I had help figuring this out from &lt;a href="http://philomousos.com/"&gt;Hugh&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://ryanfb.github.io/"&gt;Ryan&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href="http://blogs.library.duke.edu/dcthree/"&gt;DC3&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;$ find &lt;i&gt;{searchpath}&lt;/i&gt; -name "*.xml" -print | parallel --tag jing &lt;i&gt;{relaxngpath}&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;The &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;find&lt;/span&gt; command hunts down all files ending with ".xml" in the directory tree under &lt;i&gt;searchpath&lt;/i&gt;. The &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;parallel&lt;/span&gt; command takes that list of files and fires off (in parallel) a &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;jing&lt;/span&gt; validation run for each of them. The &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;--tag&lt;/span&gt; option passed to &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;jing&lt;/span&gt; ensures we get the name of the file passed through with each error message. This turns out (in general terms as seen by me) to be much faster than running each &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;jing&lt;/span&gt; call in sequence, e.g. with the &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;--exec&lt;/span&gt; primary in &lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;find&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As I'm running on a Mac, I had to install &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/parallel/"&gt;GNU Parallel&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://www.thaiopensource.com/relaxng/jing.html"&gt;Jing RelaxNG Validator&lt;/a&gt;. That's what &lt;a href="http://brew.sh/"&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt; is for:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;&lt;strike&gt;$ brew install jing&lt;/strike&gt;&lt;br&gt;$ brew install jing-trang&lt;br&gt;$ brew install parallel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;NB: you may have to install a down version of Java before you can get the jing-trang formula to work in homebrew (e.g., &lt;span style="font-family: Courier New, Courier, monospace;"&gt;brew install java6&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What's the context, you ask? I have lots of reasons to want to be able to do this. The proximal cause was batch-validating all the &lt;a href="http://epidoc.sf.net/"&gt;EpiDoc&lt;/a&gt; XML files for the inscriptions that are included in the &lt;a href="http://isaw.nyu.edu/publications/inscriptions/campa/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Corpus of Campā Inscriptions&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; before regenerating the site for an update today. I wanted to see quickly if there were any encoding errors in the XML that might blow up the XSL transforms we use to generate the site. So, what I actually ran was: &lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;span style='font-family: "courier new" , "courier" , monospace;'&gt;$ curl -O http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng&lt;br&gt;$ find ./texts/xml -name '*.xml' -print | parallel --tag jing tei-epidoc.rng&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Thanks to everybody who built all these tools!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</description><category>collaboration</category><category>efficiency</category><category>epidoc</category><category>horothesia</category><category>tei</category><category>tools</category><category>validation</category><category>xml</category><category>xslt</category><category>yaks</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2014/04/batch-xml-validation-at-command-line/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 00:07:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>First pass at extracting useful data from my dissertation</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2012/05/first-pass-at-extracting-useful-data/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;You'll find context in &lt;a href="http://horothesia.blogspot.com/2012/05/open-access-epigraphic-evidence-for.html"&gt;yesterday's post on the dissertation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It turns out it wasn't as hard as I anticipated to start getting useful information extracted from my born-digital-for-printing-on-dead-trees dissertation. Here's a not-yet-perfect xml serialization (borrowing tags from the TEI) of "instance" information found in the diss narrative:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/paregorios/demarc/blob/master/xml/instances.xml"&gt;https://github.com/paregorios/demarc/blob/master/xml/instances.xml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Each instance is a historical event (or in some cases event series) relating to boundary demarcation or dispute within the empire. Here's a comparison between the original formatting for paper and the xml.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For paper:&lt;br&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-nu_yP3-852Q/T71bfc35IOI/AAAAAAAAAQE/MTtfTmuT0PQ/s1600/wookie.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left:1em; margin-right:1em"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="390" width="400" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-nu_yP3-852Q/T71bfc35IOI/AAAAAAAAAQE/MTtfTmuT0PQ/s400/wookie.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;br&gt;XML:&lt;br&gt;&lt;pre style="font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; color: #000000; background-color: #eee;font-size: 12px;border: 1px dashed #999999;line-height: 14px;padding: 5px; overflow: auto; width: 100%"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;div type="instance" xml:id="INST9"&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;  &amp;lt;idno type="original"&amp;gt;INST9&amp;lt;/idno&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;  &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;A Negotiated Boundary between the &amp;lt;placeName &lt;br&gt;    type="ancient"&amp;gt;Zamucci&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt; and the &amp;lt;placeName &lt;br&gt;    type="ancient"&amp;gt;Muduciuvi&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;  &amp;lt;p rend="indent"&amp;gt;Burton 2000, no. 78&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Date(s): &amp;lt;date&amp;gt;AD 86&amp;lt;/date&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;  &amp;lt;p type="treDisputeStatement"&amp;gt;This boundary marker was placed in &lt;br&gt;    accordance with the agreement of both parties (&amp;lt;foreign xml:lang="la"&amp;gt;ex &lt;br&gt;    conven/tione utrarumque nationum&amp;lt;/foreign&amp;gt;), and therefore may be taken as&lt;br&gt;    evidence of a &amp;lt;hi rend="bold"&amp;gt;boundary dispute&amp;lt;/hi&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;  &amp;lt;p rend="indent"&amp;gt;This single boundary marker from coastal &amp;lt;placeName &lt;br&gt;    type="modern"&amp;gt;Libya&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt; provides the only evidence for the resolution&lt;br&gt;    of a boundary dispute between these two indigenous peoples. The date of the &lt;br&gt;    demarcation, as calculated from the imperial titulature, places the event in &lt;br&gt;    the same year as the reported ‘destruction’ of the &amp;lt;placeName &lt;br&gt;    type="ancient"&amp;gt;Nasamones&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt; by &amp;lt;placeName type="ancient"&amp;gt;Legio III &lt;br&gt;    Augusta&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt; as a consequence of a tax revolt in which tax collectors &lt;br&gt;    were killed.&amp;lt;note n="286"&amp;gt; Zonaras 11.19. &amp;lt;/note&amp;gt; It is not clear whether &lt;br&gt;    the boundary action was related to the conflict, or merely took advantage of&lt;br&gt;    the temporary presence of the legionary legate in what ought to have been&lt;br&gt;    part of the proconsular province. Surviving documentation for proconsuls&lt;br&gt;    during the 80s AD is incomplete, and therefore we cannot say who was&lt;br&gt;    governing &amp;lt;placeName type="ancient"&amp;gt;Africa Proconsularis &amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt;at the &lt;br&gt;    time of this demarcation.&amp;lt;note n="287"&amp;gt; Thomasson 1996, 45-48. &amp;lt;/note&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;    Neither party seems to have been related to the &amp;lt;placeName &lt;br&gt;    type="ancient"&amp;gt;Nasamones&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt;; rather, they are thought to be sub-&lt;br&gt;    tribes of the &amp;lt;placeName type="ancient"&amp;gt;Macae.&amp;lt;/placeName&amp;gt;&amp;lt;note &lt;br&gt;    n="288"&amp;gt;Mattingly 1994, 27-28, 32, 74, 76.. &amp;lt;/note&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One thing that made this a lot easier than it might of been was the way I used styles in Microsoft Word back when I created the original version of the document. Rather than just painting formatting onto my text for headings, paragraphs, strings of characters, and so forth, I created a custom "style" for each type of thing I wanted to paint (e.g., an "instance heading" or a "personal name"). I associated the desired visual formatting with each of these, but the names themselves (since the captured semantic distinctions that I was interested in) provided hooks today for writing this stuff out as sort-of TEI XML.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's more to do, obviously, but this was a satisfying first step.</description><category>demarc</category><category>horothesia</category><category>openness</category><category>tei</category><category>xml</category><category>xslt</category><category>yaks</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2012/05/first-pass-at-extracting-useful-data/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2012 03:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Give Me the Zotero Item Keys!</title><link>https://paregorios.org/posts/2012/02/give-me-zotero-item-keys/</link><dc:creator>Tom Elliott</dc:creator><description>&lt;i&gt;I fear and hope that this post will cause someone smarter than me to pipe up and say UR DOIN IT WRONG ITZ EZ LYK DIS ...&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Here's the use case:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/"&gt;Integrating Digital Papyrology project&lt;/a&gt; (and friends) have a &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/groups/papyrology"&gt;Zotero group library&lt;/a&gt; populated with 1,445 bibliographic records that were developed on the basis of an old, built-by-hand &lt;a href="http://library.duke.edu/rubenstein/scriptorium/papyrus/texts/clist.html"&gt;Checklist of Editions of Greek and Latin Papyri (etc.)&lt;/a&gt;. A lot of checking and improving was done to the data in Zotero.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Separately, there's now a much larger pile of bibliographic records related to papyrology that were collected (on different criteria) by the &lt;a href="http://www.ulb.ac.be/philo/cpeg/bp.htm"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Bibliographie Papyrologique&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; project. They have been machine-converted (into &lt;a href="http://www.tei-c.org/"&gt;TEI&lt;/a&gt; document fragments) from a &lt;i&gt;sui generis&lt;/i&gt; Filemaker Pro database and are now &lt;a href="http://papyri.info/bibliosearch"&gt;hosted via papyri.info&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="https://github.com/papyri/idp.data/tree/master/Biblio"&gt;the raw data is on github&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There is considerable overlap between these two datasets, but also signifcant divergeance. We want to merge "matching" records in a carefully supervised way, making sure not to lose any of the extra goodness that BP adds to the data but taking full advantage of the corrections and improvements that were done to the Checklist data.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We started by doing an export-to-RDF of the Zotero data and, as a first step, that was banged up (programmatically) against the TEI data on the basis of titles. Probable matches were hand-checked and a resulting pairing of papyri.info bibliographic ID numbers against Zotero short titles was produced. You can see &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/biblio-matching/matches-2012-02.xml"&gt;the resulting XML here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;I should point out that almost everything up to here including the creation and improvement of the data, as well as anything below regarding the bibliography in papyri.info, is the work of others. Those others include Gabriel Bodard, Hugh Cayless, James Cowey, Carmen Lantz, Adam Prins, Josh Sosin, and Jen Thum. And the BP team. And probably others I'm forgetting at the moment or who have labored out of my sight. I erect this shambles of a lean-to on the shoulders of giants.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To guide the work of our bibliographic researchers in analyzing the matched records, I wanted to create an HTML file that looks like this:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace; font-size: small;"&gt;Checklist Short Title = Papyri.info ID number and Full Title String&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace; font-size: x-small;"&gt;BGU 10 = PI idno 7513: Papyrusurkunden aus ptolemäischer Zeit. (Ägyptische Urkunden aus den Staatlichen Museen zu Berlin. Griechische Urkunden. X. Band.)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: 'Courier New', Courier, monospace; font-size: x-small;"&gt;etc.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;In that list, I wanted items to the left to be linked to the online view of the Zotero record at zotero.org and items on the right linked to the online view of the TEI record at papyri.info. The XML data we got from the initial match process provided the papyri.info bibliographic ID numbers, from which it's easy to construct the corresponding URIs, e.g., &lt;a href="http://papyri.info/biblio/7513"&gt;http://papyri.info/biblio/7513&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But Zotero presented a problem. URIs for bibliographic records in Zotero server use alphanumeric "item keys" like this: CJ3WSG3S (as in &lt;a href="https://www.zotero.org/groups/papyrology/items/itemKey/CJ3WSG3S/"&gt;https://www.zotero.org/groups/papyrology/items/itemKey/CJ3WSG3S/&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;That item key string is not, to my knowledge, included in any of the export formats produced by the Zotero desktop client, nor is it surfaced in its interface (argh).&lt;/b&gt; It appears possible to hunt them down programmatically via the &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/support/dev/server_api/read_api"&gt;Zotero Read API&lt;/a&gt;, though I haven't tried it for reasons that will be explained shortly. It is certainly possible to hunt for them manually via the web interface, but I'm not going to try that for more than about 3 records.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;How I got the Zotero item keys&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, I have two choices at this point: write some code to automate hunting the item keys via the Zotero Read API or crack open the Zotero &lt;a href="http://www.sqlite.org/"&gt;SQLLite&lt;/a&gt; database on my local client and see if the item keys are lurking in there too. Since I'm on a newish laptop on which I hadn't yet installed &lt;a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/xcode/id448457090?mt=12"&gt;XCode&lt;/a&gt;, which seems to be a prerequisite to installing support for a &lt;a href="http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0405/"&gt;Python virtual environment&lt;/a&gt;, which is the preferred way to get &lt;a href="http://www.pip-installer.org/en/latest/installing.html"&gt;pip&lt;/a&gt;, which is the preferred install prerequisite for &lt;a href="https://github.com/urschrei/pyzotero"&gt;pyzotero&lt;/a&gt;, which is the python wrapper for the Zotero API, I had to make some choices about which yaks to shave.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I decided to start the (notoriously slow) XCode download yak and then have a go at the SQLLite yak while that was going on.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I grabbed the trial version of &lt;a href="http://www.razorsql.com/"&gt;RazorSQL&lt;/a&gt; (which looked like a good shortcut after a few minutes of Googling), made a copy of my Zotero database, and started poking around. I thought about looking for detailed documentation (&lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/support/zotero_data"&gt;starting here I guess&lt;/a&gt;), but direct inspection started yielding results so I just kept going commando-style. It became clear at once that I wasn't going to find a single table containing my bibliographic entries. The Zotero client database is all normalized and modularized and stuff. So I viewed table columns and table contents as necessary and started building a SQL query to get at what I wanted. Here's what ultimately worked:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;pre style="background-color: #eeeeee; border: 1px dashed #999999; color: black; font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; font-size: 12px; line-height: 14px; overflow: auto; padding: 5px; width: 100%;"&gt;&lt;code&gt;SELECT itemDataValues.value, items.key FROM items &lt;br&gt;INNER JOIN libraries ON items.libraryID = libraries.libraryID&lt;br&gt;INNER JOIN groups ON libraries.libraryID = groups.libraryID&lt;br&gt;INNER JOIN itemData ON items.itemID = itemData.itemID&lt;br&gt;INNER JOIN itemDataValues ON itemData.valueID = itemDataValues.valueID&lt;br&gt;INNER JOIN fields ON itemData.fieldID = fields.fieldID&lt;br&gt;WHERE groups.name= "Papyrology" AND fields.fieldID=116&lt;br&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;The SELECT statement gets me two values for each match dredged up by the rest of the query: a value stored in the itemDataValues table and a key stored in the items table. The various JOINs are used to get us close to the specific value (i.e., a short title) that we want. 116 in the fieldID field of the fields table corresponds to the short title field you see in your Zotero client. I found that out by inspecting the fields table; I could have used more JOINs to be able to use the string "shortTitle" in my WHERE clause, but that would have just taken more time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The results of that query against my database looked like this:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;pre style="background-color: #eeeeee; border: 1px dashed #999999; color: black; font-family: Andale Mono, Lucida Console, Monaco, fixed, monospace; font-size: 12px; line-height: 14px; overflow: auto; padding: 5px; width: 100%;"&gt;&lt;code&gt;P.Cair.Preis.    2245UKTH&lt;br&gt;CPR 18           26K8TAJT&lt;br&gt;P.Bodm. 28       282XKDE9&lt;br&gt;P.Gebelen        29ETKPXC&lt;br&gt;O.Krok           2BBMS7NS&lt;br&gt;P.Carlsb. 5      2D2ZNT4C&lt;br&gt;P.Mich.Aphrod.   2DTD2NIZ&lt;br&gt;P.Carlsb. 9      2FWF6T6I&lt;br&gt;P.Col. 1         2G4CF756&lt;br&gt;P.Lond.Copt. 2   2GAEU5QP&lt;br&gt;P.Harr. 1        2GCCNGJV&lt;br&gt;O.Deir el-Bahari 2GH3FEA2&lt;br&gt;P.Harrauer       2H3T6EU2&lt;br&gt;(etc).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, copy that tabular result out of the RazorSQL GUI, paste it into a new &lt;a href="http://www.libreoffice.org/"&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/a&gt; spreadsheet and save it and I've got &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/biblio-matching/zdump-content.xml"&gt;an XML file&lt;/a&gt; that I can dip into from &lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/biblio-matching/matches2html.xsl"&gt;the XSLT I had already started on&lt;/a&gt; to produce my HTML view.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://idp.atlantides.org/biblio-matching/matches-2012-02.html"&gt;Here's the resulting HTML file&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;On we go.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;Oh, and for those paying attention to such things, XCode finished downloading about two-thirds of the way through this process ...&lt;/i&gt;</description><category>bibliography</category><category>horothesia</category><category>papyrology</category><category>tei</category><category>xml</category><category>xslt</category><category>yaks</category><category>zotero</category><guid>https://paregorios.org/posts/2012/02/give-me-zotero-item-keys/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2012 04:04:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>